<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leziak.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://leziak.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-13T13:12:14+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leziak.com</title><subtitle>Articles about technology, photography, art, writing and games</subtitle><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><entry><title type="html">Life is Strange photo wall (Max Caulfield memorial wall)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-photo-wall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is Strange photo wall (Max Caulfield memorial wall)" /><published>2020-01-29T16:57:25+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-29T16:57:25+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-photo-wall</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-photo-wall/">&lt;p&gt;One of the things that enchanted me in &lt;em&gt;Life is Strange&lt;/em&gt; was Max Caulfield photo memorial wall at Blackwell Academy. It was one of those small details that made me fall in love with this game, contributing to its unique atmosphere. The Polaroid wall in Max’s dorm room allows player to not only appreciate her photography skills, but also learn more about her personality. In some way it also reflects Max’s decisions, especially the ones made at the beginning of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since my first playthrough of the game, I’ve been thinking about recreating Max’s photo wall at home. The opportunity for that appeared in August 2019, when I was doing a renovation of my home office. I decided to dedicate a whole wall to &lt;em&gt;Life is Strange&lt;/em&gt;. I want to share the final result with you, along with a small DIY tutorial on how to make Max photo wall that will look as similar to the in-game version as possible. &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-dark-office.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-dark-office-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-dark-office&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The recreation of Max Caulfield photo memorial wall in my home office at night…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day-office.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day-office-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day-office&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;… and during the day.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many variants of Life is Strange Polaroid wall that one can recreate at home, depending on available space, materials, desired aesthetics, budget, etc. Please keep in mind that below you’ll find only one of many possibilities. I encourage you to be creative and simply have fun with it – there is no bad way of making a photo wall and perhaps you’ll come up with your own ideas on how to make something work in a better way than described below. If you have any questions, do not hesitate to contact me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-photo-wall-inspired-by-life-is-strange&quot;&gt;My photo wall inspired by Life is Strange&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Max Caulfield photo wall consists of 76 prints of various moments from both &lt;em&gt;Life is Strange&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Before the Storm&lt;/em&gt;. Some of them are the exact optional photographs that Max can take in the game, while others are cropped from screen shots or cut scenes.  All pictures match the size of a classic Polaroid film Max has been using throughout the game and are printed on a thick, high quality paper. While Max’s Polaroid wall at Blackwell is organic in its nature (i.e. photographs are not perfectly aligned with each other, nor are they group thematically), I aimed for a more organised look that would be pleasant even for a person not familiar with the original composition. That’s why I decided to make a few “thematic zones” referring to different characters, locations or events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-pricefield-1-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-pricefield-1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-pricefield-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-pricefield&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;My Life is Strange photo wall is loosely divided into several thematic zones. Here you can see the central part of the composition, devoted to Max and Chloe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most difficult thing was, by far, to obtain proper lights for the photo wall. Recreating the exact composition of Polaroids from the game was not a priority for me, but I wanted to have lighting matching the original one as close as possible. The vast majority of lanterns available online is way too small in diameter (and there are not that many types resembling Max’s lights to begin with). It took me a few hours of googling, plus help of my friends from Twitter, to find a &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; model of lights similar to the ones that Max used at Blackwell. Still, they are not an exact match (they are made from polyester, not paper like the ones in the game). But on the other hand they use warm LED lights, so they have low energy consumption and don’t warm up too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see that my Life is Strange photo wall has two additions. The first one is a fine art print of Chloe and the mysterious raven from &lt;em&gt;Before the Storm&lt;/em&gt;. It was one of the first artworks I bought after playing &lt;em&gt;Life is Strange&lt;/em&gt; for the first time. In fact, I ordered it even before I finished &lt;em&gt;Before the Storm&lt;/em&gt;, so at that moment I wasn’t quite sure about the role that raven was supposed to play in the events of the game. The second one, presenting one of my favourite scenes from the original game, is in fact a postcard. I decided to add it to the wall not only for the graphic on the front, but, most importantly, because of the message at the back from my dear friend (who is also a fan of &lt;em&gt;Life is Strange&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I decided to add some extra things to my Life is Strange photo wall: a fine art print of Chloe and the raven and a postcard depicting one of my favourite moments from the original game. Together they create a centrepiece that viewer’s eyes naturally gravitate to.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole Max Caulfield photo memorial wall is situated at the wall opposite to my desk, so all I have to do when I’m working is to lean to the side a bit, to see it behind my computer screen, at the far end of the room. During the daytime the lights are unplugged, but in the evening they turn my home office into a location taken out from Arcadia Bay. They also work perfectly as a mean to reduce contrast between bright computer screen and the background, when the ceiling lights are turned off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-make-your-own-life-is-strange-photo-wall&quot;&gt;How to make your own Life is Strange photo wall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to create your own Polaroid wall, I have some good news for you: the whole process is actually much simpler than one could think and doesn’t require any tools, although spirit level is recommended for the best effect. If you have all materials at hand and have already planned the layout, you can make your own photo memorial wall in one afternoon (of course, depending on the size of the wall and complexity of your project).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shopping list – what you are going to need:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Polaroids or print-outs made on a thick, stiff paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;chain of paper lanterns or other similar lights&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adhesive putty (recommended) or double-sided adhesive tape (not recommended)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;spirit level&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;long ruler (optional)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s talk about each of these items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroids-or-prints&quot;&gt;Life is Strange Polaroids or prints&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They will be the core element of your decoration, so you have to make sure they are of a good quality and all have correct size (any variations in terms of height or width will result in misalignment of neighbouring pictures). The thicker, sturdier the paper they have been printed on, the better, because it is less likely to get bent or damaged when placing the decoration, rearranging pictures or taking them down. You can either print them yourself (naturally, you need to prepare all graphics first) or purchase them online. I bought all my Life is Strange Polaroids from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/TheRewindClub&quot;&gt;The Rewind Club&lt;/a&gt; on Etsy and I wholeheartedly recommend you that store. They have a wide selection of Polaroids and other merchandise from &lt;em&gt;Life is Strange&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Before The Storm&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Life is Strange 2&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lights&quot;&gt;Lights&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the most difficult item to get right. On the contrary to what one could think, it is very hard to find the exact chain of paper lanterns that Max had in her room at Blackwell, both in terms of size and appearance&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Most of the lanterns I checked were either too small or didn’t have paper covers. I really wanted to have lighting as close to the original as possible, and in the end I was ready to assemble them myself, buying empty paper lanterns and generic lights separately. Luckily, my friends recommended me an excellent set that looks almost identical to lights used for Max’s photo wall. I’m talking about &lt;strong&gt;Lunar Lantern Lights&lt;/strong&gt; produced by Lights4fun. These are LED lights certified for  both indoor and outdoor use. They come in warm white flavour, which is perfect for my purposes and are easy to set up. There are ten lanterns in one set, but you can connect multiple sets together, creating longer chains. The main difference between these and Max’s lanterns is, their covers are made of polyester, not paper. It makes them refract light in a slightly different way (the glow coming from Lunar Lantern Lights is more pearly, while the one from normal paper lanterns is rather matt). For me, personally, it does not matter in the slightest. Additionally, polyester covers are far more durable and they don’t get dirty easily. The whole set is waterproof, so you can even clean it with water or wet cloth if needed, just remember to keep the plug dry. I found these lamps &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B01ANZR3RO&quot;&gt;on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;, however you might be able to get these (or something similar) at your local store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lunar-lantern-lights-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lunar-lantern-lights&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-vertical&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-vertical-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-vertical&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Lunar Lantern Lights used in my installation have polyester covers instead of paper ones, which results in a more pearly, satin glow.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adhesive-material&quot;&gt;Adhesive material&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the way you’ll want to mount your Polaroids, you are going to need some sort of adhesive to stick them to the wall. I strongly recommend using &lt;strong&gt;adhesive putty&lt;/strong&gt; for the best effect, since it will not damage the paint on the wall or the prints themselves when taking the decoration down. You can shape it into any way you want, it is perfect for holding such light objects like prints or Polaroids against a wall. It also allows for corrections after placing the picture, either by moving it slightly when adhered to the wall, or replacing it entirely in new location. For my Life is Strange photo wall I used &lt;strong&gt;Faber-Castell Tack-It&lt;/strong&gt; adhesive putty bought &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Faber-Castell-Reusable-Removable-Adhesive-Multipurpose/dp/B075QDRJWZ&quot;&gt;on Amazon&lt;/a&gt;, but you can pick whatever brand you want, since they all have virtually the same properties and usability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-adhesive-putty-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-adhesive-putty&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I used Faber-Castell Tack-It adhesive putty to mount Polaroids on the wall, although you can choose from a multitude of other options.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another option is a &lt;strong&gt;double-sided adhesive tape&lt;/strong&gt;. It is cheaper and easier to find in stores, and it offers much stronger connection between the Polaroid and the wall. The problem is, double-sided tape is so strong, it will almost certainly peel off some wall paint when you will try to take the decoration down eventually, not to mention ruining the prints as well (i.e. tearing or delaminating their backs). It also glues both surfaces instantly, so you have only one try to align each print in the correct way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can mount a set of cords stretching from wall to wall and attach prints to these cords using clothes pegs. In that way the wall behind will remain intact, but on the other hand you’ll have to find a way of hooking the cords to opposite walls, which might require some drilling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spirit-level&quot;&gt;Spirit level&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe this part is self-explanatory. The use of a spirit level will depend on the aesthetics you aim for when creating your own Polaroid wall. If you are a fan of neat, organised compositions, spirit level will make it much, much easier to create a levelled, straight layout, with equal intervals between prints. Generally speaking, the longer the spirit level, the better, because you can control your level for more than a single Polaroid at the time (you can also mark vertical and horizontal intervals directly on your level with a pencil). I’ve been using a regular, 50-centimetre long spirit level I bought years ago, but you can also use a laser line level (although it will not be as comfortable to use in this particular case as an old school spirit level). Of course if you desire to get a more organic appearance of your photo wall and you don’t want (or need) to keep all photographs perfectly aligned, you can just eyeball the level of each row of prints. That, while not neat and perfect, would create a look more resembling the original Polaroid wall seen in &lt;em&gt;Life is Strange&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;long-ruler&quot;&gt;Long ruler&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you decide not to use a spirit level (or you are using a laser line level instead) but still want to keep equal spacing between Polaroids, you are going to need something to mark the correct interval, both horizontally and vertically. For that you can use a plain ruler (again, the longer ones would be more convenient), or a long strip of a cardboard, etc. Basically anything that would allow you to measure and mark a distance and that could be placed conveniently at the wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-step-by-step&quot;&gt;Making Life is Strange Polaroid wall step by step&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-plan-your-photo-wall&quot;&gt;1. Plan your photo wall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you grab your tools and start putting Polaroids on the wall, you should plan the whole thing and visualise your desired composition. First of all, you need to know how much space do you have available for the decorations and how many photos you want to fit on that space. If you want to incorporate other elements (like the fine art print or the postcard in my case) you need to include them in your plan as well. You can either draw the whole thing or take a picture of a wall and annotate it digitally (see my example below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-layout-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-layout&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You should plan the entire layout of your photo wall beforehand. The main limiting factor for positioning the lanterns may be the length of the cable available.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend you start outlining your composition with placement of the lights. Please keep in mind that one of the factors limiting your layout might be the length of a cable connecting neighbouring lanterns. You need to plan where to place each lantern in a sequence as not to exceed the cable length available to you. Of course the type of lighting will also determine your composition. For example, you might opt for a bare lightbulbs instead of LED lights in paper lanterns. In that case your lights would have a different diameter, which would have to be accounted for in the planning stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A tip:&lt;/strong&gt; you can achieve best results in terms of aesthetics when designing an asymmetrical lighting layout. Try to avoid placing lanterns in a predictable way, at regular intervals, etc. If you are still unsure about it, remember that Max Caulfield photo memorial wall was not symmetrical either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When planning the layout of your photo wall you have many various options, depending on your personal preferences. You can sort or group them in rows or columns thematically by characters, location, the game they are from, etc. You can also arrange them in zones (i.e. group together Blackwell students, adult characters) or place them chronologically, to reflect the progress of the story. A good idea is to group Polaroids with the same/similar dominating colours, so they can create a mosaic of some sort on your wall. You can also embrace the chaos and place them randomly or semi-randomly. Whatever works for you best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more thing: when planning your photo wall you should know whether it will be a finished composition or you are going to add some elements later. This will dictate how you are going to place lanterns and other elements (i.e. it may be necessary to put a lantern outside of your current composition, so it would provide enough light to the extension in the future). Always plan for the final version, even if it means that for the time being a part of your Polaroid wall might look unfinished. It will save you much time in the future, keeping you from rearranging the entire thing from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-choose-and-collect-all-required-elements-and-tools&quot;&gt;2. Choose and collect all required elements and tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the whole thing outlined, you can start gathering all the decorations, lighting and other items necessary to finish the composition. If buying Polaroids online make sure that they are of a correct size and printed on a good-enough paper. Check the technical requirements for the lights (my lanterns were only available with a UK plug, so I had to buy an adequate adapter for EU sockets beforehand). Get an adhesive putty and try it out at some hidden part of your wall to make sure it does not damage it and can be easily removed. Collect your tools, if you need any. Check the batteries in a laser line level, if you use one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-prepare-your-working-place&quot;&gt;3. Prepare your working place&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get yourself some flat surface (a desk, coffee table, couch, etc.) that is big enough to lay out all the Polaroids that will be placed on your wall. Then, using your notes and plan from the first step, recreate the entire composition. Don’t worry about spacing, photos can overlay each other. You only have to make sure that they are sorted correctly (i.e. which photos will be put next to which ones in neighbouring rows/columns). &lt;strong&gt;Double check everything.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s easier to make some corrections now rather than to rearrange Polaroids when they are already on the wall. At this stage you may also see that some photos do not work well next to each other, so it is a good moment to make some final rearrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-layout-2-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-layout-2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;To make everything go smoothly recreate your desired composition on a flat surface, like a desk or coffee table, remembering to leave empty space for lanterns or other objects. It will give you an easy reference when transferring your idea onto a wall.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-start-placing-your-first-row-of-photos-at-the-wall&quot;&gt;4. Start placing your first row of photos at the wall&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although you can place Polaroids either by rows or by columns, I strongly recommend the former, because it is much easier to check if everything is levelled and spaced correctly. The first row of pictures is the most important one and it has to be placed precisely, because you are going to use it as a reference for the next ones. In order to minimise errors and inaccuracies, it is best to start with a middle row of a composition rather than the top or bottom one. You can use a spirit level or a ruler to mark the exact interval required in your composition, therefore placing next Polaroids will be easier. &lt;strong&gt;Always believe what the spirit level shows you, not your own eyes.&lt;/strong&gt; I cannot stress that enough. If you are 100% sure that the Polaroid is not placed straight, but the spirit level shows you that it is, it is in fact straight. If you are working on a big repetitive pattern (like a grid of Polaroids on a wall) it is ridiculously easy to lost a sense of true level, because our brain will naturally switch to using existing Polaroids placed in a row as a reference for the true level. I was using a spirit level and still, I skew the right third of the layout upward, because I listened to the sense of level perceived with my eyes and not to what the spirit level showed me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-making-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-making&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You should do your best to place the first row as precisely as possible (you can use a spirit level to check of the Polaroids are straight). It will allow you to work quicker when expanding your composition to the next rows.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember to leave empty space where you want to place your lights!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using an adhesive putty, you can place two small pieces of it about 1 centimetre (half of an inch) from the top and bottom edges of the picture, along its centreline. They shouldn’t be too thin, otherwise it would be difficult to scrap them from the wall if they stick. They do, however, need to be relatively flat, as not to cause visible bulge in the print when you press it against the wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-adhesive-putty-2-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-adhesive-putty-2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;One piece of adhesive putty is enough to mount a single print on the wall. Just tear it in half and place both pieces near the top and the bottom of a Polaroid, along the centreline. Make sure to flatten the adhesive putty a bit, although don’t make it too thin.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-extend-your-polaroid-wall-from-the-first-row-upwards-and-downwards&quot;&gt;5. Extend your Polaroid wall from the first row upwards and downwards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After successfully placing the first row (and checking several times that it is, in fact, level) you can start expanding your Polaroid wall by adding next rows, starting right above and below the first one and then proceeding outwards. At this stage, if you were precise with the first row, you don’t need to keep the spacing between Polaroids (you can follow the spacing of the original row using a level or a ruler), but you need to carefully check if every new Polaroid is straight. A good idea is to, every couple of Polaroids placed, take a few steps back and look at the wall as a whole from the distance. It will help you to detect potential problems, like some photos being rotated, rows (or parts of them) being skewed, or some photos not mixing very well aesthetically. Don’t be afraid to make necessary adjustments, but also remember that you still have your original layout you are trying to recreate, so you need to be aware of all the deviations you’ve made since the beginning of the work. When you are done check all Polaroids to make sure they are attached securely to the wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-prepare-the-lighting&quot;&gt;6. Prepare the lighting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assemble the lanterns according to the user’s manual provided with the product. Plug them in to check if they work correctly and there are no dangerous anomalies (smoke, overheating, etc.). If everything is fine, unplug them and start placing lanterns at the reserved spots on the wall. Lunar Lantern Lights are very light, so I had no problem mounting them with the same adhesive putty I used for the Polaroids. You just need to remember to place adhesive on cables above the lanterns themselves, in a way that would allow them to hang in the correct position. You may need to use two of three pieces of adhesive for every mounting point to achieve best results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-3-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;When mounting the lights, remember to place adhesive putty on the cables above the lanterns, so the lanterns hang in the correct position on the wall. You may want to combine two or three pieces of adhesive putty to ensure the mounting is stable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;7-enjoy-your-own-max-caulfield-photo-memorial-wall&quot;&gt;7. Enjoy your own Max Caulfield photo memorial wall!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well done! You did a great job and now you can enjoy your own piece of Arcadia Bay at home 🦋 If you found this tutorial useful, please don’t forget to reach out to me &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitter.com/kamilleziak&quot;&gt;on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, I would love to see a picture of your creation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;At least in Europe. Maybe it’s easier in North America. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Technically, you don’t need to leave empty space for lights, but by doing so you will avoid a situation in which some pictures are permanently obscured by lanterns. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="polaroid" /><category term="photography" /><category term="blackwellacademy" /><category term="decorations" /><category term="tutorial" /><category term="diy" /><summary type="html">One of the things that enchanted me in Life is Strange was Max Caulfield photo memorial wall at Blackwell Academy. It was one of those small details that made me fall in love with this game, contributing to its unique atmosphere. The Polaroid wall in Max’s dorm room allows player to not only appreciate her photography skills, but also learn more about her personality. In some way it also reflects Max’s decisions, especially the ones made at the beginning of the game. Ever since my first playthrough of the game, I’ve been thinking about recreating Max’s photo wall at home. The opportunity for that appeared in August 2019, when I was doing a renovation of my home office. I decided to dedicate a whole wall to Life is Strange. I want to share the final result with you, along with a small DIY tutorial on how to make Max photo wall that will look as similar to the in-game version as possible.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Catra and Adora (Catradora artwork from She-Ra)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/catra-and-adora-artwork-from-she-ra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Catra and Adora (Catradora artwork from She-Ra)" /><published>2020-01-13T18:46:25+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-13T18:46:25+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/catra-and-adora</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/catra-and-adora-artwork-from-she-ra/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/Catra_and_Adora_wm_740px.png&quot; alt=&quot;catra-and-adora-artwork-from-she-ra&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the awesome recommendation of my friend, I’ve started watching She-Ra and the Princesses of Power on Netflix recently. I immediately fell in love with the main characters, Adora and Catra. Which means that my first artwork of 2020 is this Catradora piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was drawn in Procreate (which is an excellent program by the way).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a bigger version click &lt;a href=&quot;../images/Catra-and-Adora-wm_resized.png&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="art" /><category term="catra" /><category term="adora" /><category term="she-ra" /><category term="catradora" /><category term="drawing" /><category term="digitalart" /><category term="procreate" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy New Year 2020</title><link href="https://leziak.com/happy-new-year-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy New Year 2020" /><published>2020-01-01T11:13:34+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-01T11:13:34+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/happy-new-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/happy-new-year-2020/">&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this special day, I want to wish you every success for the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Click on the picture to see a full-sized version&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-neil-gaiman-new-year-wishes.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/life-is-strange-neil-gaiman-new-year-wishes-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;life-is-strange-neil-gaiman-new-year-wishes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="neilgaiman" /><category term="personal" /><category term="website" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life is Strange comic book vol. 7 (Waves #3)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-7/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is Strange comic book vol. 7 (Waves #3)" /><published>2019-07-30T15:21:31+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-30T15:21:31+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-7/">&lt;p&gt;The previous issue of Life is Strange comic book has been, in my opinion, the best one yet. It was the first issue that I thoroughly enjoyed. Will the seventh one live up to its predecessor? Let’s find out! &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I’m pretty sure that you have already read (or at least looked at) my articles about all the previous issues of Life is Strange comic book, but if you didn’t (or if you simply want to refresh your memory), you can find all of them under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://leziak.com/tags/liscomicbook/&quot;&gt;#liscomicbook&lt;/a&gt; hashtag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover of issue #7 (the third one in Waves story arc) is pretty simple yet interesting. We can see Max standing in front of a shop window. Next to her reflection there is a reflection of the mysterious guy wearing black, the one that we know from the two last issues. But he is only visible through a reflection, he doesn’t occupy the same physical space as Max. It instantly reminded me of the cover made for the first issue of the comic comic book, the one in which Chloe was next to Max, but her reflection was missing. Is this a sign that the sad guy and Max do not belong to the same timeline or reality? Or maybe &lt;em&gt;neither&lt;/em&gt; of them belongs to the reality in which they have met?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very skeptical about introducing new original characters into the stories with a well-established set of characters. In this situation I still cannot make myself like this guy, even despite the fact that apparently he will play some crucial role in Waves, otherwise he wouldn’t be featured on the cover. Because this is second-to-last issue, I’m hoping to get some new information about him and why Max can see him even if others can’t (or can only for a brief time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-cover-7.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-6&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The cover if issue #7 of Life is Strange comic book reminds us that there is more than one reality and not everything is visible for everyone&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first scene in this issue shows some shady dealings in the dark alley made at night. Turns out it’s a retrospection showing a little backstory to the sad emo guy’s character. He and his friend were trying to make a deal with some drug dealers but things went wrong. The sad guy – Tristan as it turns out –  disappeared and his best friend got killed. The scene moved us to the girls’ apartment, where Tristan was telling his story to Max in her room. It looks like his powers allow him to become invisible. He uses them to survive on the street, although when Max points out it’s technically stealing, he says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I survive. I take what I need. Only what I need.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it does not lessen his crimes, it is a bit similar to what Max does in her current timeline. She just survives. While she wants to give Chloe happiness (even if it means seeing her with Rachel as her girlfriend), she, for herself, only wants a bare minimum to remain functional. She does not have ambitions, dreams, hopes (beside seeing Chloe happy). She is only a shadow of her former self. She only wants to survive and that’s what she and Tristan have in common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Tristan mentioned that his parents are the reason why he lives on the street, they have always considered him a black sheep. It is weirdly familiar to another person who, as we know, was not accepted by his parents, or at least by his father (yep, I’m talking about Nathan Prescott). Although being unaccepted by parents is where the similarities end. As far as I know, Tristan didn’t try to kill anyone or didn’t drug anyone (but we still don’t know his full story).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few hours later Chloe and Rachel arrive. They banter playfully while Rachel tries to convince Max to go to the party her friends throw. Both girls talk about Rachel’s nearing performance on the East Coast which brings some new informations. Apparently Rachel is trying to take Chloe with her, so they won’t be separated for the six-month-long tour. I didn’t know about it and if it happens, Max will be completely abandoned and even more unhappy than she is now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But anyway, when Rachel knocks on the door to Max’s room, brunette emerges after a while, introducing Tristan to Chloe and Rachel. That scene was awesome (and hilarious). The look on Chloe’s face when she realised Max was not alone in there was gold! And I love how Chloe’s temper got better of her and she started saying something, before Rachel stopped her in a rather unsophisticated way. It was perfect, showing both Rachel’s and Chloe’s personalities in a realistic way, consistent with Life is Strange and Before the Storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-max-tristan-meeting.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-max-tristan-meeting&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The surprised look visible on Chloe’s face when she realised her shy, socially awkward best friend has been socialising with a stranger, was priceless (no pun intended)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looked like Max and Tristan reached some sort of understanding. Max discovered why sometimes she was the only person to see him and he learned about her and her time-travel powers. That was interesting and, actually, not a bad start. Once I learned more about him he didn’t bother me that much in the story. Besides, his appearance in the girls’ apartment resulted in an interesting situation for Max, who was demanded by Chloe and Rachel to explain what he was doing there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max told them that both her and Tristan needed some help, needed to talk, so they had helped each other. Of course this didn’t settle too well with Chloe who only the previous day was trying to convince Max to trust her, to share her burden. And she failed. Max tried to explain it, but I’m not sure it made the situation any better when she talked to Chloe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I know this will make no sense to you, and I wish I could explain it, but… sometimes there are things that are easier to share with a stranger than with people you love.”&lt;br /&gt;
“You are right, Max… it makes no sense to me…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That scene was written and drawn awesomely! Especially the anger, the betrayed trust that was clearly visible in Chloe’s eyes made it so emotional. It was the second time Life is Strange comic book has surprised me in a very positive way. Introducing this new dynamics between Max and Chloe in the previous issue, and now complicating it further with the fact that Max was more willing to tell her secrets to a total stranger than her best friend, it made me hope that the rest of Waves will focus on Max and Chloe and their relationship (unfortunately, only as friends in this timeline).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At last, Max, Chloe and Rachel arrived to the party that Rachel’s friends (if we can use that word referring to acquaintances and social media influencers she knows) organised. I must say, it was amazeballs to see the girls in their evening attires (I don’t think Max has ever appeared in a party dress before, both in the game and comic books), although the party was a festival of cliche and superficiality (but it only made our girls to stand out even better). There was a beautiful and nostalgic scene in which Max and Chloe reflected on how they both have changed since childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-party-max-chloe-memories.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-party-max-chloe-memories&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;We played hide and seek in waterfalls… we were younger…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime Tristan (who has been invited to the party by Max) decided he didn’t want to be anywhere near that place, invisible or not. He luckily found an abandoned backpack on the street, in which there was some food… and drugs… and a gun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then, at the party, all hell broke lose. It turned out that Callie, the girl who organised all of this, OD’d. Max took her phone and ran out of the building and into the street to get better signal… and then she witnessed how the drug dealers from Tristan’s story were aiming at him with a gun, blaming him and his deceased friend for the arrest of one of their own. The issue finished with a gunshot, although we can’t see what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seventh issue of Life is Strange comic book was… interesting. Intriguing. And it left me wanting to see more. It wasn’t as good as the previous one (which, again, was so great because it focused on Max entirely) but it was still good. The biggest positive surprise (that I still can’t quite explain) is that Tristan’s story did not bother me as much as I expected. It wasn’t cheesy, it wasn’t over-empathised, it was okay. And knowing his story and his relation to Max made me look at him with a little more sympathy (which does &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; mean that I think he should be featured on the cover as one of the main characters).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will still hold myself with complementing Waves until I see the conclusion to this story arc presented in issue #8. It all depends on how the story will finish (or, it will rather not finish &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;, it will certainly end with some cliffhanger and life-changing event that will set the tone for the third story arc). Both this and the previous issue were enjoyable for me, due to the fact we had much more Max and Chloe screen time than in Waves #1. Although it still hurts me to see that we do not have any realistic chance for Pricefield in this story arc (and probably not in the next one either, if it depicts the events during Rachel’s performances on East Coast). Having said that, there are noticeable improvements to the writing in comparison to Dust and graphics are always on the best level. I recommend reading this issue regardless of your favourite ship or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=One%20True%20Pairing&quot;&gt;OTP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yay&quot;&gt;Yay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;focused on Max and Chloe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we’ve learned about the mysterious guy and his story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;scene when Chloe and Rachel discover Max and Tristan&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Max and Chloe’s talk at the party&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chloe’s facial expressions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nay&quot;&gt;Nay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;drugs, drugs, drugs!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rachel and Chloe’s playful banter in their apartment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the possibility of Chloe going to the East Coast with Rachel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tristan’s encounter with the drug dealers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the party&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overall-summary-in-three-words&quot;&gt;Overall summary in three words&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;interesting, multidimensional, enjoyable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="comicbooks" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="chloeprice" /><category term="rachelamber" /><category term="arcadiabay" /><category term="series" /><category term="review" /><category term="recap" /><category term="liscomicbook" /><summary type="html">The previous issue of Life is Strange comic book has been, in my opinion, the best one yet. It was the first issue that I thoroughly enjoyed. Will the seventh one live up to its predecessor? Let’s find out!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life is Strange comic book vol. 6 (Waves #2)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-6/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is Strange comic book vol. 6 (Waves #2)" /><published>2019-07-29T10:02:36+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-29T10:02:36+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-6/">&lt;p&gt;The new arc of Life is Strange comic book shows Max’s life after she had left her original timeline and looked for the one in which she could give Chloe happiness she deserved. It’s been two years since Max made her choice but she still struggles to accept it. Did she choose right? &lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article describes the second issue of Waves, the story arc that is supposed to provide us with a continuation to the plot described in the first four issues. You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-5&quot;&gt;read my review&lt;/a&gt; of the first issue of Waves or &lt;a href=&quot;https://leziak.com/tags/liscomicbook/&quot;&gt;look at all my articles&lt;/a&gt; about Life is Strange comic book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One look at the cover of the sixth issue gives us a hint of what we can expect. In the foreground we can see Max who has dreamy look, focused on something beyond the picture. Then there’s Chloe and Rachel, both girls appear to stare in the same direction. There are some palm trees in the background, indicating that we are still in Santa Monica. In the contrast to the cover of issue 5, showing Max with blue skin (like if she had jumped straight from Cameron’s &lt;em&gt;Avatar&lt;/em&gt;), this cover is plain, ordinary looking (but not in a bad way). I wonder whether Max looks (or imagines) at Chloe she left behind in the other timeline. Maybe she contemplates her choice made in Arcadia Bay?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-cover-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-6&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The cover of issue 6 is more vanilla than the previous one. I’d say it’s the most ordinary looking cover we’ve seen so far (which is not necessary a bad thing)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue begins with Chloe working in the workshop on her first commissioned sculpture. It is a very satisfying scene, it fits Chloe so well. The glow in her eyes visible when she works on the sculpture shows that she does something she is really proud of, something that gives her joy. The whole setting, welding machine, various tools, scraps, etc. remind me of the American Rust. This new Chloe resembles the old one, left in Arcadia Bay, in more ways than one could think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we can see Rachel talking to Max. I know I’ll repeat myself, but I love how Max changed her choice of clothes since the original Life is Strange. Gone are grey hoodies, now she wears more vibrant clothes, clothes that – in my opinion – suit her &lt;em&gt;so well&lt;/em&gt;. Rachel confesses to Max that she can see how Chloe changed, and that she changed for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Hm… So what changed?”&lt;br /&gt;
“Honestly? … Chloe. It sounds corny, but… Chloe’s so real, you know? She calls my bullshit in a way no one else wold dare. She grounds me.”&lt;br /&gt;
“Like… an anchor?”&lt;br /&gt;
“Oh my god, yes! Yes, she’s like n anchor. In the best way. Tethers me to life. Makes me want to do it better.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something very uplifting. Knowing that Chloe has a positive influence on Rachel. It means that Chloe herself is in a stable, happy mindset. She is happy enough not only to enjoy her life and what it offers, but also to be a guiding light, be an anchor to someone else. This shows how huge potential Chloe has in every timeline. She is capable of doing great things, of being great person, of inspiring others. And this is hella awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weirder part of the conversation begins when Rachel admits that she felt threatened by Max when she appeared in Rachel’s and Chloe’s lives two years ago. While it is understandable that Rachel perceived Max as a potential threat due to the fact that she used to be Chloe’s best friend – even before Rachel met the blue-haired punk – it is also strange, considering how confident Rachel was. The discussion quickly turned into Max’s expiation for abandoning Chloe for five years; which was interrupted when both girls, being in the grocery store, noticed the sad guy in black from the previous issue. The guy left the shop without paying for his food (it might’ve already become his habit?) but it looked like only Max had noticed it. She decided to pursue him, leaving Rachel with their groceries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was one of the most dynamic scenes in the whole Life is Strange comic book. I didn’t know Max would be so determined to discover the secret of that guy. There was one thing that was especially interesting: &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; people could see that guy, at least &lt;em&gt;sometimes&lt;/em&gt;, so it looked like he was not a part of another timeline (like Dana or Warren in Dust).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-max-tristan-running.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-max-tristan-running&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Max is desperate to discover the secret of the emo guy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Max thought that she had lost him, he approached her himself, asking why she was following him. And… his nose was bleeding. This is a strong indication that he has some sort of powers but does he have a time-travelling powers like Max? Or maybe he can move freely between realities/timelines? Max didn’t get much information from him, except from &lt;em&gt;“Stay the hell away from me!”&lt;/em&gt; Well, we are only halfway through Waves story arc, so I think it’s quite possible that some new informations about that mysterious guy will be revealed in the two last issues (or it will all end up with a cliffhanger, like Dust did).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next scene we are moved to the girls’ apartment, in which both Chloe and Rachel show that they are worried about Max and want to know the reason for her strange behaviour. While Chloe saw that boy in the coffee shop and Rachel in the grocery store, they don’t know that there is another reason why Max was so insistent on finding the truth about him. She still hasn’t shared her secret, how it happened that she suddenly appeared in L.A. two years ago. Instead, Max tries to give the girls subtle hints that there might be something strange at play here, but she ends up frustrated that she can’t tell them the truth. She finally bursts out, crying that there are things she can’t tell them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-max-frustrated.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-max-frustrated&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Max believed this is the reality she belongs to, but she still can’t forget about the other life, the other Chloe, timelines she crossed. She can’t share her thoughts with Chloe and Rachel which results in frustration and sense of being lost&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, this is one of few things that made me truly enjoy this issue of Life is Strange comic book. Previously we had a lot of focus on Chloe and Rachel, their relationship and problems (especially in the context of Rachel’s coming performances on the East Coast). Max was somehow lost in it. It was plainly visible in the fifth issue that she was thirdwheeling Amberprice so much. In this issue Max finally raises to the role of the main character, this issue is Max-centric, and that’s what distinguishes it from the previous ones, making it special and – in my personal opinion – much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When on the next day Rachel and Chloe discussed Max’s behaviour, there was some very important dialogue that I believe will have huge implications on Max’s future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;”Did she ever lose it like that… you know, before?”&lt;br /&gt;
”No. I’ve never seen her like that, Rach. Freaked me the hell out. (…) That girl that went crazy last night? Im not sure I knew her very well  either. ”&lt;br /&gt;
”Huh? What do you mean?”&lt;br /&gt;
”It’ll sounds [sic] nuts, but… sometimes it’s almost like she’s a different person. (…) sometimes… I’m not sure the Max I knew ever entirely came back.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know this might be just a way of showing how much the events of Life is Strange, the final choice, changing timelines and witnessing flickers between the timelines has changed Max. But knowing how symbolic Life is Strange always was, it may also mean that this is not the timeline this particular Max belongs to. She might have made a wrong choice when she was in the Transect. She chose a wrong timeline again. And while this timeline does not try to actively get rid of her, it might be that she will eventually have to find her happiness elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-chloe-worried-about-max.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-chloe-worried-about-max&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This is so powerful scene… Chloe realises that live wasn’t as easy for Max as she might’ve initially thought…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue of the comic book nails it when it comes to showing both Max’s emotional turmoil and Chloe’s (and also Rachel’s, to a lesser extent) fears about her best friend. For me this is the best written issue of Life is Strange comic book yet. This is what the whole story of the comic book should have been about in the first place. Also, while I am not a fan of Rachel Amber, she reacts in a good way here, telling Chloe that Max needs her. We all know that Chloe often has a problem with acting when something bad happens to the person she cares about, she sometimes needs a little encouragement to do the right thing, and Rachel provided such an encouragement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime Max made a decision. She started packing to try to get away from Chloe, probably to somehow return to the previous timeline if possible. She stated herself, contemplating things as she packed her bag:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Chloe, I don’t know why I was pulled here. Like I have a right to walk into your life here and make it harder? That’s everything I don’t want to do. There has to be a reason. That boy. I hate lying to you, but how do I even begin to share the truth without breaking what you have here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This scene was so evocative, so emotional. Max’s doubts and fears, her pain, pain she carried over through all the timelines, slowly accumulating it, to the point when it just became too much. It was difficult to read. It hurt. But it was well-written, in the true spirit of Life is Strange. When we strip away all additional plot, secondary characters, locations, etc., Life is Strange was always about Max and Chloe. And in this issue, at last, we can explore implications of Max’s decision and what it meant to her, to change her timeline, to leave that Chloe behind, in Arcadia Bay, and come here, to this Chloe and Rachel. We can see that Max still love Chloe, love &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; Chloes in all the timelines, and even despite the fact she hurts so much, she does not want to interfere with Chloe’s happiness. She is willing to, once more,  make a sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-max-cries-broken.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-max-cries-broken&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This issue of Life is Strange comic book allowed us to see how much Max has sacrificed for Chloe, to give her happiness she deserved&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max didn’t have a chance to finish her packing before Chloe came to her room, to talk about recent events and to tell Max she was worried about her. Of course she momentarily discovered Max’s intentions to runaway (even though the brunette assured her she was only packing „symbolically”). She assured Max that she was not alone and that she could talk to Chloe about what bothers her. She pleaded to Max to let Chloe help her. But Max turned to her with eyes full of tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I-I really don’t think you can, Chloe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This singe sentence broke my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chloe talked to Max about how she was angry when William died, how she had serious issues with Joyce and barely spoke to her for almost a year. She achieved a small success, making Max promise to not leave without letting her know first. Although this was a small victory, it was something of a tremendous importance. In Dust we saw that Chloe had finally come to terms with losing Joyce in the storm, she grew up as a person, become more mature. And this new Chloe, although her life was not marked by the tragedy of losing &lt;strong&gt;both&lt;/strong&gt; parents, she was still more mature, more familiar with grief and anger and with ways of dealing with them. This showed great development of her character and was another thing that I appreciated in this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the last part, completely unexpected, was the discovery of Chloe’s patron, who ordered the sculpture she made (called &lt;em&gt;the Storm&lt;/em&gt;, by the way). It was… Tammi from the High Seas. Wowser. I did not expect that! The whole band arrived to L.A. to give a few concerts, it turns out that Tammi is a cousin of Paul, owner of the coffee shop Max cooperates with. Of course the band didn’t know Max (they never met in this timeline) but it leads to an interesting question: is their meeting a pure coincidence or there are other powers at play here? The first thing that comes to my mind is the mysterious guy in black, especially because he was right out of the coffee shop, starting a conversation with Max when she had to get some fresh air after the initial shock of meeting High Seas in this timeline. It looks like he has some big reveal to make, but it’s a mystery so far.  I guess we will find out in the two last issues of Dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t been a fan of Life is Strange comic book so far, due to many issues I mentioned in my previous articles. But being completely honest with you, this was the first part of the comic book that I genuinely enjoyed. The part of the story presented in issue #6 was well-written, consistent and had this distinctive Life is Strange vibe that was missing from previous issues. I love the fact it explored the dynamics between Max and Chloe instead of focusing on Chloe and Rachel. I also really appreciate that it gave us an insight into Max’s thoughts and the burden she’s been carrying with her for the last two years. I have no idea how the story will develop in the seventh issue, but this was a very good issue that I can recommend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yay&quot;&gt;Yay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the issue focuses on Max and her feelings&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dynamics between Max and Chloe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chloe being supportive for Max&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chloe’s workshop (and the sculpture)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High Seas are back! (^.^)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nay&quot;&gt;Nay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;possible importance of the sad guy for the story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we still know virtually nothing about the sad guy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;repetitive scenes with the sad guy disappearing or running from shops&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;typo in the text (not the first one…)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Max may never find the right timeline for her&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overall-summary-in-three-words&quot;&gt;Overall summary in three words&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;promising, poignant, introspective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="comicbooks" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="chloeprice" /><category term="rachelamber" /><category term="arcadiabay" /><category term="series" /><category term="review" /><category term="recap" /><category term="liscomicbook" /><summary type="html">The new arc of Life is Strange comic book shows Max’s life after she had left her original timeline and looked for the one in which she could give Chloe happiness she deserved. It’s been two years since Max made her choice but she still struggles to accept it. Did she choose right?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life is Strange comic book vol. 5 (Waves #1)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-5/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is Strange comic book vol. 5 (Waves #1)" /><published>2019-06-01T18:50:10+02:00</published><updated>2019-06-01T18:50:10+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-5/">&lt;p&gt;Today I read the fifth issue of Life is Strange comic book, the one opening a new story arc that is supposed to build on the foundations of Dust. Here you’ll find my thoughts on the new issue and its storyline.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you probably know by now, originally Life is Strange comic book was intended to be a finished 4-issue story. Due to its popularity and huge demand publisher decided to turn it into an ongoing series with multiple story arcs. First four issues concluded the Dust story arc and the current one, issue number 5, begins a new one, mysteriously called Waves. Is it a subtle hint that we should expect another natural disaster like Arcadia Bay’s tornado, or maybe it refers to the tides of time interfering with Max’s fate? I don’t know yet, but for sure the new name is intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you forgot what happened in previous issues you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://leziak.com/tags/liscomicbook/&quot;&gt;read my articles about them&lt;/a&gt;. Just a quick reminder: Max we knew from the comic book has left the main timeline and chose another reality, the one in which Chloe and Rachel were together in LA, to live in. There was a subtle hint (later &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Emmavieceli/status/1101032495708098560&quot;&gt;confirmed by the writer, Emma Vieceli&lt;/a&gt;) that another Max (the right one?) takes place of the previous Max in the timeline of the abandoned Chloe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know whether the first issue of Waves would continue the story of Max who travelled to another timeline to live with Chloe and Rachel or Max who replaced her in the main timeline of Dust and reunited with Chloe during the memorial ceremony in Arcadia Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First look at the issue #5 of Life is Strange comic book makes me wonder about the peculiar cover art. Max with blue skin and clothes (and pink hair) takes a photo using an instant camera while three butterflies (also blue) fly above her. In the picture there is a sign saying &lt;em&gt;Oregon thanks you. Come back soon&lt;/em&gt;. I must admit that I kind of like the new appearance of Max here (especially her pink hair looks cool), it reminds me of some sort of an underwater scenery (maybe that’s the reference to the title of this story arc?). Next we have a two-page recap of the events depicted in &lt;a href=&quot;https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-4/&quot;&gt;the final issue of Dust&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-cover-5.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-5&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The new cover stands out from the previous ones, clearly indicating the beginning of a new story arc&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First scenes of the new story arc are much more peaceful and relaxing than the ones from Dust. In Dust we saw Max being alone amid a swarm of butterflies, with her nose bleeding and Chloe nowhere to be seen. Waves introduces us to vibrant and colourful atmosphere of Santa Monica where we follow Max working on her laptop in a coffee shop ran by her friend/customer Paul. It bears an important implication: apparently Waves continues the story of Max who moved from the original timeline to the one with Chloe and Rachel living together. Which means we don’t get to see (yet or at all) what happened to Chloe that was left behind in Arcadia Bay nor we can witness her reunion with another Max that entered that timeline. It also means that Chloe presented in Waves is a different Chloe from the one we had seen in previous issues. It makes me a bit sad, because I really liked that Chloe and I appreciated the way in which she grew as a person, dealing with the loss of her mother, her home, her town. I hoped that we would get to see how she deals with seeing a new Max, how both of them attend the ceremony of unveiling the memorial, meet with the High Seas, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the new timeline, two years after her final travel through the Transect, Max still works as a photographer, which is an uplifting thing. I’m happy to see that what she had suffered from the hands of Jefferson did not ruin photography for her and she can still find joy in working with the camera. She talked about taking some photos for the coffee shop owner, Paul, to show the interior of his shop on the website. There were only two of them, Max and Paul, inside, not counting a young boy wearing a long black coat, with a clear sign of distress on his face. It looked like Max was the only one who saw him. Even Chloe, who went into the shop few minutes later, completely ignored the boy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the conversation taking place between the girls I learned that Max lives with Chloe and Rachel. Chloe works in an auto repair shop and Rachel is going to auditions, probably wanting to become an actress. On one hand it’s sweet that Chloe and Rachel took Max under their roof (when Dust finished I had no idea how close Max would become with the girls, considering the fact Chloe hadn’t seen her for years). On the other hand it’s… awkward. I mean, Rachel and Chloe are a thing in this reality, so as much as Chloe is happy to have Max back in her life, I can’t shake the impression that living with your former ex best friend and her girlfriend is the very definition of thirdwheeling. Wouldn’t Max prefer to give Chloe and Rachel some space? Wouldn’t that be hurtful for her to see the display of affection of one girl for the other? I know that she chose this reality specifically to give Chloe a chance to decide what she wants. However, if two years later Chloe is still with Rachel I think it’s pretty clear what she wants (at least in this timeline) so Max shouldn’t really tag along with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I definitely enjoyed Max’s new attire. She abandoned dorky T-shirts and grey hoodie for a more vibrant clothes. I like her dream-catcher necklace and I absolutely adore the butterfly tattoo on her wrist. Speaking of changes, I also appreciated Chloe’s  necklace in this timeline, a single nut. I like to thing she took this nut from her old pickup that she had found in American Rust, so a part of Arcadia Bay is still with her all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-max-chloe-coffee-shop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-max-chloe-coffee-shop&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;It’s good to see some peaceful, adorable moments, without nosebleeds, flickering timelines and tornadoes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next couple of scenes take place in the apartment where the three girls live. There’s a lot of affection between Chloe and Rachel, with Max standing nearby. It’s… awkward. Weird. It doesn’t seem like it bothers Max but it does bother me. I feel like Max shouldn’t be there, it’s like she’s interrupting something. For me, as a Pricefielder, these scenes were painful to see. I know that Chloe is happy with Rachel and now she also has her best friend at hand, but I still firmly believe that the comic book should not be headed that way. It was supposed to continue the story of Life is Strange and Life is Strange was about &lt;em&gt;Max and Chloe&lt;/em&gt;. I know it’s not feasible economically but there should be two separate editions of the comic book. One with a storyline describing Pricefield after Life is Strange and one showing Amberprice after Before the Storm. Trying to merge it into one happy Amberpricefield will not work for everyone. I will even risk and say it will not work for the vast majority of fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-chloe-rachel-max.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-chloe-rachel-max&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Thirdwheeling much, Max?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure Emma Vieceli was trying her best to come up with the story that would satisfy as many fans as possible or that would at least disappoint as few fans as possible. But taking the “safe” route with Max, Chloe and Rachel living happily together seems cheesy to me. And it is not a very probable outcome. There is one more thing. Rachel in the comic book is not Rachel we know from Before the Storm. She has different personality and character, she acts differently. Sure, there are six years between the events of Before the Storm and Life is Strange comic book, she could have changed during that time and most surely she did. But the comic book Rachel is to the in-game Rachel like the Nightmare Max to the regular Max.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max spends some time thinking about the evens of Dust and Chloe she left behind in Arcadia Bay. She misses that Chloe, she misses time when she knew her friends and they knew her. This part was done in a good way. I like the fact that Max actually contemplates things, tries to understand them and tries to understand herself. She ponders her decision to leave that Chloe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the transect I looked for the brightest light that would let me in… And it drew me here. And I’ve made the most of it ever since. I promise. It’s… a good life. But it’s not the life I made with you and I want to know you’re okay. I just… I wish there was a way to know. I can live with loneliness if I could just know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the thing that was my main problem with the ending of Dust. Max has sacrificed her happiness for her idea of Chloe’s happiness. She can’t be sure whether this Chloe in new timeline is actually happier that the Chloe left behind, she also doesn’t know whether Chloe left in Arcadia Bay is happier now with the new Max that took her place. &lt;strong&gt;It is quite possible that Max’s sacrifice actually didn’t improve anything.&lt;/strong&gt; That it was meaningless, unnecessary. Additionally, by introducing multiple realities, multiple Maxes that are on par with each other, Emma diminished the importance of both player choices at the end of Life is Strange as well as Max’s choices throughout the entire comic book (including choices we are yet to see). It doesn’t really matter what Max does, who Chloe chooses, etc., as these are neither the only nor the most important Max and Chloe. We could have an intriguing, compelling storyline with a satisfying ending, just to discover in the first issue of the next story arc that it was all meaningless, as there is a new set of Max and Chloe ready to take over. That’s what bothers me a lot with how the comic book handled the story and player’s final choice in Life is Strange. It shows that, on the contrary to the game, choices don’t matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event of the first issue of Waves was Chloe learning that Rachel is going to leave California for six months, to work with a theatre performing Shakespeare’s plays on the entire East Coast, from New York to Florida. Both Max and Chloe were surprised but Chloe took it worse due to the fact that her girlfriend is going to be absent for such a long time. There was an argument between Chloe and Rachel but they made peace soon, leaving Max in another awkward situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-max-sad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-max-sad&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;It clearly shows this is not a place for Max. Maybe the decision she made in the transect was wrong?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Max was wandering on the beach, thinking about the choice she made, she saw that sad boy from the coffee shop again and their eyes met for a second. Moment later he was gone. Max was afraid it could have been another flicker, but the last panel of the issue shows the boy hiding around the corner, a thin line of blood pouring from his nose. That was surprising as hell. Does it mean he has powers like Max used to? Why people weren’t able to see him but Max did? There are many questions and no answers, and knowing the pace of the Dust story arc, we won’t get any until the final issue of Waves is here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was… not what I expected from the new story arc. I hoped to see Chloe reuniting with Max in Arcadia Bay, instead I got the same Max with a new Chloe and Rachel. Seeing how Max doesn’t quite fit between Chloe and Rachel made this whole issue feel awkward and uncomfortable, and a bit painful to be honest. While I don’t like where the story is going, I do appreciate awesome art and beautiful vivid colours of this issue. Considering aesthetics and the art Life is Strange comic book is really good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yay&quot;&gt;Yay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;peaceful scenes in Santa Monica&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Max’s butterfly tattoo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paul and Perry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;references to Dust (déjà vu in the coffee shop, High Seas’ song)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;vivid colours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nay&quot;&gt;Nay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the sad guy in black&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the apparent importance of that guy to the Waves story&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fact he might have some powers like Max&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rachel is nothing like the actual Rachel from Before the Storm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Max thirdwheeling Amberprice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overall-summary-in-three-words&quot;&gt;Overall summary in three words&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;awkward, inconstant, colourful&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="comicbooks" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="chloeprice" /><category term="rachelamber" /><category term="arcadiabay" /><category term="series" /><category term="review" /><category term="recap" /><category term="liscomicbook" /><summary type="html">Today I read the fifth issue of Life is Strange comic book, the one opening a new story arc that is supposed to build on the foundations of Dust. Here you’ll find my thoughts on the new issue and its storyline.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Raven’s Path (a teaser chapter)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/ravens-path-teaser/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Raven’s Path (a teaser chapter)" /><published>2019-04-29T20:15:44+02:00</published><updated>2019-04-29T20:15:44+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/ravens-path-teaser</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/ravens-path-teaser/">&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;foreword&quot;&gt;Foreword&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear friend,&lt;br /&gt;
you are about to read a small piece of the Raven’s Path. It is a Life is Strange story, taking place a few days after the events depicted in the game. The following teaser chapter has been taken out from the middle of the story, to show you what you can expect. &lt;strong&gt;It is spoiler-free, which means you can safely read it without the risk of discovering too many important details.&lt;/strong&gt; I hope you will enjoy it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you finish, please consider leaving feedback on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KamilLeziak&quot;&gt;my Twitter profile&lt;/a&gt;. I would love to hear your opinion on the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Raven’s Path premieres on 1st May 2019 on &lt;a href=&quot;https://archiveofourown.org/users/Vertiser/works&quot;&gt;Archive of Our Own&lt;/a&gt;. You can already &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vVMnXD5i9Xs&quot;&gt;watch its trailer on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would not be able to share this chapter with you without the help of my awesome friend, &lt;strong&gt;Epic Glitter&lt;/strong&gt;. They made a tremendous effort of proofreading this part of the story and pointing out the ways in which it could be improved. They offered me a thoughtful feedback, teaching me about traps and nuances of English grammar. Their constant support motivated me to keep writing, to push myself even further, to learn new ways of pouring my thoughts on paper. Thank you for everything, my friend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that Epic Glitter write their own Life is Strange fanfics? They are absolutely amazing! I wholeheartedly encourage you to check &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archiveofourown.org/users/Epic_Glitter&quot;&gt;Epic Glitter’s profile on Archive of Our Own&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, where you can find a lot of beautiful, immersing, captivating stories from Arcadia Bay and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dedication&quot;&gt;Dedication&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I dedicate this chapter to my #WeAreLiS family.&lt;br /&gt;
You are my angels.&lt;br /&gt;
I love you.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/raven_break_small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do not stand at my grave and weep&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I am not there; I do not sleep.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I am a thousand winds that blow,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I am the diamond glints on snow,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I am the sun on ripened grain,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I am the gentle autumn rain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;When you awaken in the morning’s hush&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I am the swift uplifting rush&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Of quiet birds in circled flight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I am the soft stars that shine at night.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Do not stand at my grave and cry,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I am not there; I did not die.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary Elizabeth Frye&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/raven_break_small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-lighthouse&quot;&gt;The Lighthouse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Max reached the bus stop after last period, Kate had already been waiting for her. She noticed Max approaching and waved her over with a smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Oh, I’m so happy you made it, Max!” She said, hugging Max warmly. “You’ll see, you’ll definitely feel better changing your surroundings a little.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope so, Kate.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Where do you want to go?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max shrugged. “I don’t really mind any place. We can go wherever.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Are you sure?” Kate inquired and Max nodded in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Okay, so…” Kate said with voice full of excitement “let’s see the lighthouse! I’ve been wanting to go there ever since I came to Arcadia Bay, but I had no one to go with at first and then, after the Vortex Club party…” an ephemeral trace of sadness appeared in her voice. “I didn’t feel like hiking. But now I’m with you and I would absolutely love to see Arcadia Bay from the cliff! I’ve heard it’s a picturesque view.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max hesitated. She didn’t really want to go to the lighthouse, that place was full of sad memories, plus the nightmare she had last night… But she saw the hopeful look on Kate’s face and she realized she couldn’t think only about herself. After all, it was Kate who wanted to help her and offered her a friendly talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Sure, we can go see the lighthouse” Max agreed, to Kate’s delight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Great!” Kate exclaimed as the yellow school bus with &lt;em&gt;Blackwell Academy Transportation&lt;/em&gt; written on the side pulled to a stop in front of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bus quickly filled with students. Despite the fact that some of the students were eligible for place in the dormitories, the majority of the school population lived in the town itself and now, once classes were over, they were coming home from campus. After half of an hour the bus finally arrived at the stop on the north side of Arcadia Bay. It was the closest place to the lighthouse they could reach with a school bus. Three other students from Blackwell got off at this stop. Max briefly recognized them as being from the younger class. They headed towards the path leading to the beach, while Max and Kate took a gravel road leading uphill, to the cliff and the lighthouse overlooking the bay. Max looked up and noticed that the upper story of the lighthouse was bathed in sunlight, a snow-white obelisk towering above a dark-green forest. It had a captivating aura to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They followed the uphill road for a few minutes. When they reached a parking lot near the trail leading to the lighthouse itself, Max spotted a blue jay that perched on a boulder, looking at her curiously. Max instinctively grabbed her messenger bag to take out the camera, only to remember that, since Chloe’s death, she was no longer carrying her Polaroid with her. &lt;em&gt;Maybe that’s okay, after all. I lost my passion for photography anyway.&lt;/em&gt; She observed the bird proudly ruffling up its feathers for a moment, and then moved on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the girls emerged from the forest into an open space at the top of the cliff, Kate let out a cry of astonishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wow… Max, it’s so beautiful up here!” she exclaimed, absorbing the view in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although in the morning the weather was somewhat capricious, now the sun was shining bright and strong, bathing the entire town of Arcadia Bay in golden light. Throughout the town, as well as the rest of Oregon, trees had already started to lose their green coating and forests were speckled with shades of yellow, brown and red. In the bay, several fishing boats had ended their daily routine, slowly returning to the port to sell their afternoon catch. For someone like Kate, who had been here for the first time, the vista must have been truly stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Gosh, this sight is incredible” Kate’s voice was full of admiration. “Is it always so wonderful?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If the sun is shining and the weather’s okay, then… yeah.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Ah, what a pity you don’t have your camera on you! I bet you’d have taken gorgeous photos!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max nodded slightly, pretending to agree. It was good to see Kate happy, and with every passing minute, she reminded Max more and more of the old, carefree Kate from the time before Victoria’s video came to light. Max, however, could not share her happiness. Looking around, she couldn’t get rid of an unnerving feeling of déjà vu, as if she was reliving her all-too-recent nightmare. Although it was a sunny afternoon, in her mind, Max could still see the terrifying storm. She remembered the huge tornado that once raged above the ocean, blinking as the present-day crests of gentle waves calmly lapped against the undisturbed shoreline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max looked in the direction of the higher part of the clifftop, close to the lighthouse. That was the place where she met Chloe in her dream. Max walked there slowly, stopping near the cliff’s edge, near the spot where she watched Arcadia Bay reduced to dust. She gave the town a long look. Four thousand six hundred and twenty-five people. That’s how many residents of Arcadia Bay owe their lives to Chloe, though they didn’t even know about it, nor would they ever. Did Max act properly? Did she have a right to trade one life for four thousand others? Was that really what Chloe wanted? In her last moment, knowing that she would soon cease to exists and that her timeline would soon be irrevocably terminated, did she regret her decision? As her best friend stared at the photo, did Chloe want to tell her to stop?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No,&lt;/em&gt; Max thought with intensity, &lt;em&gt;maybe Chloe was not perfect, but she was not a coward. Never.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chloe might not have been a coward,&lt;/em&gt; said a voice in her head that belonged to herself, &lt;em&gt;but you are! You were afraid to make the decision yourself, you convinced yourself that Chloe knew better, that she had a right to make such a dire choice. You did nothing to save her. You did not oppose her. You just wrote her off.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No!” Max cried out loud, trying to drown out the thoughts that tormented her. She took a step forward, standing almost on the very edge of a cliff. She looked at Arcadia Bay. It felt like when she blinked, under her half-closed eyelids she could see the contours of a tornado making its way toward the town. When she closed her eyes and concentrated, she felt that she could hear the deafening roar of wind and the sound of rain, overpowered by the peals of a thunder every couple of seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You shouldn’t stand so close to the edge.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max opened her eyes but did not look back. She glanced down and saw the shadow of Kate, who was standing two steps behind her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What do you mean ”why?“” Kate sounded surprised. “You can fall, Max!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It doesn’t matter” Max replied in a flat voice, staring blankly at the horizon. “She’s gone…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Max…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terrified, Kate watched Max standing motionless on the edge of a cliff. After a moment that seemed like eternity, Max took a deep breath and slowly, unhurriedly, turned back. She saw Kate’s concerned face and noticed her watery eyes. Max passed her without a word, going to the lower part of the cliff and sitting down on the lone wooden bench.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All is lost, Kate.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max herself was surprised by the lack of sadness or despair in her voice. It was completely emotionless, hollow, tired. Max didn’t wallow in self-pity, she was merely stating a fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate’s look was still full of worries. She went to Max and sat down beside her, hands clasped together on her knees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“All is not lost, Max” she assured, trying to sound confident, but her worried tone was not very convincing. “You are not alone. There are people who care about you.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Like who?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Like me” Kate stated, her voice gaining some confidence. “I’m tremendously sorry for your friend, but you don’t have to fight this pain alone. I know perfectly well how terrible it is, when your world collapses and you can’t get any help. But you’ve helped me! Please, let me help you now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max looked up and and turned her head, staring at Kate. She looked at Max intently and her gaze was… kind. Full of compassion and… understanding. Ever since Max lost Chloe, she hadn’t seen understanding in anyone’s look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know how you can help me” Max said honestly. “I don’t know how to help &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt;!”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate took Max’s hand in her own. Their eyes met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Maybe we can start by just talking?” she suggested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know where to begin.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Begin at any point, I’ll put everything together” Kate assured her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max looked at the sky above the cliff, where seagulls were soaring calmly, their screams reaching the lighthouse with the wind. She wanted, really wanted to tell Kate everything, but she knew it was impossible. What would she say? &lt;em&gt;I saw my best friend being shot to death by Nathan Prescott, then I discovered I could rewind time. I saved her, spent a week with her, I’ve fallen in love with her, I solved the mystery behind Rachel Amber’s disappearance, only to ultimately find out that my powers had caused a huge tornado that would have killed everyone in Arcadia Bay. So I came back to the very beginning and I let my beloved die on a dirty bathroom floor, lonely and scared. I let her bleed out, convinced, in the last moments of her life, that the last words she’d ever hear,&lt;/em&gt; ‘Nobody would ever miss your punk ass, would they?’ &lt;em&gt;were true. Because of me, she left this world believing that everyone who has ever loved her, abandoned her in the end!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Take your time” Kate said calmly, “we have an entire afternoon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It won’t work” Max sighed, shaking her head. “I really want to tell you everything, but I can’t.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate’s face darkened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why?” she asked, disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Because” Max replied with a resigned voice, “not everything can be described with words. Because sometimes words are hollow, dead, they lack the emotion that drives them. Because you cannot turn back time that has already been rewound. Because regardless of how much we would struggle to change the past, our fate will always reach us in the end. Because memories are always real, even if the events themselves have turned into nothingness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s… really deep” said surprised Kate after a moment of silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max laughed grimly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Trust me, Kate, deep things, repeated time and again, quickly become clichés.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“If you say so.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate evidently wanted to avoid confrontation. For a moment, both girls remained silent. Kate stared at her knees, her right hand holding the little cross hanging from her neck. Max was looking straight into the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You know, Max…” Kate began after a moment, whispering, as if embarrassed by what she wanted to say. “I have to tell you something.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max glanced at Kate. She was looking down, at her shoes, avoiding Max’s eyes and unknowingly turning the golden cross in her hand. She looked like she was gathering her courage to tell Max something important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m listening to you, Kate.” Max encouraged her, trying to make her voice sound a little softer after her recent tirade. Max knew she could not solve her own problems, but she would never allow anything to torment her friend’s caring, gentle soul. After taking a few deep breaths, Kate began:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“After the Vortex Club party, when… when that video showed up on the internet” Kate winced, as the corners of her mouth dropped in a sad grimace. Although Max helped her last week, it was clear that the wound was still fresh. “I felt so… lonely. Abandoned by the others. When I tried to explain what happened to me, and ask for help, nobody believed me. No one wanted to listen… I was alone, that is, before you helped me” she added quickly, glancing at Max apologetically. “I had the feeling that I was trapped in a nightmare, a nightmare I could not wake up from…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max shuddered. Obviously Kate couldn’t know that, but she repeated almost exactly the same words she had uttered in another reality, standing on the rooftop, moments before she jumped into the void.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was a terrible feeling” Kate continued, closing her eyes as if to recall some mental image. “Sleep did not bring me relief, only nightmares. Even after waking up everyone was laughing at me and scorning me. I couldn’t get help from anyone, I felt that… I could not take it anymore. I just wanted to… stop suffering. Rest.” She opened her eyes and looked at Max, her expression filled with a mix of pain and compassion. “I was considering, very seriously…” she paused, searching for the right words. “I-I wanted to end it all. You know what I mean?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max nodded in silence. Of course she knew. She did not admit to Kate that she knew even more than Kate had told her. She had no idea if Kate was going to jump from the dormitory roof in this reality or chose another way to depart this life, but Max was painfully aware that if she hadn’t had a serious conversation with Victoria in Jefferson’s classroom, it might have ended with another tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Max, I’m telling you all of this because… I saw your drawings today, in Esperto’s class” Kate hesitated, the lingering embarrassment in her voice mixed with concern. “I was… I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; worried about you” she corrected herself. “I don’t want you to make my mistake. I don’t want you to… do something terrible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max looked at Kate, her throat tight with a mix of emotions. Poor Kate, poor shy Kate, how much effort and determination it must have cost her, to admit to Max she’d struggled with such desperate intentions and suspected Max may have done the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Please” Kate added after a moment, “don’t tell anyone about what I told you, okay? I don’t want them to bully me again.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Of course, Kate” Max quickly assured her, “you have my word.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tears appeared in Kate’s eyes and began to drop on her cheeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Can you… can you also promise me that… that you will not do anything stupid? Please, Max…” she started to break down, tears staining her white shirt. “I would never forgive myself if you… if you…” she broke off, sobbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max hugged her, letting her rest her head on Max’s shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I will remember your words, Kate, I promise. Thank you for being here for me… You are the only one…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few minutes passed as they held their embrace. The warm afternoon sun lit their faces, both bearing traces of tears, although neither of them were crying anymore. Max stared at Arcadia Bay below. The idyllic atmosphere was suddenly interrupted by a black raven who swooped down, sitting on a board bearing an Arcadia Bay map. Years ago, Chloe had scrawled a red pirate skull to mark the location of their tree fort. He cried loudly, making Kate look up. The raven turned his head a bit, and one of his eyes fixed on the girls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He looks like he’s watching us” Kate noticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No, he looks like he’s watching me&lt;/em&gt; Max thought, feeling a strange unease. She tried to convince herself it was nothing more than a mere coincidence. It was quite possible that some stray raven just flew over to them, hoping to get some corn… No, Max didn’t believe herself at all. This raven looked identical to the one sitting on Chloe’s shoulder in Max’s most recent nightmare. Such happenstance could occur anywhere, but not in Arcadia Bay. There were no coincidences in Arcadia Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Maybe we should feed him?” Kate suggested timidly. “He might be hungry.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think he came here for food, he’s just being curious, that’s all” Max said, feigning confidence in her voice. She did not want to scare Kate, telling her that mysterious animal from her dream has just materialized in bodily form ten feet away. “Besides, I don’t have anything to eat that I could give him. What about you?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate looked inside her bag, rummaging. In the meantime Max kept her eyes fixed on the raven. And the raven was looking at her. &lt;em&gt;Did he just wink at me?&lt;/em&gt; she thought, surprised. &lt;em&gt;No, that’s not possible. I think I’m really starting to lose my mind…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t have any food either” Kate answered after a moment, closing her bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“That’s okay, he will fly away soon enough.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The raven seemed to understand what Max had just said. He squawked and flew to the other side of the map, where he began fiercely tapping his beak against it, as if trying to split a walnut. Surprised, Kate gave out an involuntary cry, but it did not seem to scare the raven away. He paused for a moment, looked at the girls, and resumed pecking the map shortly after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Shoo!” Max shouted, jumping from her seat and flailing her arms. The raven took off, circled above them and perched on a high branch of a nearby pine. Max’s angry stare followed him. “Damn bird.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He was a bit strange” Kate said cautiously. Max always wondered how Kate could keep her distance and watch her words in different situations. “It looked like he wanted to peck a hole in the map.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hmm…” A sudden thought came to Max. She turned away from the raven sitting above her and walked to the stand displaying a map of Arcadia Bay. The map was made of thick laminated paper, resistant to water and sunlight, so it wasn’t weathered much, despite its age. The lighthouse and the water tower marked opposite ends of the town, with Blackwell Academy, the town hall, and other important sites throughout the rest of Arcadia Bay were also visible. Max’s look, however, turned to a red, crooked pirate drawing, made with a permanent marker by eight-year-old Chloe Price. The symbol faded slightly in the sun, but it was not what drew Max’s attention. There were fresh scratches in the laminate, precisely in the spot where Chloe’s pirate symbol was located. Scratches made with a bird’s beak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No fucking way…&lt;/em&gt; Max turned back to the forest and looked at the branch where the raven sat a moment ago, but the branch was empty. The bird was nowhere to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Did he destroy the map?” Kate asked worriedly, but Max shook her head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No, he only scratched it slightly, never mind.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were the scratches actually made by the raven few moments ago? What if Max was hallucinating, or starting to see a mystery in things that did not matter? Regardless, Max realized one thing: since returning from Seattle, she’d avoided visiting the tree fort Chloe and her had built together. She didn’t visit it in &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of the timelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Kate, would you like to go somewhere else with me?” Max asked suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate blinked, surprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What do you mean?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There is this one place I haven’t visited since the childhood. I’m curious if it’s still standing” Max answered, making sure she didn’t involuntary look at the pirate symbol on a map. She didn’t want Kate to get the impression that Max was doing something because of the bizarre story with the raven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know” Kate hesitated, glancing at the sun as it slowly dipped towards the horizon. “Maybe we should come back? We’ve been here for some time already, and I would not like to stay in the woods after dark.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Come on, we’ll get there in half of an hour! The sun won’t set for another two. Besides, we’ll get closer to the town.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Fine” Kate sighed, rolling her eyes. “But if I break my leg in the woods in the dark, you’ll have to carry me to Arcadia Bay yourself!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You have my word” Max said, grinning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“So where are we going?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“South” she replied, pointing the direction with her hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/raven_break_small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first it was a bit difficult. Max got lost twice, looking for a path that used to trace the edge of the woods, and was now completely overgrown with dense bushes. But when she reached the crossroads with a huge, graffiti-covered boulder, she knew they were on the right track. She remembered how Chloe had once scared her when they were children, jumping out from behind this boulder and screaming maniacally.  Chloe’s face was smeared with mud and she had small branches and leaves attached to her clothes. Max screamed at the top of her lungs, thinking that some monster wanted to eat her, until she realized that the monster was laughing in the same way her best friend did. Max smiled at the memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are getting closer” she assured Kate who bravely kept the pace. “Just ten more minutes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Okay.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took them fifteen minutes to reach the tree fort. When Max saw the strange structure suspended in the fork of a huge oak, she felt a twinge of sadness. The fort looked smaller than she remembered from her childhood, and it was in much worse condition than she expected. One wall was missing and the roof seemed to be very skewed. Some boards were rotten and covered with lichen, although here and there Max noticed the whiteness of new wood, a certain sign that someone was attempting makeshift repairs. A rope hung from an anchor in the fort, its neat knots lying against the trunk of the old oak in neat intervals. Its threads were stainless and unfrayed, making the rope ladder look quite new. Max guessed it was supposed to make climbing up to the hideout a bit easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Amazing!” Kate praised, standing next to Max and eyeing the fort. “It looks like a real paradise for children!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was a paradise for me as a child,” Max admitted in a nostalgic voice. “For me and Chloe. We dressed in pirate clothes, put on captain hats and eye patches, and pretended that we wanted to conquer all of Arcadia Bay.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Did you make it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I don’t know” Max shrugged. “For some time it seemed that everything was possible. That we would always be together, two pirates from Arcadia. But then the world caught up with us. Chloe’s dad died in a car accident, I left for Seattle with my parents. Our childhood dreams remained just that. Childhood dreams.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate walked to Max and stood beside her, looking at the tree fort. She gently placed her hand on Max’s shoulder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You came back here” she said. “You came back for yourself and for her. Pirate ships always return to their home port, don’t they?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max didn’t answer, lost in her thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate took her bag off her shoulder and began to rummage in it. After a moment she took out a hard cover notebook and a few colored pencils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I would like to draw your fort” she said to Max, opening her notebook on a blank page. “Every child dreams of such a fort, and if one day… if one day my dream comes true and I’ll become an illustrator, this drawing might be an inspiration for children in the future. Then… then your dream will come true in some way, you will conquer the world with Chloe…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max felt tears gathering in her eyes, not for the first time today. This time, however, they were tears of gratitude. She remembered how, as children she and Chloe claimed this forest their own. They called it their kingdom, a free state and sanctuary for all kind of pirates. She remembered how the other Chloe, with beautiful strawberry blond hair and soft, mellow voice, that lacked the usual anger and rejection, said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Being with you again has been so special. I just wanted to feel like when we were kids running around Arcadia Bay…. and everything was possible. And you made me feel that way today.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max only said “thank you,” trying to hold back her tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, Kate smiled and sat down on the grass, crossing her legs. She looked observantly at the fort and began drawing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max approached the oak and looked at the rope. When she and Chloe were children, the small wooden ladder that William had built was placed by the trunk. Now, however, there was no trace of it. Whoever was still using the tree fort probably didn’t want others to access it too easily. The floor was situated not lower than thirty feet, and small bulges on a trunk told Max that all the branches below the floor must have been cut off quite a long time ago. Therefore, climbing up the knotted rope was the only option available for someone who wanted to get inside. When Max grabbed the rope and pulled hard to test it, it held up. Apparently, whoever placed the rope here had been meticulous about it.Max made sure her messenger bag was safely slung over her shoulder. Then, she gripped the rope with both hands and, using knots on the rope and bulges on a trunk as support for her feet, slowly started climbing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She thought it would be easier than it actually was, though the difficulty laid mostly in the fact that Max felt quite weak. Walking all the way from the bus stop, to the lighthouse, and from the lighthouse to the pirate fort, had exhausted her more than she anticipated. When she finally reached the fort, she laid on the floor, breathing heavily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Wowser, that was hard” she muttered to herself, catching her breath. Fortunately, she started feeling better after a while, so she sat up and looked around the interior of the wooden structure. From the inside, it was also clear that the fort had seen better days. The roof apparently leaked in a few places, resulting in development of some green algae on the floor. On the edges of the missing wall, Max noticed the remnants of rotten boards, which meant that the wall most likely fell down when the rest of the structure was unable to support the damaged part. On the other hand, due to the whole wall missing, much more light reached the inside of the fort than used to through the lonely small window in the neighboring wall. Max could see the interior better, lit by the golden rays of the sun which was slowly approaching the horizon in the west.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was disappointed to see that drawings she and Chloe made with colored chalk as children did not survive. The largest of them all, depicting two girls in superhero costumes, along with Captain Bongo, was just on the missing wall. This didn’t mean, however, that the three standing walls were completely devoid of decorations. On the contrary, almost every free surface was covered with drawings or inscriptions made with some black marker. &lt;em&gt;Five years is enough time to change Chloe, but also to change our fort&lt;/em&gt; Max thought, getting up and looking at each wall while admiring the creative work of… Chloe, probably. Who else would write, with capital letters, &lt;strong&gt;BLACKHELL SUCKS!&lt;/strong&gt; across the entire wall?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of inscriptions Max could understand, like &lt;strong&gt;I CAN’T SLEEP ANYMORE&lt;/strong&gt;. She felt a twinge of sadness when she saw a small inscription written in tiny letters, &lt;em&gt;I’m always alone&lt;/em&gt;. This one wasn’t written in capital letters. It looked like done not in anger, but rather in sadness or resignation. For some reason that fact hurt Max more than the underlying sketch of her and Chloe in pirate costumes,  in which Max’s face has been scratched with a huge X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all inscriptions were understandable for Max. For example, she had absolutely no idea why at the bottom of one wall, just above the floor, Chloe wrote &lt;strong&gt;FUCK YOU ELIOT!&lt;/strong&gt; She also didn’t know what Chloe was talking about in a huge writing than ran around the only window in the fort and read: &lt;strong&gt;NO MORE TEMPEST! NEVER AGAIN!&lt;/strong&gt; To make things even stranger, there was a figure drawn at its end, that looked like a caricature of a person wearing a hat with a great beak, like toucan’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Is everything OK, Max?” Kate’s voice called to her from below. Max walked cautiously to the opening where the fourth wall was missing and saw Kate looking up, still keeping her notebook and pencil in hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes” she waved to Kate. “Do you want to come up? The view is pretty cool.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate shook her head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m not a good climber” she laughed. “With my luck I would break my leg &lt;em&gt;for real&lt;/em&gt; and you would have to carry me to Blackwell on your back. I prefer drawing from the ground level.” 
“If you change your mind just let me know!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Mhmm” agreed Kate, resuming drawing in her notebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max turned around, closely inspecting the equipment stashed in the treehouse. Only now did she realize that the floor was not as clean as it might have seemed. Practically in every corner of the fort there were empty beer bottles (in one corner they stood arranged in quite an impressive pyramid). Here and there there were also cigarette butts, thought most of them filled the red “OREGON” ashtray. The most distinctive piece of equipment, however, was a small, worn-out leather suitcase, lying on its side in the corner of the room. Max noticed that it was the only dry corner in the whole fort, the one where all rotten boards had been painstakingly replaced with the new ones and all holes in adjoining walls covered with plywood. Max came closer and looked warily at the suitcase. It had a lock, but apparently it was defunct, since the lid was kept closed by a piece of wire. Max bit her lower lip, hesitating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She didn’t want to brusquely go through private possessions that probably belonged to Chloe. It must have been something valuable to her, since she made efforts to keep this corner of the tree fort relatively dry and protected from the elements. On the other hand, Max was grimly aware that Chloe would never come back for these things. On top of that, if Max left these items in the fort, eventually either someone would steal them or they’d be destroyed by the elements. For a long time, Max stared indecisively at the suitcase. At last, she came up with an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/raven_break_small.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Can you finally tell me why you took this suitcase?” Kate asked for the third time as they were returning to Arcadia Bay. The sun was already low above the horizon and the girls cast huge shadows ahead of them. At this time of day the school bus had already ended its course and no regular lines were stopping at that bus stop, so after a short discussion, they decided to return to Blackwell on foot. It was less than two miles, except that walking on the pavement was much faster than hiking through the overgrown forest path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max let out a moan of resignation. Although Kate was shy and reluctant in everyday life, at times she could be a really irritable pain in the ass. Where did all this stubbornness come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I didn’t want the things inside to get destroyed. Besides, someone could steal them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You mean, someone other than you? Then why didn’t you just put those things in your bag? Why are you schlepping this old, broken suitcase all the way to Blackwell?” Kate asked in a matter-of-fact tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max looked at the suitcase in her hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I did not want to open it” she admitted after a while, passing the intersection and turning towards the road leading to the hill Blackwell Academy stood on. “These are Chloe’s things, they were probably important to her. I don’t want to… violate her privacy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I know what you mean” Kate nodded. “Wise decision.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“One of the very few, lately” Max muttered to herself, but Kate didn’t hear that. After a minute she asked Max another question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Maybe…” she began cautiously, “since these are Chloe’s things, we should give them back to her parents? I mean, to her mother.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max stopped for a moment, considering Kate’s suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“No” she responded finally, resuming her walk. “For some reason Chloe kept these things outside of her home. I don’t think she wants… she would have wanted” Max corrected herself, “to bring them back to the house she disliked so much since David moved in. It would not be right.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate did not reply to that, but Max could see in her look that something was still bothering her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Max…” she finally spoke in an unsteady voice, unable to hide her nervousness. “What if there is something illegal in there? I do not want you to get suspended or worse, expelled, because of this suitcase.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max kept to herself the fact that she had already almost been expelled due to David’s complaint, which was another reason why she was not going to set her foot on Cedar Avenue again. Kate would be even more worried, and Max didn’t want that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Whatever’s inside, nothing will happen until I open it” Max said rationally. “After all, it’s not a nuclear bomb or something…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carrying the suitcase, Max could feel that its contents were light, so it probably didn’t include a pistol with a supply of ammunition or a set of hand grenades. Although, knowing Chloe’s fondness for guns, Max briefly considered running the suitcase through a metal detector, just to be sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I hope you are right” Kate replied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the girls reached Blackwell Academy, the campus was already deserted. Max only saw a group of students leaving the drama group meeting, but she and Kate headed straight to the dormitory building, avoiding any questions. The corridor on their floor was also empty. Kate stopped in front of the doors leading to her room and reached into her bag for keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank you, Max, for going with me to the lighthouse. I’m glad we spent some time together.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Thank &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt;, Kate” Max answered, “for your good words and support. I needed that” she admitted honestly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Any time, Max! Good night!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Good night!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The girls hugged goodbye. Then, Kate disappeared into her room. Max opened the doors to her own. It was dark inside, but Max didn’t switch the lights on. She placed the suitcase on the floor under the mirror and lied back on her bed, not even bothering to change her clothes. She was tired. An afternoon full of adventures and the long walk took away all her strength. She only wanted to fall asleep without any dreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s good you finally came back.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The foreign voice made Max jump to her feet. She reached to turn on the chain of small hanging lamps, which softly illuminated the dozens of Polaroid photographs dotting her wall. She looked around her room in panic. In the dim light she saw a figure who was sitting calmly on the couch, giving Max a scrutinizing look.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Chloe.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="arcadiabay" /><category term="writing" /><category term="fanfiction" /><category term="lisstories" /><category term="ravenspath" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Max and Chloe (comic book style)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/max-chloe-comic-book-style/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Max and Chloe (comic book style)" /><published>2019-03-11T18:54:34+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-11T18:54:34+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/max-and-chloe-comic-book-style</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/max-chloe-comic-book-style/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/max-chloe-comic-book-style-740px.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;max-chloe-comic-book-style&quot; /&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“My powers might not last, Chloe.”&lt;br /&gt;
“That’s okay. We will. Forever.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My humble gift for Chloe’s birthday. Max &amp;amp; Chloe fanart in a comic book style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High-res version is available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deviantart.com/vertiser/art/Max-and-Chloe-Life-is-Strange-comic-book-style-789207238?ga_submit_new=10%3A1559414679&amp;amp;ga_type=edit&amp;amp;ga_changes=1&quot;&gt;deviantART&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the video clip showing speed drawing of this fanart &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCaf0VZDXJjqEhXSZ4yaByUg&quot;&gt;on my YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;740&quot; height=&quot;416&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/sumHuCx1HD0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="art" /><category term="drawing" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="chloeprice" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="arcadiabay" /><category term="digitalart" /><category term="procreate" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life is Strange comic book vol. 4 (Dust #4)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-4/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is Strange comic book vol. 4 (Dust #4)" /><published>2019-03-01T19:00:17+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-01T19:00:17+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-4/">&lt;p&gt;It is done. I’ve read the fourth and the final issue of Life is Strange comic book, the one concluding the Dust story arc. Did Max manage to solve the mystery of parallel realities? What happened to Chloe?&lt;!--more--&gt; This is the last review of the Dust story arc (you can read all of them &lt;a href=&quot;https://leziak.com/tags/liscomicbook/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Although we know already that the comic book will have its continuation with a new story arc, the plot of the future issues remains unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover of vol. 4 is straightforward dire. This time there are no subtleties. We can see Max crying, looking away; behind her Chloe stands turned back. There is a long fracture splitting the scene (and Max’s image) in two, on the right side a swarm of butterflies rises in some eerie blue glow. It looks like some source of light (probably the setting sun) illuminates sides of girls’ silhouettes. This time, in opposition to the cover of the first issue, Max is the one who has some ghostly quality to her. She looks like a reflection in a broken mirror, her left hand is semi-translucent and somehow, at least to me, she looks a bit less real than Chloe in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-cover-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This cover does not reveal subtle hints. It shows openly that the reader should be prepared for the worst&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recap pages provide some most needed context to the final part of Max’s and Chloe’s adventure. Especially the last sentence is very ominous:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Max feels like she’s becoming untethered in time and space, and whatever is happening to her is hurting more and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until this moment I thought Chloe was the one in danger. After all, most of Max’s visions were from the timeline in which Chloe died in the bathroom, so I expected Chloe’s death to be the main element differentiating the timelines. But in third issue I saw a reality in which Chloe was alive, there was no storm &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Rachel Amber was alive, which means it’s not all about Chloe, but rather about Max becoming unconstrained in time-space continuum (or whatever fancy term Warren would use).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blue butterflies. Again. This time they are filling the entire page, blocking the view of a strong white light behind them. And in the next frame… Max? With her eyes closed? Okay, I really, really don’t like where this is going… It turns out that Max managed to enter the space from which she can see various flickers, a pieces of different realities, of different timelines. She can see a reality in which she and Chloe are happy together… but there is another one where Chloe and Rachel are together, and that Chloe doesn’t look any bit sadder than the one with Max.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-max-eyes-butterflies.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;max-eyes-butterflies&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“Chloe… did I ever ask you… what you actually wanted?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max wakes up in the back of Chloe’s pickup. The girls have a long and meaningful conversation about parallel universes, different realities, each of them containing a unique version of Max and Chloe. But then Max drops a bomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Chloe… did you love Rachel? As more than a friend?”&lt;br /&gt;
“…where did that come from? How did–? I never said…”&lt;br /&gt;
“You didn’t have to.”&lt;br /&gt;
“But, Max, that doesn’t mean I don’t…”&lt;br /&gt;
“I know.”&lt;br /&gt;
“It’s just…”&lt;br /&gt;
“Not the same?”&lt;br /&gt;
“I don’t know. With everything… I’ve not even been able to think about…”&lt;br /&gt;
“I know. Me too. I want to, but…”&lt;br /&gt;
“Somewhere out there, our lives are normal and we’re not carrying a metric ton of baggage. If we were there, then…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sorry, but &lt;strong&gt;what the actual fuck?!&lt;/strong&gt; So now it looks like Chloe did love Rachel, but she can’t love Max the same? So we not only do not have Pricefield, but we have some weird &lt;em&gt;post-mortem&lt;/em&gt; Amberprice on the agenda? Okay, I know what you would say. Chloe loving Rachel doesn’t mean she doesn’t love Max, and they’ve been through so much it can be all confusing and they can’t work out their feelings just yet, etc. But it doesn’t change the fact that in my personal opinion there should be no place for Amberprice in this comic book. This is a continuation of Life is Strange, for heaven’s sake, not Before The Storm! Continuation of adventures of Max and Chloe. Max. and. Chloe. So Chloe has already forgotten how Rachel cheated on her and lied to her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then a flicker came to Max, showing Max’s grave, the possibility that she died in the car crash with William. It scared both girls, but Max started to realise it may mean one thing: she does not belong to this timeline. And that’s when I understood what was the symbolism behind the cover of this issue. Max said that those flickers, other realities were pulling her stronger and stronger, and it hurt her more and more. I think in that moment it became clear to Chloe that Max would leave her, would leave her timeline. Max was scared of it, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-max-grave.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-max-grave&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Maybe Max was never meant to be alive in this timeline?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s so hard to explain. It’s like… this reality is pushing me out. It’s like every Max that ever was is crossed over and confused in me. Like all the jumping displaced her… me… and… maybe there’s a Max who’s meant to be here… and she wants her universe back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max and Chloe went back to Blackwell where Chloe, rather unexpectedly, thanked Max and said her goodbyes. She already knew what Max was going to do. She knew she would lose her, and she would lose her soon. But she was ready to let Max go, because she said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I love you too much to see you hurting, Max Caulfield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-goodbye-kiss.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-goodbye-kiss&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This time it was Chloe who kissed Max goodbye&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning the High Seas arrived to Arcadia Bay to offer Max and Chloe their support, should the girls need it. But Max and Chloe had more important thing to do. Max took her photo from the wallet, the very photo seen in the first issue, and said to Chloe she was going to use that photo not to jump, but rather to access the transect that would allow Max to choose the right reality, the one Max should be in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next two frames, showing Max slowly fading away, her head rested on Chloe’s shoulder… It hurt like hell. Poor Max. Poor, brave Max… Her last dialogue with Chloe was so touching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I wish we could stay like this forever.”&lt;br /&gt;
“Somewhere out there… we do.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then Max was gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-max-demise.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-max-demise&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;May you find your peace, Max…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max found herself in space between realities, in space where she had to make an ultimate choice. And she did. She chose a reality to live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Chloe… You’re my anchor. You’ve always been my anchor. And wherever I find myself I know you’ll be there. But your whole life, you’ve had choices made for you, and I’m no less guilty. And so now I choose your choice. You get to choose, Chloe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-home-white.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-home-white&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max found herself on Santa Monica beach. Facing Chloe and… Rachel. When Chloe saw Max she was astonished. She did not expect Max and it appears that she hasn’t seen Max in a long time, living the dream with Rachel. So the ultimate reality Max found herself in was the one where Chloe had been happy with Rachel in Los Angeles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Gimme your best shot, life. I’m ready for whatever you throw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow. I really don’t know what to say. I definitely did not expect that ending. I expected Chloe to end up dead, or erased from the timeline, or Max rewinding herself out of existence, or something like that. This is definitely much better ending that one could hope for, in a way that Max is alive, Chloe is alive, heck, even Rachel is alive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-santa-monica.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-santa-monica&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A new reality, a new timeline full of possibilities. A timeline where Chloe and Rachel are alive and live together.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if this is a happy ending then why I’m so sad? Max choose the reality she thought was the best for Chloe, but had been Chloe aware of other possibilities, would she let Max choose this exact timeline, or would she rather have Max make a different choice? In this life Chloe and Rachel are together, they’ve been together for some time, and Max only now appeared again in Chloe’s life. I don’t think there is any possibility that in this reality Max and Chloe will end up together, and I definitely do not believe in Amberpricefield. So for Max it is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a happy ending, nor is it for the Chloe that was left behind in Arcadia Bay on the morning of the memorial ceremony. And if this Chloe was already happy with Rachel, does she really need Max at her side? And as a who? A fifth wheel? An awkward friend from the past?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t say I’m content with this ending, although it was still better than I expected. I hoped for something different, though. I simply hoped for a happy Pricefield ending, nothing more. I just wanted Max and Chloe finally be happy together. I doubt they will be as happy in this reality as they would have been in one of the others. But maybe Max will find her strength and happiness in the sacrifice she made for Chloe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish the girls that their Santa Monica dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yay&quot;&gt;Yay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chloe is alive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Max is alive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rachel is alive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the goodbye kiss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Max’s final words in this comic book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nay&quot;&gt;Nay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;so many things left unexplained&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Max sacrificed her happiness for her idea of Chloe’s happiness&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chloe was left alone in Arcadia Bay in the original reality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no Pricefield&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we still don’t know what the memorial looks like&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overall-summary-in-three-words&quot;&gt;Overall summary in three words&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;poignant, surprising, unfulfilling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="comicbooks" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="chloeprice" /><category term="rachelamber" /><category term="arcadiabay" /><category term="series" /><category term="review" /><category term="recap" /><category term="liscomicbook" /><summary type="html">It is done. I’ve read the fourth and the final issue of Life is Strange comic book, the one concluding the Dust story arc. Did Max manage to solve the mystery of parallel realities? What happened to Chloe?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life is Strange comic book vol. 3 (Dust #3)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is Strange comic book vol. 3 (Dust #3)" /><published>2019-03-01T12:24:44+01:00</published><updated>2019-03-01T12:24:44+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-3/">&lt;p&gt;The second issue of Life is Strange comic book ended with a cliffhanger. I was seriously worried what would happen in the next volume and how Max would solve the mystery of the phenomena she had experienced.&lt;!--more--&gt; Will she be able to stop timelines from interlacing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://leziak.com/tags/liscomicbook/&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; you can find all my reviews of the comic book. As previously, this review had been written before I read the fourth issue, so I still don’t know how this story ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I opened vol. 3 with a heavy heart and the cover was not reassuring. It showed a set of Polaroids capturing Max in different places and in different positions. There were few shots of her face (one with a trace of blood under her nose), one of Max holding William’s camera, one of the girls holding their hands. In that one Max’s forearm was overlaid with a golden marker, something in a shape of a flower (rose, probably) decorating her skin. In the same golden letters someone wrote below &lt;em&gt;now you’ve got one too!&lt;/em&gt;, adding dozens of hearts, stars and smiley faces to the picture. When I looked carefully I realised that nearly every Polaroid was decorated or signed in a similar way, which indicated that it must have been Chloe’s doing. That was really cute, as she scribbled &lt;em&gt;SUPER MAX&lt;/em&gt; under a photo of Max’s face with closed eyes, in bold golden letters, adding stars around Max’s head. But why there were no Polaroids of Chloe, save for a single frame where both girls held their hands? Also, one photograph showed a blue butterfly perching on Max’s shoulder. I definitely don’t like where this is going…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-cover-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;lis-comic-book-cover-3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;After playing Life is Strange and reading this comic book I will never be able to look at Polaroids in the same way again&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recap pages were useful, but when I saw a name “Diana Ward” in the description, I sighed in disbelief. &lt;em&gt;Oh man, are you cereal?&lt;/em&gt; Why do they always have to make embarrassing typos in characters’ names? The same thing happened in &lt;em&gt;Welcome to Blackwell Academy&lt;/em&gt;, there was a typo in Max’s name, &lt;strong&gt;supposedly written by Max herself!&lt;/strong&gt; Is it that hard to proofread the whole thing before the release?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first page of the story normally contained Max’s thoughts and retrospections with a lot of butterflies, but this time there is nothing but the butterflies, flying calmly in the dark. I guess that’s because, as fas as we know, Max is unconscious at the beginning of this issue. The next page, however, forced me to use the internal supplies of patience I didn’t know I possessed. The High Seas got back again, in a short interlude, composing a new song and wondering how Max and Chloe handle seeing Arcadia Bay again. I don’t like the band. They annoy me, they don’t fit into my vision of Life is Strange. But I have to admit, the lyrics of their song–inspired by Max and Chloe–are powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;They say forever is a long time,&lt;br /&gt;
but I don’t hear a word they say.&lt;br /&gt;
They say forever is a long time,&lt;br /&gt;
but I guess I must have found a way&lt;br /&gt;
to bend the rules and the tides of time;&lt;br /&gt;
forever starts the day I make you mine.&lt;br /&gt;
With so much there between us,
so many things unsaid,&lt;br /&gt;
there are words I want to say to you&lt;br /&gt;
if I could only clear my head.&lt;br /&gt;
Can we forget about the past and draw a line?&lt;br /&gt;
Forever starts the day I make you mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next scene evoked so many emotions. Apparently Chloe had carried unconscious Max to her old room and looked after her while Max was recovering from the previous vision. Seeing Chloe’s room destroyed, the window broken, most of the posters torn apart, the globe lamp fallen, it was a difficult experience. But at the same time I felt that despite all the destruction, it is still Chloe’s room. Her punk style was still visible and even the tornado could not take that away from her. When Max woke up Chloe explained everything to her. I especially appreciated one thing she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While you were asleep I spent some time in the house. My house. I feel like… I know my parents didn’t choose to leave me, but it’s starting to sink in now that they really are both gone. Maybe I needed this chance to say goodbye. To “process” or whatever bullshit word they call it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m glad that Life is Strange comic book has finally tackled this issue. As I mentioned in previous reviews, this adds to the realism of the story and makes it more believable. It is hopeful that Chloe chose to accept the loss of Joyce instead of hiding behind the wall of anger and frustration as she did after William had passed away. Maybe that’s because she has Max at her side now, maybe that’s because seeing the storm and its horrors changed her. Nevertheless, Chloe seems to be more mature, ready to handle whatever the world can throw at her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly a blue jay appeared in Chloe’s room, trying to get out through a broken window. I appreciated this little scene, a reminder of the moment when Max had saved a blue jay (maybe the very same one?) in Joyce and David’s bedroom in original Life is Strange. This time it was Chloe who set the bird free. There was something symbolic in that act, just like if by letting the bird fly away Chloe has also accepted that her mom is gone, letting the sorrow be carried away on blue, feathered wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-chloe-birdie.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;chloe-birdie&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;“You’ve been resurrected, birdie. Fly, be free!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later that day girls arrived at the Blackwell Academy, or what was left of it. There was a lot of nostalgia to handle, both for them and me. And of course, weird things started happening again. Max met Warren, alive and well. Warren, who &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; about the storm and people who died, not Warren from a timeline where there was no storm. That was super-weird. In the previous issue of the comic book Joyce told Max that there was no storm after Chloe died, while in Warren’s timeline &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; storm and Chloe’s death happened. Does it matter that Max is seeing more than one alternative timeline?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One comment that Warren made during his dialogue with Max is worth mentioning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;(…) I feel like I could look into those windows and see the old gang sat in classes like nothing has changed. (…) Not that, you know, I ever make habits of looking through windows at people or…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obviously refers to an easter egg at the beginning of episode 2 of Life is Strange, when Max could see Warren secretly starring at windows of her dorm room. That was one of things that made me lost all sympathy I might have left for this guy. His behaviour was downright creepy. But let’s go back to the comic book. Chloe has realised that Max is talking to someone that’s not there, and when she took Max’s hand to join her vision, something bad happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chloe didn’t join Max’s vision like she did in Two Whales diner, but instead her head started to hurt really bad and she got a nosebleed, just like Max. The vision was gone and both girls found themselves alone in front of the Blackwell Academy. But then another vision started and someone was approaching them with a newspaper in hand, smiling and waving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rachel Amber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a whole new level of weirdness. On a scale of 1 to 10 I’d rate it as 12 and a half. It was yet another timeline or alternative reality, or whatever you call it. Rachel told Max and Chloe that Jefferson, after being fired from Blackwell for stealing school supplies (some duct tape for his Dark Room, perhaps?) got arrested in another school after he slept with one of his students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-rachel-max-chloe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;rachel-chloe-max-hands&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Rachel in the alternative timeline was as tactful and diplomatic as in the original one&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the vision came to past, Chloe asked Max if she had been jumping, and then girls &lt;strong&gt;checked their watches.&lt;/strong&gt; I was wondering since the vol. 1 why they started wearing watches, especially that they weren’t exactly in the girls’ style, and now one little mystery was finally explained. Apparently Max and Chloe periodically checked their watches to make sure they remained synced which would mean Max hasn’t been moving at a different pace through time, i.e. using her powers or photojumping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chloe needed some time alone to process things after seeing Rachel (or her projection, or her ghost, or her alternative self?), so she took a few steps away from Max, who was still sitting at the edge of a fountain… with another Chloe. Okay, now my weird-o-meter showed 15. Suddenly &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; Chloes disappeared and Max was left alone, slowly succumbing to slumber or some malady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lis-comic-book-max-maladie.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;max-maladie&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This was the most scaring scene in the third issue of Life is Strange comic book&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Max woke up Warren was sitting next to her. Warren she had met before, the one who remembered both the storm and Chloe’s death. He was aware that Max did not belong to his timeline, and explained to her what possibly happened. That was insanely crazy (weird-o-meter showed &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;err&lt;/code&gt; and stopped working altogether), but at least I’m happy I finally got some answers regarding the whole alternating timelines thing. Warren was working on it with another version of Max, the one from his own timeline, and they figured out that these events, flickers, as they called them, they were actually instances of parallel words, occasionally merging or intertwining for a moment of two. So Max was in fact not only travelling through the time, she was travelling to the other worlds. When Max came back to her own world, there was no sign of either Warren or Chloe. And, as always, that’s where the issue had to end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wowsers. That was a lot to digest. The whole idea of not only different timelines, but different &lt;em&gt;realities&lt;/em&gt;. Now I know what is happening, but I still don’t know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; is it happening. I sincerely hope that the final issue of Dust story arc will answer that question. I’m still not over the fact that the ending of original Life is Strange ignored most of the mysteries introduced earlier in the game and left so many questions unanswered. I hope this won’t be the case with Life is Strange comic book. This issue was good, but…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…there is still no Pricefield in sight. On one hand I get it. Not every fan who chose to save Chloe in Life is Strange automatically assumed there was a romantic relationship between the girls and would like to go down that path. On the other hand Amberprice was a kind of a thing in Before The Storm and we are still being denied some most eagerly expected, authentic love between Max and Chloe. To be honest, I don’t expect it will appear in the final issue. I think that creators of the comic book will hold Pricefield just out of reach of the fans, for whatever reason they conjure. Well, I guess I’ll find out soon, reading vol. 4 later today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yay&quot;&gt;Yay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chloe’s room&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;saving the blue jay&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chloe coming to peace with her loss&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rachel Amber&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nay&quot;&gt;Nay!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the whole Seattle interlude with the band&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Warren&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;too much red hue in Blackwell scenes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no Pricefield in sight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;overall-summary-in-three-words&quot;&gt;Overall summary in three words&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nostalgic, red-hued, parallel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="comicbooks" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="chloeprice" /><category term="rachelamber" /><category term="arcadiabay" /><category term="series" /><category term="review" /><category term="recap" /><category term="liscomicbook" /><summary type="html">The second issue of Life is Strange comic book ended with a cliffhanger. I was seriously worried what would happen in the next volume and how Max would solve the mystery of the phenomena she had experienced.</summary></entry></feed>