<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leziak.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://leziak.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-14T14:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leziak.com</title><subtitle>Articles about technology, photography, art, writing and games</subtitle><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><entry><title type="html">In the search of a perfect writing setup</title><link href="https://leziak.com/perfect-writing-setup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In the search of a perfect writing setup" /><published>2023-11-14T14:20:03+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-14T14:20:03+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/search-perfect-writing-setup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/perfect-writing-setup/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been looking for a way to optimise my writing workflow and find a perfect setup for many years. I have tried numerous solutions, both software (word processors, markdown editors, notepads) and hardware-related (keyboards in almost every shape and form). The more I looked for a perfect setup the more I doubted it had ever existed. Experimenting, however, brought me an immense joy, even if paired with a bit of frustration at times.<!--more--></p>

<p>I have always appreciated writing. It is a truly fascinating process, in which one can immortalise their thoughts, opinions and memories. I have learned more about myself by reading my old journals than through any other form of retrospection. But for me the act of writing is strongly affected by technical aspects and the smoothness of the overall experience. That is why I write a lot by hand, and use fountain pens on a daily basis. I care about the details of the process, as they can help me to immerse myself in the story I am telling without any external disruptions. That is why the quality of the writing workflow and specifics of the writing setup are so important to me.</p>

<p>For handwriting, I have already found the perfect solution<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>: a combination of a comfortable fountain pen with an excellent nib, good quality ink and acid-free paper. My daily driver is <strong>Aurora Talentum GT</strong>, currently paired with <strong>Aurora 100th Year Special Edition Gray</strong> ink and <strong>Leuchtturm 1917</strong> notebook.</p>

<p>For typewriting, I have tried many solutions. It is relatively easy to find a good stationary setup. If one has no intention to move the hardware very often (or at all), a good mechanical keyboard with a high resolution monitor can be paired with a multitude of devices, from a regular PC, through a Mac, to a tablet or similar device. Having a dedicated space for a stationary setup means that one can invest in hardware that is optimised in terms of ergonomy and usability. An excellent solution would be a second, e-ink computer screen, used solely for writing, although they are hard to come by and pretty expensive (one of the best examples is <a href="https://onyxboox.com/boox_mira">Onyx Boox Mira</a>). I would love to use it as a dedicated computer screen for writing, yet I cannot justify such expense.</p>

<p>E-ink screens are superior to regular LCD or LED ones, due to lack of a backlight and eye strain that comes with it. They have also excellent readability in the sunlight, which may not be a top priority for a stationary setup, but is a huge factor for a mobile writing station. There have been a few projects trying to use the advantage of an e-ink screen in a portable writing device, with mixed results.</p>

<p>One of the most notable examples is the Freewrite Smart Typewriter, produced by Astrohaus. I <a href="../freewrite/">wrote about Freewrite back in 2016</a>, when the first generation was available for purchase. The device combines a mechanical keyboard with an e-ink screen and some basic sync functions in order to deliver a distraction-free typing experience. Currently Astrohaus sells the third generation of the Freewrite, which, while virtually identical to its predecessor in terms of visuals, offers certain software enhancements. The synchronisation feature is also more developed, allowing for wireless sharing of the draft to Google Drive, e-mail or Postbox (Astrohaus’ proprietary cloud service). I must admit that I was seriously considering buying the newest generation of the Freewrite Smart Typewriter (they also sell a portable device called Freewrite Traveller, but it lacks mechanical keyboard and the screen, while still e-ink, misses the built-in illumination). Two things that ultimately pushed me <em>away</em> from purchasing a Freewrite were: unreliability of the device and the unfriendliness of the company towards users.</p>

<p>Both in the unofficial Discord server dedicated to Freewrite users, as well as their subreddit, there are many, many complains from dissatisfied users. Those users lost large parts of their drafts due to software glitches, had issues with syncing their drafts wirelessly due to company’s proprietary cloud service being down or had their Freewrite Smart Typewriters or Travellers rendered unusable due to hardware failure (battery swelling, circuit board failure, keys being stuck or unresponsive, etc.). To make things worse, Astrohaus offers only limited, 90-days warranty for their products, which is absolutely ridiculous considering the 500-600$ price tag for regular models (and even higher for special or limited editions). One can find many posts on Reddit in which users lament due to Astrohaus wanting an exorbitant amount of money to repair their broken Freewrites, and some hefty two-way shipping costs on the top of that. And good luck if you want to try and replace the broken part yourself: design choices made by Astrohaus make it nearly impossible, due to, for example, battery connectors being soldered (!) to the PCB. It is hard to explain such decision by anything other than hostility towards users wanting to repair the device on their own, since there is <em>plenty</em> of space inside Freewrite’s chassis to use a regular detachable connector instead. Heck, Astrohaus could even sell the replacement batteries themselves, extending the lifespan of their products, but apparently it is not in their best interest. I refuse to support a company with such dubious standards.</p>

<p>There is a viable alternative for people looking for a mobile e-ink device suitable for writing: Remarkable 2. It is an e-ink tablet which allows for the creation of handwritten notes, offers handwriting OCR for many languages, PDF annotations and more. Some time ago a Remarkable Type Folio premiered, an external keyboard in a form of a folio cover. It allows one to use Remarkable as an e-ink typewriter. Although Remarkable Type Folio does not have a mechanical keyboard, it still offers a portable writing solution with an e-ink screen free of backlight-induced eye strain. It lacks illumination, just like Smartwrite Traveller, so is not usable in a dark without access to an external light source. Unfortunately, the Remarkable Type Folio supports only a handful of keyboard layouts, with the vast majority of European languages missing. It means that one cannot enter language-specific diacritics, which sadly is a deal-breaker for me. Although I write most of my essays in English, I want to retain the option to write in Polish if necessary.</p>

<p>This is almost as far as the e-ink options go, both Freewrite and Remarkable do not have competition in their respective categories<sup id="fnref:fn2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. It is a shame, thought, because I believe users could benefit greatly from innovation and price drop forced by competition in the market. Nevertheless, both devices serve a niche purpose, and there is not much demand for an e-ink typewriter or word processor in general. Most people are okay with starring at backlit LCD or OLED screens and are probably not even aware of benefits of the electronic paper.</p>

<p>My current option for writing on the go is an 11-inch iPad Pro with Paperlike screen protector and Logitech Folio Touch. It does not offer full benefits of an e-ink screen, but it does reduce glare and resultant eye-strain. I have been a fan of writing on iPad from the beginning. I used the original Smart Keyboard Folio for 2018 iPad Pro, but sadly the quality of that thing was abysmal. I had Smart Keyboard Folio break down on me after a year and a half, and its replacement followed the same course. After that I decided to make an exception and <em>not</em> buy Apple’s Magic Keyboard for the new 2020 iPad Pro, mostly because I was still wary of all the issues with their folio keyboard. Plus, the price of that accessory, even for the 11-inch model, was eye-watering (in fact, it still is). Since my iPad Pro from 2020 does not support some new functions like Stage Manager on external display, I decided to keep it for as long as possible, and only buy Magic Keyboard for the new model, once I decide it is time to upgrade. And since the current model has been working like a charm for four years now, it might not happen anytime soon.</p>

<p>I am thinking about experimenting with an external mechanical keyboard connected to an e-ink tablet working on Android, or to a Raspberry Pi connected to an e-ink display. The first solution would be trivially easy to implement, but also quite expensive (e-ink tablets, especially ones with a colour screen, still cost a lot), while the second one would allow me to save some money but for the price of time taken to make everything work well together. For now, I continue to use my iPad Pro, hoping that one day I will find that elusive perfect writing setup.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>It should be noted, naturally, that what is the perfect solution for <em>me</em> may not necessarily be the perfect solution for anyone else. I am not trying to arbitrary push my setup as the best option here, but merely to show you one of many possibilities. <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>People often compare Remarkable 2 and Kindle Scribe in general, but for the purpose of typewriting Kindle is useless, as it does not support any external keyboards. <a href="#fnref:fn2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="freewrite" /><category term="remarkable" /><category term="eink" /><category term="keyboard" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been looking for a way to optimise my writing workflow and find a perfect setup for many years. I have tried numerous solutions, both software (word processors, markdown editors, notepads) and hardware-related (keyboards in almost every shape and form). The more I looked for a perfect setup the more I doubted it had ever existed. Experimenting, however, brought me an immense joy, even if paired with a bit of frustration at times.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I made a Pixelfed account</title><link href="https://leziak.com/pixelfed-account/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I made a Pixelfed account" /><published>2023-08-08T12:56:24+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-08T12:56:24+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/pixelfed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/pixelfed-account/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I’ve created a <a href="https://pixelfed.social/vertiser">Pixelfed</a> account to share my everyday and casual photographs online. <!--more--> I had deleted my Instagram account a couple of years ago and I’ve been trying various replacements since. While Instagram inarguably has the largest user base, it also has serious privacy issues, as it (or actually Meta, the parent company of Instagram and Facebook) collects tremendous amount of data about its users, their devices, location, habits, interests and multitude of other things. All this for a single purpose: to serve users the most effective ads possible.</p>

<p>I abhor Meta’s dubious ethics, therefore I was looking for Instagram alternative. I’ve tried various services, of which <a href="https://www.vsco.co">VSCO</a> briefly captured my attention. Ultimately I was discouraged by the recurring subscription cost and the fact that it felt very hermetic and monotonous. With the increased popularity of federated social media I started to publish photographs on my <a href="https://mastodon.social/@vertiser">Mastodon</a> first<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but it didn’t feel like an optimal solution. I considered creating a separated account in federated social media specialised in sharing photographs, namely Pixelfed. That thought stayed with me for a couple of months, but only at the end of July I finally took the step to create an account and upload my first photographs.</p>

<p>The whole experience has been positive so far and I intend to keep my Pixelfed profile. As for its content, it will be similar to VSCO and, previously, Instagram: casual, everyday photographs, occasionally mixed with some travel shots. If you are looking for some thematically consistent series of fine art photographs, feel free to check out the <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/vertiser/gallery/71989994/photographs">Photography gallery on my deviantART profile</a>. DeviantART is still the main place where I publish more sophisticated works.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I had an account since 2018, but I hardly posted anything until I started seriously considering leaving Twitter in 2022) <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="photography" /><category term="technology" /><category term="pixelfed" /><category term="socialmedia" /><category term="vsco" /><category term="federated" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently I’ve created a Pixelfed account to share my everyday and casual photographs online.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I will play every game I own</title><link href="https://leziak.com/play-all-games/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I will play every game I own" /><published>2023-07-17T11:15:09+02:00</published><updated>2023-07-17T11:15:09+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/play-all-games</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/play-all-games/"><![CDATA[<p>If you are a gamer, you probably have a long list of titles in your library, and chances are, you have not played all of those games. Thanks to spontaneous purchases, Steam Summer Sales, Black Friday offers, etc. we tend to accumulate more and more games at attractive prices. ‘It was a bargain, and I wanted to play this game anyway’ one may justify their purchase to themselves (<em>I</em> do quite often, actually). In the end many of those games never see the proverbial light of day, and they stay on shelves of our digital libraries, collecting virtual dust. <!--more--></p>

<p>During my decades of gaming I realised that, most of the time, I prefer to replay known titles rather than to try out something new. I have certain favourites that have a permanent place in my heart, like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gothic_(video_game)">Gothic</a>, Skyrim, The Witcher series, and I like to get back to them whenever I can. But the problem arising from this attitude is, I rarely try something new. Buying Nintendo Switch in 2019 has partially alleviated the issue, allowing me to try many new games, especially when travelling. But it has not solved the problem with many titles staying in my library, never even installed, or only opened briefly for a couple of minutes. At some point I decided to change that, so I created the <a href="../all-games/">All Games</a> project.</p>

<p><strong><a href="../all-games/">The All Games</a> project is my attempt at playing every single game I have in my gaming library (or <em>all</em> my gaming libraries, to be precise).</strong> I have an intention to play every game on my many accounts: Steam, GOG, Origin, as well as standalone games I bought digitally or physically over the years. The goal is, to actually experience all the games I own. So I do not want to only open them, finish the first chapter, mission or quest and be done with it, but get involved with the core aspect of each game. This rule does not specify that I must have a 100% completion of all games<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, nor that I need to get all of the game’s achievements/trophies on a respective platform. I do not need to finish the main storyline or quest, but I must engage in each game. For certain games I may add my own goals or achievements that I want to get. Once I obtain them all, I will consider game fully completed from my point of view.</p>

<p>Should I inevitably buy some new games along the way, they will be added to the goal; they will affect the progression and count towards the total number of games to play. Both the list of the games and the progression will be updated regularly. Naturally, games that I had already played and completed will be included in the list. I have no incentive to do things that I do not like in my free time, so if there is a game that displeasures me, I will abandon it at certain point, but not before making several attempts to discover some likeable aspects.</p>

<p>There is no specific timeframe or a deadline for the whole endeavour. I treat it as an ongoing personal project, a way of making sure I fully utilise the entertainment potential of games I already own. <a href="../all-games/">The progress page</a> will be updated regularly, to reflect the current status of the project.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>as a matter of fact, it would be impossible, since many games do not have a measurable progress or completion <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="project" /><category term="games" /><category term="onlinegames" /><category term="gothic" /><category term="allgames" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you are a gamer, you probably have a long list of titles in your library, and chances are, you have not played all of those games. Thanks to spontaneous purchases, Steam Summer Sales, Black Friday offers, etc. we tend to accumulate more and more games at attractive prices. ‘It was a bargain, and I wanted to play this game anyway’ one may justify their purchase to themselves (I do quite often, actually). In the end many of those games never see the proverbial light of day, and they stay on shelves of our digital libraries, collecting virtual dust.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The dusk of Reddit</title><link href="https://leziak.com/dusk-of-reddit/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The dusk of Reddit" /><published>2023-06-21T08:24:45+02:00</published><updated>2023-06-21T08:24:45+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/dusk-reddit</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/dusk-of-reddit/"><![CDATA[<p>I have noticed that with each passing year I have fewer social media accounts. On the first of January 2023 I permanently deleted my Twitter account and now I let go of Reddit as well. Both decisions are rooted in a similar issue: questionable ethics and actions of the respective CEO. <!--more-->I do not believe an explanation is in order for me leaving Twitter. Elon Musk’s irresponsible and erratic behaviour has been widely described and discussed on the web. But what about Reddit?</p>

<p>Two months ago Reddit <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/reddit/comments/12qwagm/an_update_regarding_reddits_api/">announced changes in the access to their API</a>, an action that bears dire consequences for the third party apps many people used to browse Reddit, like Apollo for iOS or RIF for Android. To cut the long story short: third party apps will have been basically forced to shutdown by the end of June due to gargantuan costs of use of Reddit API starting in July. There is a <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/apolloapp/comments/144f6xm/apollo_will_close_down_on_june_30th_reddits/">detailed explanation of the situation</a> posted by Christian Selig, the developer of Apollo and I encourage you to dig deeper into the conversation, to uncover the whole picture of Reddit malevolence.</p>

<p>The main issue that arises both from Twitter and Reddit examples is, the social media as we know them became so goal-oriented that they lost the big picture in the process. The goal, in virtually all cases of commercial/centralised social media is simply to multiply the revenue <em>in perpetuo</em>. And anyone who has even rudimentary knowledge of how the world is working knows that it cannot happen. Profit cannot rise exponentially, even if that’s what investors or owners would expect. And looking for a way to further maximise profit, to monetise the hell out of a social media website and its users can have dreadful consequences. We know what happened to Twitter, and now similar thing is happening to Reddit. Somehow Reddit CEO<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> believed that he had a right to own the users, their content and their work, and monetise on that while at the same time taking away their choice of Reddit clients that offered superior experience to both Reddit website and the first party app. Mass protest in the form of many subreddits going dark (i.e. restricting posting or visibility) arose on the 12th of June and lasted for 48 hours, however Reddit admins started to do a whole set of unethical things, including threatening moderators of subreddits that were still protesting after the 14th that they would be removed and a new moderation team would be installed in their place, manually changing subreddits restrictions against the will of the moderators or users, removing or suspending moderation teams and so on. It should be noted that all those actions were approved (or even sanctioned) by the CEO, whose main goal is apparently to show everyone that he is right (despite the fact he really isn’t), even if it’s destroying Reddit in the process.</p>

<p>I have no doubts that once the dust settle there will still be plenty of users on the platform, and most of the top subreddits will have new, pro-Reddit moderation teams. But the Reddit we know is already lost. Many people have already left or will leave Reddit in the very near future, and, what apparently is not yet obvious to the sorry excuse of a CEO, those would be people who actually were <em>creating</em> content on Reddit, people who added value to the website. Because without the creators, the moderators, the people who care about their communities, Reddit is only a shell. And pretty useless one, at that.</p>

<p>A few days before the going dark protests I have already scrambled and removed all my content on Reddit, including posts, comments, conversations. Two days later I have made a <a href="https://gdpr.eu/data-privacy/">GDPR request</a> under Article 15 to obtain all my data and check whether Reddit has truly removed all the informations I ordered them to. Once I confirm there is no content authored by me left on their platform, I’m permanently deleting my account <strong>[Update: I have already done it]</strong>. I have already removed it from the Social media links sections on the <a href="../about/">About</a> page. If you want to delete your Reddit account as well, I strongly recommend you delete your content first, as to not give Reddit anything to monetise from for free. Normally even if you delete your account all your content (posts, comments, etc.) are still there, only with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[deleted]</code> placeholder instead of your actual username. That is why it is important to use a tool like <a href="https://redact.dev">Redact</a> first, to overwrite and then delete your content before deleting the account itself.</p>

<p>I’m leaving Reddit without regrets. There is no way I would support an unethical conduct or enable an evil person to hurt online communities by adding one more user to the head count. I hope that Reddit will crash and burn, and people find an alternative that would be more user-friendly. Federated social networks come to mind here, as their fundamental characteristics of being decentralised yet federated make them immune to egregious acts of a single bad actor like Reddit’s CEO. If you are looking for a Reddit replacement, options in the federated social networks include <a href="https://kbin.social">kbin.social</a>, <a href="https://join-lemmy.org">lemmy</a> and many other projects. You can also check <a href="https://sub.rehab">alternatives for specific subreddits</a> to find an optimal place to continue your discussion and engagement in certain communities. That is the beauty of open internet: one or even many evil people cannot monopolise your experience, nor force you to use their social media platforms. People will always seek safe and free alternatives. Just remember to be mindful and tread carefully as you discover new places on the internet. Not all communities, websites or servers have the same rules regarding privacy, handling of your data, etc. But this is something we all should have learned by this point.</p>

<p>Whatever your post-Reddit journey will be, I wish you good luck.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I deliberately omit his name here, as he is simply a spoiled pitiful idiot who does not deserve any recognition whatsoever. <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="technology" /><category term="internet" /><category term="reddit" /><category term="socialmedia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have noticed that with each passing year I have fewer social media accounts. On the first of January 2023 I permanently deleted my Twitter account and now I let go of Reddit as well. Both decisions are rooted in a similar issue: questionable ethics and actions of the respective CEO.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The persistence of information</title><link href="https://leziak.com/persistence-of-information/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The persistence of information" /><published>2023-05-09T08:51:59+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-09T08:51:59+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/persistence-of-information</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/persistence-of-information/"><![CDATA[<p>In the modern digital age we are facing a threat of losing information at an unprecedented scale.<!--more--></p>

<p>Internet in general, and World Wide Web in particular, is a one-of-a-kind place accumulating tremendous amount of knowledge. Ever since the WWW was conceived in 1991<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> it has helped millions of people to share various pieces of information, from favourite pasta recipes to books reviews. If not for the web, we would not be in the place we are now, both socially and technologically.</p>

<p>90’s and 00’s were, in my opinion, the golden age of the Internet. People were discovering what the Internet was all about. It was an uncharted territory and everyone of us felt like an explorer in the middle of an unknown jungle. There were plenty of treasures to discover, but it often depended on one’s abilities to look for the right thing in the right place (that’s also why in the early days it was called “surfing the internet”, not simply “browsing”). Web catalogues were popular, grouping pages in thematic categories (i.e. “sports”, “motorisation”, “cooking”, “gardening” and so on). Search engines were not a thing yet. You could not simply type your keyword, press Enter and get results a second later. It was more like looking through a phonebook (although I’m aware that this comparison might be lost anyway for the younger generation). Websites were not added to catalogues automatically. For each catalogue one wanted their website to be added to, they had to undergo the process manually, by either filling a form or contacting the webmaster. And there were <em>a lot</em> of catalogues to choose from.</p>

<p>The websites themselves were not perfect, by any standard, simply because there were hardly any standards to adhere to. Everyone tried to make their website look pretty, and for some it meant adding sparking GIFs as the background, for other it was bars with coloured moving text, for others — clip arts, etc. Digital cameras were not as popular, so photographs were not omnipresent, and videos were virtually nonexistent till the mid-00’s, mostly because many people still used dial-up connections, which had very limited speed (and by saying “limited” I really mean that: 56 <em>kilobits per second</em> was the maximum speed of a standard dial-up connection, which correspond to a total bandwidth of <em>8 KB per second</em> (upload and download combined).</p>

<p>Still, despite the obvious shortcomings, the early web (sometimes also called “the web 1.0”) was inherently <em>personal</em>. People shared their thoughts, knowledge and opinions not only through their personal websites, but also on various <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_forum">internet forums</a> and, in certain cases, even beyond the web itself (e.g. via <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usenet_newsgroup">newsgroups</a>, which used usenet protocol). While every internet forum was an independent entity, the whole community of the early Internet shared similar attitude. It was a social place and a sharing place. Forums were ran by private individuals, whose goal was not to monetise or track the users to sell their data, but to simply maintain a discussion in a semi-public space. Informations posted on forums, newsgroups or personal websites were widely available to almost everyone. Even if a given forum had privacy settings requesting guests to log in in order to view discussions or download attachments, etc., it was usually only a brief obstacle, as anyone was free to register and to make use of the knowledge and informations provided. And those informations remained unobstructed, easy to search for, easy to use. It was even easier with personal websites, since they didn’t require any registration at all in order to access their content, making the knowledge posted there available. And the knowledge available was sometimes so specific or niche, it was unobtainable in any other way.</p>

<p>I still remember one time when I contacted the owner of a website devoted to hamsters, because I had one that seemed to be allergic to regular food and the vet I went to was unable to help me due to their lack of experience with small pets. That website owner had published an incredibly detailed article on what and when she was giving to her hamsters in order to keep them in good health and prevent allergies. Keep in mind it was 2001, and one could not simply find such informations easily. After I contacted her she gave me some helpful tips on what to do and thanks to that I was able to make my hamster healthy and happy again. I would have not been able to do that, had the access to that website been restricted somehow.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, we are long past that point in the history of the web and Internet. The rise of giants like Google and, later, Facebook has forever changed the shape of the Internet. Now private, personal websites are few and far between, and the vast majority of informations is being shared via social media. Instead of private, people-oriented internet forums we have Facebook groups, instead of personal websites and blogs we have tweets, status updates and shorts. This causes a multitude of problems, including:</p>
<ul>
  <li>walled garden: content being only accessible by people registered to the given social network (e.g. Instagram forcing people to log in in order to view public profiles)</li>
  <li>content already accepted being subject to later removal/alteration/censorship due to a shift in company policy (e.g. Tumblr NSFW content ban)</li>
  <li>users being tracked while browsing content on a platform (basically <em>any</em> social media right now)</li>
  <li>unexpected restrictions of various type due to changes of the ownership/policy/goals (i.e. Elon Musk blocking Twitter users from linking to other social media)</li>
  <li>content not being available on older hardware or software, or via privacy modes restricting ad targeting or user profiling</li>
</ul>

<p>These problems are merely the tip of an iceberg. The whole shift towards social media as the primary space for sharing, well, basically <em>anything</em>, caused a great websites extinction. Long gone are private websites where the owner shared precious knowledge on a niche subject, there is hardly anything left of internet forums where people passionately discussed miscellaneous topics. Usenet groups are totally obsolete now. Many of my web bookmarks saved 10, 15 years ago are dead now, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Link_rot">link rot</a> is spreading and may be even a bigger problem in the future. Although we live in an age of information, we are losing incredible amount of data. Some of the websites of the old Internet have been <a href="https://web.archive.org">archived</a> in a bare-bones form, but it does not preserve how the website looked like when it was alive. It can give us a glimpse of a lost past, but nothing more.</p>

<p>Naturally, there are many reasons for why certain websites or articles are no longer available. Some of them have been hosted under a free subdomain, and the service providing free subdomains has ceased operation. Some were located on personal computers that acted as servers, and were lost when the computer was no longer online, perhaps too old, too loud, too power hungry. Some were removed when the owner did not pay for their hosting on commercial servers. Some people have inevitably lost interest in maintaining their website or being an admin of an internet forum. Many simply passed away, and their websites eventually succumbed to lack of maintenance or failed payment for another hosting/domain renewal period. Whatever the reason, it all ultimately leads to the loss of information. We loose knowledge from people who can no longer share it, we loose stories from people that cannot tell them anymore. We loose many precious things before we even realise how precious they were. This is why the persistence of information is so important.</p>

<p>We cannot afford to loose information. The knowledge published online should be preserved whenever it is possible. What has been lost cannot be recovered, but we may take action to make sure that the current state of the web knowledge in its general meaning is preserved. First and foremost, <strong>own your words!</strong> This catchphrase simply means that one should primarily post their content, regardless of its type (articles, photos, drawings, etc.) on their own website. Whenever you upload your work of art, that art being old Grandma’s recipe, a National Geographic-worthy photograph or review of a book you read, upload it to the part of the web that belongs to you. If you post your content on Twitter, or Facebook, or Tumblr, or any other website, it is subject to the website’s terms of service, and can be deleted or banned on a whim. If the website goes down for any reason, all your stuff goes down with it. If you decide to leave that social network (like during the Twitter exodus last November), you leave your content behind. Of course you can re-publish it in a new place, but people who had the link to your original post won’t be redirected to the new place. By sharing your content, knowledge and information on your own website you retain full control. You can change servers and hosting providers as many times as you want; as long as you keep your domain up, the URL will always be the same. I, myself, have changed hosting providers five times since 2015, while this website still remained operational.</p>

<p>There is a concept that describes this premise in a greater detail, called <a href="https://indieweb.org/POSSE">POSSE</a> — Publish [on your] Own Site, Syndicate Elsewhere. While keeping information on one own’s website does not eliminate the risk of deletion due to abandoning the project, or one’s untimely demise, it makes that knowledge more accessible to people on the Internet. I know that one could argue that social media have much further reach than a personal website, but the whole affair is not about the reach, views or impressions. It is about <em>persistence</em>. I believe that owning your own words is a key to information persistence on the Internet.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>technically, Tim Berners-Lee shared his vision of what we now call the web in 1989, but the web itself only began its public existence two years later <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="technology" /><category term="writing" /><category term="information" /><category term="website" /><category term="internet" /><category term="history" /><category term="ownyourwords" /><category term="posse" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the modern digital age we are facing a threat of losing information at an unprecedented scale.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Florence — a short (yet lovely) little game</title><link href="https://leziak.com/florence-game/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Florence — a short (yet lovely) little game" /><published>2023-03-15T07:40:02+01:00</published><updated>2023-03-15T07:40:02+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/florence-game</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/florence-game/"><![CDATA[<p>Some time ago I had an opportunity to play Florence. It is a short but interesting game about life, happiness and discovering your true self. <!--more--> The game presents the story of Florence Yeoh, a woman in her mid-twenties, who follows her daily routine and works in an office job. The job, as well as her whole life, is monotonous and does not make her happy. However, one day when walking down the street she hears a street performer playing a cello. She decides to listen to his music, and that’s how she meets Krish.</p>

<p>The rest of the game depicts their dates and relationship. While the story is linear (one can only follow a planned path, and there are no decisions that change the final outcome), Florence feels very refreshing in a way. The player slowly discovers Florence’s relationship with Krish, from the initial honeymoon phase to the first fight and later conflicts. Most of one’s actions comes in a form of various mini games, and completing puzzles moves the story forward. I was playing Florence on Nintendo Switch and mini games utilised console’s controls in a proper way, although sometimes were a tiny bit annoying (i.e. when one had to be fairly precise while solving a jigsaw puzzle).</p>

<p>Florence is a short game — it took me about an hour to complete, although I was not in a hurry. One could probably finish the whole story in about twenty minutes, although I do not recommend that approach. The pleasure of Florence comes from exploring the game and its story, and rushing it would ruin the experience. I played Florence on Nintendo Switch and it looks like a perfect game to play on the go. It is beautifully immersive and makes morning commute go faster. Unfortunately it does not have big replay value, since the plot, mini games and ending are always the same. I wish developers had thought about adding some new content or ending unlocked once a player finishes the game for the first time.</p>

<p>Speaking of the ending, the final message of the game is bittersweet, although optimistic. I personally believe Florence would have benefited from a different approach. Nevertheless, I understand why developers chose what they did.</p>

<h3 id="yay">Yay!</h3>
<ul>
  <li>lovely aesthetics</li>
  <li>interesting story</li>
  <li>positive vibes</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="nay">Nay!</h3>
<ul>
  <li>the ending</li>
  <li>no player-dependent choices</li>
  <li>short</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="overall-summary-in-three-words">Overall summary in three words</h3>
<p><strong>immersive, refreshing, short</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="nintendoswitch" /><category term="florence" /><category term="review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some time ago I had an opportunity to play Florence. It is a short but interesting game about life, happiness and discovering your true self.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How my flight simulation journey began</title><link href="https://leziak.com/flight-sim-journey-beginning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How my flight simulation journey began" /><published>2023-02-01T12:01:50+01:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T12:01:50+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/flight-sim-journey-beginning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/flight-sim-journey-beginning/"><![CDATA[<p>Do you know those stories when someone had been loving airplanes from their early years, and they spent every free moment to learn about aviation, flight procedures, various aircraft and so on? It was nothing like this for me. <!--more--> I cannot recall a single defining moment that sparked my interest in aviation. I think it was more gradual, growing slowly without me noticing.</p>

<p>While I was not an aviation geek, I have always liked to watch some documentaries about airplanes, although there was no particular reason that I can pinpoint. Maybe it was because of the technology involved? Or physics of flight? Or just the awesomeness of aerial view? I have no idea. I only know that I had been watching Air Crash Investigation on National Geographic Channel for a few years and I found that series really… interesting (I don’t think that “entertaining” would be the right world, especially in the context of what was shown in the programme, but I truly liked watching new episodes and discovering reasons for failures that were reenacted).</p>

<p>I remember that at the end of 2017 I had a lot of free time. I was staying home alone after Christmas, till the 2nd or 3rd of January, since the rest of my family travelled to another city for a family meeting. I was a designated house-sitter, so I had to look after our house and a family dog. It was a nice although not necessary exciting time. I was spending evenings watching Marvel movies (basically did an Avengers marathon), I read some books, watched YouTube, but soon I found myself a bit bored. I decided, rather spontaneously, to check out some flight simulators for PC. Keep in mind that I was not familiar with the subject and knew nothing about the software or hardware required. I found a relatively cheap joystick and throttle set<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> on Amazon, that I ordered with express delivery, and after a short web search I found X-Plane 10 and bought its license.</p>

<p>Two days later the joystick and throttle set arrived, and after a brief configuration I opened X-Plane 10 to begin my first flight. I remember that once I launched X-Plane I was surprised that there was no such thing as “new mission” or “play” button, etc. I was a newbie back then, and I didn’t know yet that flight simulation is not a game and it would be rather depreciating to treat it as such. To be fair, I still don’t consider flight sim a game. It is a sort of entertainment, that’s for sure, but for me there is a distinctive difference between playing e.g. Skyrim or Minecraft, or GTA, and flight simulation. I suppose it is because, while in ordinary games I can do whatever I want, regardless of how real my actions are, in flight simulation it is much more enjoyable for me to try and imitate the realism of actual flight than to do some wild acrobatics that would probably end in a crash and a virtual crater on the ground (although there <em>were</em> many unintended crashes at the beginning of my flight sim journey; I was learning how to fly by trials and errors…).</p>

<p>It was an exhilarating experience, to perform the first successful flight in a flight simulator. I remember that I was proud of myself, even though my landing was probably rather hard (I didn’t have a landing rate plugin back then, so we’ll never know—maybe it’s for the best?). The experience of virtual flight had another important impact on me: it made me want to learn more about the topic. I was consuming huge numbers of articles, posts on web forums, YouTube videos, to learn everything: how to handle the aircraft, what are correct ways of navigating, how to fly safely and effectively. I read the whole manual for X-Plane twice.</p>

<p>I think that within a month or two I dived into another big subject, that is the social aspect of flying virtually. I learned about VATSIM and online flight certification, I also discovered virtual airlines and how great it was to be a member of a community. Before I realised, I have been flying regularly, thoroughly enjoying the experience. I started flying with a virtual airline, first it was <a href="http://www.alliance-airways.net">Alliance Airways</a>, an airline specifically focused on X-Plane. I enjoyed my time there, but at some point I decided to broaden my horizons, and I became a member of <a href="https://flyvirtual.net">Fly Virtual</a>. I’ve been flying with them ever since.</p>

<p>From the very beginning of my experience my simulator of choice was X-Plane. The key factor that determined me buying it in the first place was good physics of flight, better than in FSX, according to some fellow flight simmers. I did my first flight on X-Plane 10, but not long after version 11 was released, and my license key was good for both versions, so I made the switch. In January this year I bought X-Plane 12, although I still use version 11 on a regular basis, simply because all my add-ons and paid aircraft are there, and I haven’t got enough motivation to go through the trouble of checking which of my add-ons are compatible just yet.</p>

<p>Naturally, my adventure with flight simulation is not over. I still have a lot to learn, and there are many, many things on my to-do list, both in terms of routes and aircraft to check out, as well as improving my skills and learning something new. As long as flight simulation continues to bring me joy, I will be spending some time in the virtual skies.</p>

<p>If you want to check out my flights statistics and maps you can <a href="../flightsim">go to the summary page for my flight simulation hobby</a>.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Thrustmaster T.Flight HOTAS X, to be precise <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="flightsim" /><category term="aviation" /><category term="xplane" /><category term="simulator" /><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Do you know those stories when someone had been loving airplanes from their early years, and they spent every free moment to learn about aviation, flight procedures, various aircraft and so on? It was nothing like this for me.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to keep a resolution to write daily</title><link href="https://leziak.com/writing-resolutions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to keep a resolution to write daily" /><published>2023-01-02T10:33:25+01:00</published><updated>2023-01-02T10:33:25+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/writing-resolutions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/writing-resolutions/"><![CDATA[<p>The beginning of a new year is perfect moment to start a new resolution. While keeping a resolution throughout the year may be a challenge, there are some ways in which one may increase their chance of success. I would like to share with you some advices on how to keep a resolution to write on each day of the year. <!--more--></p>

<h2 id="decide-what-you-will-be-writing-about">Decide what you will be writing about</h2>
<p>The most important part of planning your resolution is deciding on what you are going to write about. Are you a fiction writer that wants to create a new novel? Do you like journaling and want to write down your thoughts on every day? Are you interested in writing articles on a topic you find enjoyable? To properly outline your goal you should be aware of what you <em>want</em> to write about. To make a writing resolution work you should try to write about things that are genuinely interesting to you, or bring you joy, or that you want to share your thoughts on. Forcing yourself to work on a text that you find boring won’t lead you anywhere.</p>

<p>It does not mean that you need to pick only one topic, or only one scheme of writing for your daily resolution. I believe you will have higher chances of success when alternating between different forms, i.e. a journal, blog posts, some fiction. Giving some thoughts to what type of output you want to create will help you a lot down the road, because it will allow you to plan and organise your actions accordingly. If you want to write a blog, you can make a decision to write a post per day, or maybe to write a new post every other day, so you can work on a single entry for two days, etc. In a resolution to write daily it is not important to <em>finish</em> a new piece of writing every day, but to <em>write</em> something every day.</p>

<h2 id="set-a-measurable-daily-goal-for-writing">Set a measurable daily goal for writing</h2>
<p>Once you know what you will be writing about, or what kind of texts you want to produce, you should focus on determining the specifics of your daily goal for writing. It may be counterintuitive for you, as in the last paragraph I explicitly mentioned that the resolution is simply about writing something each day. But it would be a great help in keeping your resolution to define a measurable goal for daily writing. Some clear requirement that will be easy to recognise when fulfilled each day. A few examples are:</p>
<ul>
  <li>writing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> number of words each day</li>
  <li>writing for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> number of minutes each day</li>
  <li>writing once a day, after breakfast</li>
  <li>naming one good thing that happened today</li>
  <li>writing at least one paragraph of your newest story</li>
</ul>

<p>Having a measurable goal will help you by giving an additional confidence boost when fulfilling it each day. The whole concept is based on achieving bigger goals in smaller increments. Virtually no one would be able to write a complete book in one sitting, but doing that step by step is absolutely possible.</p>

<p>It is up to you whether you would like to define a daily writing goal or just stay at “simply writing something every day”. What works for one person may not necessary work for another. However, if you decide to introduce a daily goal, my advice to you is to keep it:</p>
<ol>
  <li>simple</li>
  <li>achievable</li>
</ol>

<p>Simple means that the goal should be easy to remember and to validate. It is easier to manage a goal like <em>write 300 words each day</em> than <em>write three new chapters of the story each week, with at least 300 words on workdays and 550 words on weekends, half of which should be a dialogue</em>. The simpler the goal the better it will work. As for achievable, <strong>daily goal only makes sense when you can actually make it in everyday situations.</strong> Therefore it should be tailored to your needs, taking into account resources that you have available (free time being the most critical resource for majority of people). If you set yourself a goal that is too ambitious, after repeated failures it will only discourage you from keeping your writing resolution. If on average you write 400-500 words in one sitting, do not set yourself a goal to write 1500 words each day. You won’t make it on all days, which will frustrate and discourage you. Instead make a goal of writing at least 300 words each day, which would be <em>below</em> your average words output in this example.</p>

<h2 id="track-your-progress">Track your progress</h2>
<p>The best chance of keeping your resolution and writing something every day of the year is to keep track of the progress you have made so far, and to use the power of streaks to motivate you even further. You can mark days in calendar when you were able to write anything or those when you met your daily writing goal. If you prefer digital solutions, there are dozens of applications that will help you with that. But remember not to push yourself too much. There may be days when you will be sick, or tired, or travelling, when it just won’t be possible for you to write. It is okay to have a day or two out of the streak if your body or mind needs it. We are not machines after all.</p>

<p><strong>It is not a break in a streak that endangers our efforts. It is not returning to the routine afterwards.</strong> This is why you should always get back to your resolution as soon as possible, once the reason for your break had passed. It doesn’t matter if you lost two or five, or ten days, as long as you get back on track afterwards, everything is fine.</p>

<h2 id="find-the-motivation-inside-you">Find the motivation inside you</h2>
<p>New Year’s resolutions can be difficult to maintain in the long run. Not because they are impossible to keep, but because as the year progresses, there is less of the festive atmosphere and energy left in us, and more and more of mundane reality and responsibilities. It is getting harder to do things with the same level of excitement we had at the beginning of January. We need to keep and protect our motivation, for in many cases motivation is the main drive for changes and improvement, as well as for keeping our resolutions. There are different kinds of motivation, but the one important to us is the internal motivation. It is the strongest one, although fairly difficult to control. It can start fading if we don’t take care of it. What can help is remembering the reasons why you decided to make that resolution in the first place. What did you want to change? What did you want to accomplish? Perhaps you wanted to grow as a person. Or publish your first book. Or improve your writing style. Or impress your friend. There could have been many reasons why you decided to start a new year with a resolution to write more, but remembering those reasons will help you significantly. You can write down all the reasons why you made the resolution and look at that list every time you feel like your motivation is dwindling.</p>

<h2 id="perseverance-is-everything">Perseverance is everything</h2>
<p>There will be time when you are tired or angry, or annoyed, and the last thing you want to do is to write something because of a resolution you made a few months ago. In times when motivation fails and everything seems to align against you, perseverance is everything. Keep going even if you do not want to. Just do one small step at a time. And then another. And one more. Motivation can only get you so far. Perseverance and discipline can help you in key moments.</p>

<p>It is not possible to mention every single tip on keeping a resolution in writing, after all everyone is different and prefers different approaches to routines. I still hope that you found my advices useful, though.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="resolution" /><category term="newyear" /><category term="tips&amp;tricks" /><category term="howto" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The beginning of a new year is perfect moment to start a new resolution. While keeping a resolution throughout the year may be a challenge, there are some ways in which one may increase their chance of success. I would like to share with you some advices on how to keep a resolution to write on each day of the year.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Time before Christmas</title><link href="https://leziak.com/time-before-christmas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time before Christmas" /><published>2022-12-12T14:12:44+01:00</published><updated>2022-12-12T14:12:44+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/time-before-christmas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/time-before-christmas/"><![CDATA[<p>This time of year is always special. There is a tiny bit of magic in the air, a spark of hope and dreams that tries to carry us into the new year. <!--more-->It stands in a stark contrast to the mundane everyday routine that consumes us through the majority of the year. But December is different, and time before Christmas can be special in its own way.</p>

<p>When I was a kid I loved Christmas, and Winter holidays in general. Christmas Eve, celebrations, gifts under the Christmas tree, those were some highlights of the season that made it such an unforgettable experience for a child. I was truly fortunate, for my parents did everything they could to make Christmas a unique time for their children. We were enjoying our company, visiting relatives, going to church, listening to carols.</p>

<p>As Christmas was the culmination of the holidays, it wasn’t until many years later that I realised that my most fond memories are not of Christmas Eve or Christmas Day itself, but of the time before Christmas and all those little moments that led to it. I remember that a week or two before Christmas my father went to the attic and came down with a box of Christmas lights. We had probably around half a dozen sets accumulated through many years. Those were the ordinary lights with mini lightbulbs, not the modern LED sets, so my father and I had to check every set for burnt out lightbulbs, snapped cables (they were thin and broke easily), broken plugs. He had a special box in which he kept spare lightbulbs in various shape and size (in four colours that every set came in — red, yellow, green and blue), electrical tape, scissors, etc. It usually took us a couple of Winter evening to make all necessary repairs, with the light sets unraveled on the floor and us threading carefully between them, trying not to crush any lightbulbs, or tangle ourselves in the cables.</p>

<p>Some lights sets were quite old, I remember one that had those tiny gas bulbs shaped like a candle’s flame, giving a beautiful orange glow, with a minuscule gas arc flickering inside. The sockets were shaped like wax candles, with lightbulbs being mounted in the place of a flame. One or two candles’ plastic covers partially melted due to electric surge years ago, so my father had to repair them himself since spare parts were not available back then. I think that it might still be there, forgotten in a dusty box somewhere. It does not matter, though.</p>

<p>What matters, is a memory. It has been over twenty years and I still consider those lights-repairing evenings as one of the best, if not the best, Christmas experience. I am sure that you too could choose a particularly vivid memory related to Christmas that brings you nostalgia. Our minds are great at two things: gathering a lot of memories and hiding them from our view. For the most of the year we pay little attention to some distant memories or dreams we had before the adulthood. Contemporary world is uncannily good at overloading us with superficial stimuli, which can prevent us from thinking too much about days gone. But the past is there, and there are times, like Christmas, when it is easier for it to resurface.</p>

<p>The older I am the more I value memories from my childhood, or even from my teenage years. They have huge sentimental value, but they also allow me to see how I have changed throughout the years. Sometimes I can use this retrospection to get myself “back on track”, if I see that I gave up a hobby that I used to love (like astronomy, for example) or I am not focused on my long-term goals like I should be, etc. However, even simple action of enjoying one’s memories and nostalgic feeling that comes with it can be a pleasure in its own right (perhaps a bittersweet one, but a pleasure nonetheless). And one positive thing that comes with Christmas is that this time of year encourages us to look into our past a little bit more than usual.</p>

<p>May we put those memories to good use.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="personal" /><category term="christmas" /><category term="memories" /><category term="nostalgia" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This time of year is always special. There is a tiny bit of magic in the air, a spark of hope and dreams that tries to carry us into the new year.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fallout 76 - my impressions after three months of playing</title><link href="https://leziak.com/fallout-76-impressions-after-three-months/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fallout 76 - my impressions after three months of playing" /><published>2022-03-16T08:35:26+01:00</published><updated>2022-03-16T08:35:26+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/fallout-76-impressions-after-three-months</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/fallout-76-impressions-after-three-months/"><![CDATA[<p>In December 2021 I started playing Fallout 76. While my previous experience with the franchise culminated in the exploration of the Fallout 4 world, and even <a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLVVGXClToMy1fNPOnAelcP532bhOlLi8y">making a series of let’s play videos</a>, I was positively surprised by Fallout 76 and many new concepts this game offers.
<!--more--></p>

<p>To start with a full disclosure, I have not played all instalments in the Fallout series. I have very briefly checked Fallout 1 out and spent a few hundred hours in Fallout 4.</p>

<p>I’ve been playing Fallout 4 for a few years now, so I expected mostly a similar experience, with a strong focus on the exploration of the world and discovering little secrets of locations and people who were affected by the great war. I was aware that, rather obviously, Fallout 76 emphasises online aspect of the game, that is sharing the world, its resources and available place with other players, be it via fight or a cooperation. I must admit that I was not very keen on the idea of interacting with other players, especially since the immersion of single-player Fallout 4 was so amazing for me, but in the end Fallout 76 turned out to be much better than I expected.</p>

<p>One of the best aspects of multiplayer Fallout 76 in comparison to single-player Fallout 4 is the feeling that we are not alone in the wasteland, and that that world was not created for our use only, but we are merely one of many dwellers fighting for better future in the post-apocalyptic environment. We are not screaming into the void, but our actions and choices can affect other people and vice versa. The world of Fallout 76 does not feel <em>empty</em>. Yes, I know that NPCs in Fallout 4 populate the wasteland but it is a different feeling to see an NPC that it is to see a fellow player, a character that is being controlled by another human being, in the game. I am a sworn RPG lover and I would always choose a single-player game over an online one, but in this case the multiplayer experience is amazingly positive. I had no idea that I would like the online aspect of the game so much.</p>

<p>Speaking of the online aspect, I want to state it clearly that the community of Fallout 76 is the most awesome and friendly community I have ever encountered in an online game. Seriously. Before Fallout 76 I had been playing Escape from Tarkov for a year and a half and the difference could not be clearer. Of course that is largely due to different incentives of those games: in Escape from Tarkov you need to survive and extract from the map, and you are expected to treat everyone standing in your way as an enemy; in Fallout 76 all players share similar goal, and the success of your virtual neighbour does not mean your failure. It is also important that you can turn on the Pacifist mode in Fallout 76, making surprising attacks by rogue PvP players almost a non-issue. Before playing Fallout 76 I had browsed its reddit for some time and I was a bit puzzled by posts of people describing how a high level player saved them during a quest or dropped them some rare plans, or crafted them a weapon, etc. Until I got saved by a player 200 levels above me when a horde of ghouls downed me during a workshop defence event. He didn’t have to help me, there was nothing in it for him, but he not only revived my character, he made sure that I completed the event successfully. He departed shortly after, so I only managed to send him a heart emote as a thank-you. This is but one of many examples of how extremely helpful the community of Fallout 76 is.</p>

<p>What I also like about that game, is a huge variety of weapons, armour and special perks that can accommodate virtually any play style. Do you want to be a secret assassin, hiding in the shadows and waiting for your victims? No problem. Do you want to be a tank with a huge health pool, being able to withstand attacks from multiple enemies at a time? You can. Do you wish to be a trapper or a hunter, roaming the wilds of Appalachia with a worn out hunter rifle, looking for game? Fallout 76 has you covered. In some way it is very similar to <em>The Elder Scrolls V: Skyrim</em>, since you can be almost anyone and do whatever brings you joy in the post-apocalyptic world, yet certain aspects of Fallout 76 mechanics are superior to Skyrim. For example, starting at level 25, you can re-spec your character, switching not only special perks that they use, but also changing number of points invested into various base attributes of your character like strength, perception or intelligence. This makes gameplay more enjoyable in the long run, because you can check out various archetypes and play styles to find what suits you best. In a way you evolve with your character in the wasteland, looking for the best way in which they can survive in this hostile and harsh environment.</p>

<p>Having said that, there are some certain drawbacks of Fallout 76. I deliberately do not want to talk about the lack of content – something often mentioned by senior players – since I have not completed the main quest line yet, nor did I finish a lot of side quests. I don’t feel like I have a right to talk about this issue <em>just now</em>, I may get back to it in a few weeks or months, once I reach the end of the storyline. There is another thing, though, that is a major flaw of Fallout 76: time gating. Certain aspects of the game have daily limits, like:</p>
<ul>
  <li>amount of money you can earn by selling loot to NPC vendors</li>
  <li>number of legendary items that you can exchange for a currency called scrip<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></li>
  <li>number of Treasury Notes you can exchange for gold bullion<sup id="fnref:fn2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></li>
</ul>

<p>There are also some global limits regarding:</p>
<ul>
  <li>maximum amount of money for a player character</li>
  <li>maximum amount of special currencies like gold bullion, scrip, etc.</li>
</ul>

<p>It all comes to severely limiting certain aspects of the gameplay in order to bind players to return to game on a daily basis. If you want to do a lot of crafting, or decide to scrip a few dozens of legendary weapons acquired in a seasonal event (i.e. Fasnacht), or want to sell a pile of stuff to a trader on a railway station you are going to hit one of many limits of Fallout 76 sooner rather than later. Those artificially imposed limits will either hold you back, force you to drastically change your gameplay in order to circumvent them or to painstakingly grind resources or crafting for days or weeks. People who only play Fallout 76 occasionally might not even be aware of all the limitations of its mechanics, but anyone who wants to get some high quality, valuable items or to advance their character in a certain way will eventually bang their head against a metaphorical time-gating wall.</p>

<p>At this moment I can’t say that daily limits have ruined my fun from playing Fallout 76 in a substantial way. Thanks to some guides and tips available online I am able to manage my game time efficiently in order to maximise the use of daily limits. They also have one surprising advantage: prevent you from focusing only on a single aspect of the game. They force you to think about other activities you can do in the wasteland, other endeavours your character can undertake. It makes the gameplay more diverse and prevents boredom.</p>

<p>Now let’s talk about the elephant in the room, that is a paid subscription called Fallout 1st, which is designed to enhance your in-game experience. It is a controversial topic, and there is as many people advocating for it as there is opposing the idea. Fallout 1st gives you certain benefits like:</p>
<ul>
  <li>ability to set up a mobile fast travel point with an access to your stash, place to sleep and cook food</li>
  <li>private worlds where progress is shared with public servers</li>
  <li>custom worlds where progress is not shared with other instances</li>
  <li>special paid items in the in-game store</li>
  <li>monthly allowance of the store currency (atoms)</li>
</ul>

<p>However, the most important feature of Fallout 1st is undoubtedly the scrapbox. The scrapbox is a special type of container that, in contrary to player’s regular stash, has an unlimited capacity but can accept only junk items used for crafting. Without the scrapbox if a player wants to collect some junk to build new objects in their camp or craft/repair their armour, etc., they have to put junk in their regular stash, reducing the amount of space (or <em>weight</em>, to be precise), available for other items like food, medicine, weapons, ammo, etc. And if someone wants to craft a full set of matching armour, or to build a big camp, or to produce a lot of ammo, it means that they need to allocate a substantial part of their stash space to ingredients. <strong>Basically, without Fallout 1st subscription Fallout 76 becomes, to a certain degree, an <em>inventory management game</em> rather than an MMO RPG.</strong> It does not mean that you cannot play Fallout 76 without the paid subscription. I have seen many players who decided to not buy Fallout 1st and who overcome difficulties by knowing precisely what they were looking for and only looting/storing items that they actually needed in the short or medium term.</p>

<p>Fallout 1st is expensive if one buys it on a monthly basis, but if you decide that subscription is your thing, you can pay for the whole year in advance with a substantial (ca. 30% IIRC) discount. <strong>I do not recommend buying a year of Fallout 1st outright.</strong> You should first buy a one-month subscription to see if it is worth your money. For me Fallout 1st does enhance the enjoyment from the game itself, but I only buy Fallout 1st every couple of months. From what I’ve read it is a pretty popular strategy – to buy a month of Fallout 1st and then use that 30 days to gather as many resources as possible and store them in the scrapbox before the subscription runs out. Because once your Fallout 1st membership expires you cannot put new items into the scrapbox, but you still have access to all the items you have already stored. You can also keep all Fallout 1st items you crafted during the period of subscription.</p>

<p>From one point of view I understand why Bethesda hid an impactful enhancement behind a subscription. Since there is no monthly fee to play Fallout 76, Fallout 1st subscription is probably one of the most important sources of revenue. I have seen items sold in the Atomic Shop and I do not believe that many people actually pay for them from their own wallet, they rather use their monthly atoms allowance included in the subscription. We can discuss whether the Fallout 1st price tag is sensible, but we should remember that none of Fallout 1st benefits directly translates to some players being overpowered. Unlimited junk storage and some cosmetic items from Atomic Shop are nice, but they do not determine who is on top of the Appalachian food chain, metaphorically speaking.</p>

<p>Fallout 76 is an amazing game, but not without its quirks. At this point of my journey through Appalachia I can admit that I am pretty satisfied with what it has to offer, although I am fully aware that not everyone will enjoy Fallout 76 for the same reasons (or <em>at all</em>, for that matter). While storyline might not be as well-defined as in Fallout 4, the multiplayer aspect of the game makes it a really unique and interesting thing, and I recommend you to check it out yourself if you haven’t already.</p>

<p>See you in Appalachia, fellow dweller!</p>

<h3 id="yay">Yay!</h3>
<ul>
  <li>huge variety of playstyles</li>
  <li>interesting mechanics</li>
  <li>vivid (yet terribly dangerous) world</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="nay">Nay!</h3>
<ul>
  <li>a lot of timegating</li>
  <li>one of the most essential features hidden behind a paywall…</li>
  <li>… that is way too expensive</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="overall-summary-in-three-words">Overall summary in three words</h3>
<p><strong>controversial, enjoyable, post-apocalyptic</strong></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>you can only earn 300 scrip per day (save for very occasional double-scrip days) from exchanging unwanted legendary items, and each item is usually worth between 3 and 45 scrip <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>gold bullion is another currency, used to buy some highly desirable plans and recipes from special vendors <a href="#fnref:fn2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="fallout" /><category term="fallout76" /><category term="onlinegames" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In December 2021 I started playing Fallout 76. While my previous experience with the franchise culminated in the exploration of the Fallout 4 world, and even making a series of let’s play videos, I was positively surprised by Fallout 76 and many new concepts this game offers.]]></summary></entry></feed>