<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leziak.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://leziak.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-05T10:36:33+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leziak.com</title><subtitle>Articles about technology, photography, art, writing and games</subtitle><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><entry><title type="html">Hogwarts Legacy in the middle of the adventure</title><link href="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-middle-adventure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hogwarts Legacy in the middle of the adventure" /><published>2024-02-05T10:19:22+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-05T10:19:22+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-middle-of-the-adventure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-middle-adventure/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been playing Hogwarts Legacy for some time now and have advanced in the story and the discovery of game’s world. After putting about 20-25 hours in the game I can say that the magical world is more and more fascinating with every hour spent within. <!--more--></p>

<p>I have enjoyed the world created for the game from the very beginning. It was not entirely unknown to me, as I have been a fan of Harry Potter books since my late childhood. I know how Hogwarts was presented in movies, how it is depicted in books, but being able to explore the castle myself is an entirely new experience. It is obvious that developers spent many hours crafting the world that is both homogenous with cinematic source material and captivating for players. Hogwarts Legacy makes me want to lose myself in the world of magic and wonder, providing an immersive experience that is entertaining for both adults and children alike. There were many occasions on which I have been casually exploring my surroundings, looking for floating keys, magical creatures or simply enjoying the magnificent view, instead of progressing the main mission or a side quest.</p>

<p>This is a huge plus of Hogwarts Legacy: it allows one to choose their own adventure and play the game their way. There are days when I am focusing on a certain mission, or learning a new spell. On other days I can wander around, looking for magical plants to replenish my supplies needed for crafting potions. There are some days when I am focused on acquiring certain collectibles or discovering new locations to use the <a href="https://harrypotter.fandom.com/wiki/Floo_powder">floo powder</a> to teleport to. My playstyle varies from day to day but regardless, Hogwarts Legacy is always an enjoyable and entertaining title.</p>

<p>I am playing Hogwarts Legacy on Nintendo Switch and while I am aware that the graphics are inferior to those on PCs or other consoles, I am absolutely satisfied with the visuals delivered. To be honest, Hogwarts Legacy on Nintendo Switch looks <em>better</em> than I expected. Special effects related to magic are attractive and the entire experience is cohesive and well-thought, unlike many Switch ports which make playing on a console frustrating (I am looking at you, Skyrim). There are some occasional glitches or stutters, especially when lighting changes due to weather or time of the day, but they do not impact the experience and do not break the immersion. User interface and controls are quite intuitive, although changing spells casted during fights requires some practise. I should also mention the music and sound effects, which greatly enhance the experience. I am playing in docked mode only but I suppose they would be even more important in hand held mode, when one uses headphones. Speaking of the audio side of the game, I cannot ignore the excellent voice acting for the characters living in the magical world. Everything about Hogwarts Legacy shows developers’ care and attention to details.</p>

<p>Although I am not yet in the middle of the <em>story itself</em> (I would even dare to say I barely scratched the surface of Hogwarts’ world) I can confidently say that this is one of the best games available for Nintendo Switch, and one of the best games I have ever played. I am looking forward to discovering more magical secrets and becoming a true master of wizardy. And I will document my progress along the way.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 9 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="hogwartslegacy" /><category term="harrypotter" /><category term="nintendoswitch" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been playing Hogwarts Legacy for some time now and have advanced in the story and the discovery of game’s world. After putting about 20-25 hours in the game I can say that the magical world is more and more fascinating with every hour spent within.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sometimes older things work better than new ones</title><link href="https://leziak.com/older-things-better-than-new/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sometimes older things work better than new ones" /><published>2024-01-31T07:58:19+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-31T07:58:19+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/older-things</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/older-things-better-than-new/"><![CDATA[<p>It may not be an universal truth, but it happens often enough. Nowadays planned obsolescence prevails, but in the past, when both labour and materials were more expensive, things were built to last a lifetime. <!--more--></p>

<p>Yesterday a colleague at work asked me to borrow a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barometer">barometer</a> to conduct some research. She asked if we had a digital barometer available that can be moved from one place to another. I told her that our digital barometer is stationary, permanently mounted in a fixed location, but we can lend her an older, analogue device, called an aneroid, which is portable.</p>

<p>That particular device in question, an aneroid used to measure barometric pressure of the Earth atmosphere, was produced in 1939, that is 85 years ago, in the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR), a country that no longer exists. Yet, the aneroid works perfectly well despite its age, and is far more accurate than the majority of consumer-grade digital barometers currently in sale. If one were to match its accuracy, a digital barometer in the range of a thousand US dollars or more would be required. Still, the robustness and the high build quality of that analogue aneroid means it will probably be working well fifty years from now, while I have little hope for its digital counterpart to reach a similar lifespan.</p>

<p>Various materials, electronics and labour are cheaper now that at any previous point in history. This is both the blessing and the curse of our times. We can get any device, machine or tool imaginable, but most of those items will be obsolete, broken or otherwise useless in a couple of years, a decade or two at most. Every year smartphone producers convince us that we need the newest, the fastest, the thinnest model, with the best camera possible. And all the older, unwanted, less-than-the-best-but-still-very-capable devices will fill up drawers or, at worst case, landfills.</p>

<p>Somewhere in the ever-present race to get the best, shiniest things we have lost appreciation for things that are older and yet just as capable, if not better than their newer replacements. Of course this is not an universal and always-true paradigm, but in many cases older or even “vintage” (although this term is interpreted in a wildly varying manner) things are forgotten, even if they get the job done no worse than modern variants.</p>

<p>I am not immune to the allure of new and bright things, and I often buy products when I still have an older, working version. But I try to use some older things whenever it is possible or whenever I perceive them as superior to newer models. One example are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_single-lens_reflex_camera">Digital Single-Lens Reflex Cameras</a>, which, in my opinion, were the peak of photographic technology. Modern <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirrorless_camera">mirrorless cameras</a> have digital viewfinder instead of a prism or a set of mirrors, which is the biggest downside for me. No matter how great a digital screen is, it will never compare to an actual optical track leading from the lens to the eyepiece, with virtually infinite resolution, no delay and no power drawn. That is why I still use my old Nikon D90 and have no plans to move into the mirrorless dominium.</p>

<p>Sometimes older things are simply better.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 8 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="technology" /><category term="meteo" /><category term="barometer" /><category term="aneroid" /><category term="hardware" /><category term="dslr" /><category term="mirrorless" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It may not be an universal truth, but it happens often enough. Nowadays planned obsolescence prevails, but in the past, when both labour and materials were more expensive, things were built to last a lifetime.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Freewrite Traveler a month and a half later</title><link href="https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-month-and-half-later/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Freewrite Traveler a month and a half later" /><published>2024-01-30T11:21:39+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-30T11:21:39+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-after-month-half</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-month-and-half-later/"><![CDATA[<p>Last December I bought Freewrite Traveler, a smart typewriter with an e-Ink screen, in a laptop form factor. I have spent six weeks with the device so far. How did it change my writing habits? <!--more--></p>

<p>During those six weeks I was using Freewrite Traveler on a semi-daily basis. It became my go-to device when preparing new articles for this website, mostly because it was easy (and fun) to write using a device with an e-Ink screen. I sticked to the distraction-free rule, meaning that when working on Traveler I avoided using my phone or computer, unless it was absolutely necessary for some research related to the article I was writing. It worked really well for me, making it noticeable easier and faster to finish an article. Something about Traveler and its single purpose makes words flow much easier than when I am sitting in front of a computer, with many other programmes open in the background, besides the word processor itself. Having said that, I have to note that it was still a challenge to find time to write with my current work schedule. So, while Traveler makes it <em>easier</em> to write, it does not magically makes it easier to <em>find time to write</em>. There were a few occasions on which I simply decided not to bother with opening Traveler, however chances of me using a computer to write something were even slimmer on those days.</p>

<p>The simplicity of turning Traveler on and its readiness to accept any words I might type within a few seconds makes it almost a perfect device for writing things down in a moment of inspiration. My experience has not been frictionless, though. On two separate occasions I found Traveler completely unresponsive, despite it working normally the previous evening and having its battery sufficiently charged. Both times Traveler froze and did not accept any keyboard input, nor did it acknowledge plugging the charger in (the battery indicator light simply did not turn on, like if the charging circuit within the Traveler was inactive). Initially I was worried, and couldn’t quite understand why this had happened. But once I referred to the manual prepared by Astrohaus, I noticed a short tutorial on what to do in such situation. By simply keeping power button pressed for 15 seconds one can force Traveler to restart regardless of the status of its software and indeed, it prompted my device to “wake up” and start working normally, including a detection of the charging cable being plugged in. During such restart Freewrite Traveler performs a cold start, so it can take about two minutes before the booting process is complete and one can start writing. In contrast, putting Traveler to sleep by simply closing the lid makes it boot up almost instantaneously after the lid is opened again, allowing for a faster beginning of the work. On the other hand, even in sleep mode Traveler’s battery slowly drains, so if one wants to put Freewrite away for prolonged period of time it is best to turn the device off completely.</p>

<p>Fortunately, once Traveler was working again after the freeze I noticed that none of my texts were missing, and the device was synchronised with Postbox. I would not have lost any progress anyway, because I always send my texts to e-mail as a backup, but it is reassuring to see that even in the event of device’s software freezing no work is lost (or no work has been lost in this particular case; your mileage may vary).</p>

<p>The second freeze happened two days later, in similar circumstances. I finished my work for the day and closed the lid, and once I opened Traveler on the next day it was unresponsive. Again, I was forced to use the trick mentioned in the manual to restart the device, and after booting up it was back in working order. No files were lost.</p>

<p>Both incidents happened sometime at the end of December, and I have not experienced any troubles with Traveler ever since. I do not know what caused those issues in the first place, but the fairy close interval suggests some problems with either the firmware or Astrohaus servers. A couple of days before, Traveler’s firmware caught up to date after a series of updates, so maybe that caused both freezes? Or maybe it was due to some issues with the server to which Freewrite devices connect? I can only speculate, but what is important in such case, is that the fix described in the manual works and no files are lost<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>To be honest, it did make me feel uncomfortable to experience such software freezes so quickly after purchasing Traveler. However, the problem had little consequences and did not impede my workflow that much. Naturally, I would prefer my writing device to work all the time, but considering the experimental nature of Freewrite, I can forgive Astrohaus a mishap or two.</p>

<p>Going back to my experiences with writing on Traveler, I can say that it works well. The e-Ink screen is a delight to look at, and the lack of built-in light is compensated by commonly available external light sources (I use Traveler either at work or in my home office, so I can comfortably use additional light in either of those locations). The delay of an e-Ink screen is no factor for me, because I look at the keyboard when writing. And the keyboard itself, while not mechanical, is <em>the best</em> scissor-switch device I have ever typed on. Key travel is deep for a scissor-switch keyboard, keycaps are comfortable and sturdy, key size and spacing is very close to a normal-sized laptop. I only wish there was a variant with ISO layout available, but as I have mentioned before, Astrohaus decision to get rid of different physical keyboard variants is understandable.</p>

<p>For me Freewrite Traveler is everything it was promised to be. Nothing more, but at the same time, nothing less. It is not a fully functional word processor, but it was never advertised as such. It is not a replacement for Word, or Pages, or <a href="https://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener">Scrivener</a>, but again, it was not expected to be. It is a piece of hardware with fairy narrow functionality, but within its limits it performs really, really well. After almost two months I am still satisfied with my purchase and I can say with all certainty that without Traveler I would not have written nearly half as many words as I did. Distraction-free writing just works.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 7 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>with a big asterisk, since two cases of an issue on a single device are hardly representative for the whole population of Freewrite devices <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="freewrite" /><category term="eink" /><category term="keyboard" /><category term="typewriting" /><category term="hardware" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last December I bought Freewrite Traveler, a smart typewriter with an e-Ink screen, in a laptop form factor. I have spent six weeks with the device so far. How did it change my writing habits?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Animal Crossing: New Horizons - a lovely, peaceful game for everyone</title><link href="https://leziak.com/animal-crossing-new-horizons/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Animal Crossing: New Horizons - a lovely, peaceful game for everyone" /><published>2024-01-29T10:18:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-29T10:18:01+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/animal-crossing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/animal-crossing-new-horizons/"><![CDATA[<p>I have joined the Animal Crossing party quite late, in the second half of 2023, although I had been considering beginning my adventure on a tropical island for quite some time. I can honestly say that Animal Crossing: New Horizons is a unique game and one that I will probably play for many years to come. What made is so special for me? <!--more--></p>

<p>First of all, Animal Crossing is beautifully uncompetitive. In a world dominated by ever-present rankings, competition and rivalry Animal Crossing takes a firm stand in the domain of peaceful, casual gaming. It shows that a game can be successful without a leaderboard and without putting the constant pressure on players. It is a very interesting approach, not very popular among modern titles, which often use rankings as a way of increasing players’ engagement. I believe that Animal Crossing approach is more fulfilling and adequate, though. In a world dominated by the constant desire to be the best at all cost there is something inspiring in an approach focused on cooperation and sharing common values.</p>

<p>One way in which Animal Crossing shines is, in my opinion, its way of instilling kindness and positive emotions in people. All interactions with other inhabitants of our tropical island are based on kind, peaceful gestures, help and support. I cannot find a single thing that would emanate negative energy in Animal Crossing, which is simply beautiful. We need more games showing us that goodness and kindness not only have place in this world, but they can be the foundation of modern world.</p>

<p>Throughout our adventure on an island we help our neighbours build their houses, we reunite them with lost items, can exercise together, have pleasant conversations and share many milestones in island’s development. The gameplay is fairy simple at its core: we do not have any strict objectives and limitations. There are certain tasks that we are expected to perform, but it is entirely up to us whether we will do that straight away or take our time. Repaying the home loan, for example, can be done in a fairly fast manner, or whenever we feel like it. There are no interests and no penalties for not paying the mortgage. heck, we don’t even need to pay the loan at all, unless we want to expand our house.</p>

<p>As for other objectives, we can hunt for bugs, fishes and other sea creatures, we can collect fossils and donate them to the museum, we can try our luck in gardening, planting trees, flowers and bushes of various kind. We can even decorate the entire island if we feel like it, not to mention decorating our own home in any way we see fit. The possibilities are almost endless. I believe that at least some of Animal Crossing success comes from a simple fact that every player can play this game in their own way. You want to focus on the expansion of the village and bringing new animals to live in your paradise? You certainly can. Or maybe you would like to decorate your home according to the newest trends in interior design? Have a go at it. Do you want to be a nature lover and collect all the land and sea creatures that can be donated to the museum? You are most welcome to do so. You decide what you will do and how you will shape the future of your island.</p>

<p>Animal Crossing: New Horizons is one of the least stressful games one can play (if not the least stressful). Unironically, it makes it especially useful for adults, since we tend to have too much stress in our daily lives, and every chance at getting away from the troubles of everyday life in such a friendly environment is precious. Some games can be emotionally taxing, especially if they are associated with online activity with huge doses of competitiveness (Escape from Tarkov is a perfect example). Animal Crossing, on the other hand, makes one calmer, happier and overall more relaxed. There were many days when I returned from work tired and not really in the mood for playing any games, and while I often resigned from turning on my PC, I frequently grabbed my Nintendo Switch and played Animal Crossing even for a couple of minutes. It definitely helped me unwind after a long day.</p>

<p>The structure of Animal Crossing gameplay will not be perfect for everybody, though. The game is pretty open, but every day there is limited amount of resources one can collect. Many processes happen over several days, as the time in game flows at the same rate as in the real world. There are certain vendors or NPCs visiting the island only on certain days and one needs to learn to be patient in order to not get frustrated by the waiting. But that waiting is also what makes Animal Crossing so perfect: things happen in an organic way. One does not feel any artificial time gating, which is pretty popular in <a href="../tags/fallout76">Fallout 76</a>, for example, and one’s patience is always rewarded. I read that some players change system time on their consoles to make things happen faster in Animal Crossing, but in my opinion such action completely misses the point of playing that game in the first place. 95% of other games are fast paced and competitive, and so is the real world. We do not need to transfer that attitude into a game which main purpose is to calm and relax us. Not to mention that observing how things change in game can be a rewarding experience. For example, seasons on our tropical island are linked to actual seasons in the hemisphere we are located in. I started playing Animal Crossing: New Horizons in Summer, and it was so lovely to enjoy the vibrant atmosphere of my island. But observing how its features, weather and colours change as the seasons change around me in real life was definitely satisfying. Of course purists would say that there are no four seasons on tropical islands, and there is virtually no snow there at any point throughout the year, but it is a game, and games do not need to be a perfect reflections of reality. In fact, the games I enjoy the most are, in one way or another, quite different from real world. I use games as a form of escapism, and for that I do not need them to remind the real world.</p>

<p>Right now I am still at a fairy early stage of my adventure in Animal Crossing. I have paid all my home loans, but I haven’t progressed various tasks and quests much. I still have mostly empty rooms in my house and I need to gather some resources to craft furnitures and appliances that would fill the otherwise empty interior. I still need to connect all parts of my island with bridges and ramps, instead of carelessly vaulting through the river to explore the distant areas. I have donated dozens of various creatures to the museum, making many exhibitions possible, yet there are many more bugs, fishes and other creatures that still elude me. It will definitely take months, if not years, to catch them all but I don’t mind. I love Animal Crossing for the adventure, and the road is what matters here, not the end point.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 6 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="nintendoswitch" /><category term="animalcrossing" /><category term="games" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have joined the Animal Crossing party quite late, in the second half of 2023, although I had been considering beginning my adventure on a tropical island for quite some time. I can honestly say that Animal Crossing: New Horizons is a unique game and one that I will probably play for many years to come. What made is so special for me?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why a catch-all e-mail configuration may not be the best idea</title><link href="https://leziak.com/catch-all/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why a catch-all e-mail configuration may not be the best idea" /><published>2024-01-23T14:04:42+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-23T14:04:42+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/catch-all</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/catch-all/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been aware of the importance of a proper e-mail configuration and strict privacy for a long time, which is the main reason why I had left Gmail many years ago and migrated to another provider. One of advices I saw in many places on the Internet was to set up a <em>catch-all</em> e-mail domain, to ensure the convenience and privacy when using many accounts in various places online. <!--more--></p>

<p>In normal circumstances a person has one e-mail address in a single domain, i.e. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email@domain.com</code>. There is no explicit need to set up separate addresses for each and every service one uses their e-mail for. For example, I can use the same address with my social media accounts, utility companies, and so on. The issue that arises is, when many organisations, companies and individuals have one’s e-mail address in their databases, it is only a matter of time before one’s address leaks into the web and is used by third parties to send tons of spam. To avoid that, one can set up separate e-mail addresses, distinctive for each website and service they use. For example, one can set up an e-mail account (or simply just an alias forwarding messages to the main address) called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email2@domain.com</code> and use it only to log into a single website or service. That way, if they start to receive spam to that address they can first, identify that the company for which an account has been set up with that address has leaked that address, either intentionally or unintentionally. And secondly, they can simply delete that e-mail account or remove/disable the alias in order to stop receiving spam coming to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email2@domain.com</code>.</p>

<p>That approach would work easily for a dozen or so services or websites, but the more different accounts one would have on different websites, the more tiresome managing separate e-mail accounts or aliases can become. At one point I had over <em>two hundred</em> accounts on different websites, for various services, social media, discussion boards, etc. It would be simply impractical for me to manage that many separate accounts or aliases, so I turned towards a more systemic approach. Depending on one’s e-mail provider, it can be possible to set up a configuration called a <em>catch-all</em>. It allows the user to create e-mail aliases <em>ad hoc</em>, without any configuration, by simply allowing for messages sent to <em>any</em> e-mail address in their domain to be forwarded to their main e-mail account (or to any account they own). Of course, this option is only possible when one owns the domain in which they have their e-mail address. It is not possible to set up a <em>catch-all</em> configuration for a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@gmail.com</code> address, for example. But if one owns the domain in which their e-mail address ends, it is possible to configure their e-mail so messages sent to any address whatsoever ending in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@domain.com</code> will be forwarded to their inbox.</p>

<p>Such setting allows for a convenient creation of aliases on the go. Since e-mails sent to any address in one’s domain will appear in their main mailbox, there is no need to set up any aliases in e-mail configuration options — one could even type a random set of letters before the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@domain.com</code> and message sent to such random address would still be delivered to them. With <em>catch-all</em> enabled one can type any e-mail addresses on any websites. If one is setting up a Mastodon account on one of many servers, they can use address <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mastodon@domain.com</code>. If they are configuring their account at the electricity provider, they can use an address like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">energy@domain.com</code> or just <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">company@domain.com</code>. That way if they start receiving spam to the e-mail address they shared with that specific company only, they can be certain their address got leaked by the company.</p>

<p>When I finally enabled <em>catch-all</em> for my e-mail domain I decided to wait for few weeks before I would start changing e-mail addresses associated with each of my two hundred accounts to a unique one, clearly identifying the company or its service. Since I had no previous experience with <em>catch-all</em>, I was wary to observe any potential adverse effects of enabling that option. And indeed, once <em>catch-all</em> became active, I started receiving even <em>more</em> spam than before!</p>

<p>Initially, I was bewildered by that change. After all, I enabled that option to increase my privacy and reduce the usage of my primary e-mail address in places where it is not necessary. But quick analysis of new spam messages that started appearing after <em>catch-all</em> was turned on revealed that those were advertisements sent to some most common pre-defined e-mail addresses, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">contact@domain.com</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">info@domain.com</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">office@domain.com</code> and so on. I did not see that spam previously because I simply did not have such addresses created in the first place, therefore the e-mail server kept rejecting those messages, since they could not be delivered to a non-existent e-mail address. But enabling <em>catch-all</em> changed server’s response in a way that any e-mail sent to a non-existent address would be forwarded to my main e-mail account (after all, that is what <em>catch-all</em> is all about). That resulted in an increased volume of spam that reached my inbox.</p>

<p>Perhaps spam filters of my e-mail provider would have eventually caught up with the new spam making its way into my inbox, but since those messages had not been reaching me before, my personal filter was not trained to block them effectively. After few weeks I have decided that <em>catch-all</em> was more trouble than it was worth and have disabled that option. My inbox instantaneously became cleaner, and few spam messages that still managed to reach my inbox were put in spam folder automatically by the filter.</p>

<p>Perhaps there is a way to set up <em>catch-all</em> in a way that takes into account a list of certain addresses it rejects messages sent to automatically, although it would became <em>catch-some</em> in that circumstances. I have not explored the topic any further but if you have any experience in that regard feel free to <a href="../about">let me know</a>.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 5 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="technology" /><category term="email" /><category term="internet" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been aware of the importance of a proper e-mail configuration and strict privacy for a long time, which is the main reason why I had left Gmail many years ago and migrated to another provider. One of advices I saw in many places on the Internet was to set up a catch-all e-mail domain, to ensure the convenience and privacy when using many accounts in various places online.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The best story is the one you haven’t written yet</title><link href="https://leziak.com/story-you-havent-written/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The best story is the one you haven’t written yet" /><published>2024-01-15T08:44:31+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T08:44:31+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/story-you-havent-written</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/story-you-havent-written/"><![CDATA[<p>This simple truth speaks about our innate desire to create, to make something out of nothing, or rather to make something out of countless ideas and concepts floating in our minds. It is trivially easy to conjure some stories, characters or tropes in our heads, but the moment we try to transfer them into a physical world, either as words on paper or bytes in digital memory, they always lose some of their allure. It is a normal if frustrating process.<!--more--></p>

<p>It is important to be aware of the fact that any story will <em>always</em> loose part of its magic when it takes a specific form. After all, stories in our minds are shapeless, <em>limitless</em>. They are always interesting. It is our job, as writers, to try and bring out as much of their original potential  as we can, when we forge them into words, sentences, paragraphs and chapters. It is not an easy task, but a task we are responsible for. Sometimes it is a matter of deciding whether we feel ready to tell a certain story, or maybe we need to save it for another time. When stories live in our minds they are boundless, they can be anything anywhere. But once we write them down, they will never transform into something new. That finality can be intimidating — it certainly is for me.</p>

<p>Still, I am ready to share my stories knowing that I will not be able to convey everything I had hoped for. But I will be able to convey enough, and knowing that with each story written, my skills will improve and allow me to write better. <a href="../writing-resolutions/">Practice and perseverance goes a long way.</a></p>

<p><em>This is article no. 4 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="writing" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This simple truth speaks about our innate desire to create, to make something out of nothing, or rather to make something out of countless ideas and concepts floating in our minds. It is trivially easy to conjure some stories, characters or tropes in our heads, but the moment we try to transfer them into a physical world, either as words on paper or bytes in digital memory, they always lose some of their allure. It is a normal if frustrating process.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I like paper calendars</title><link href="https://leziak.com/why-i-like-paper-calendars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I like paper calendars" /><published>2024-01-09T07:14:23+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-09T07:14:23+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/paper-calendars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/why-i-like-paper-calendars/"><![CDATA[<p>Despite my love for technology, there are certain aspects of life in which I prefer more analogue or traditional approach. One of them is managing my schedules, for which I use a traditional paper calendar.<!--more--></p>

<p>For the past four years I have been using National Geographic desk calendars. They came in a form of a hardcover stitch-bound book with golden page edges and a textile bookmark. I appreciated their elegance and beauty, and I loved how each week was accompanied by a photograph with a brief description, often showing some interesting places at the opposite side of the globe. I had been writing down all my appointments, meetings and any time-related tasks in that calendar, creating a comprehensive schedule for both professional and private aspects of my life. I realised some time ago that such an approach really works for me. In 2020 I decided to conduct an experiment in the form of Year of Analogue — that is, making sure I prioritise the use of traditional and analogue techniques over their modern counterparts. As a result, for a year I was using a paper calendar instead of the Calendar app on my phone. What I discovered was, it actually made me more productive to use a traditional form of writing down important time-related informations instead of relying on Apple Calendar. It might be counterintuitive at first, but it turned out that writing down details of meetings, appointments, projects, etc. improved my memory and ability to analyse, coordinate and compare informations. The sole act of writing down a piece of information activates different regions of brain than the touch typing or dictating the note to a voice assistant. It makes details more memorable and easier to process afterwards.</p>

<p>I have benefited from using a paper calendar for the entire year 2020, and once it was close to an end, I decided to permanently move on to paper calendars as a replacement for the Calendar app. Because I enjoyed using National Geographic calendar so much, I bought the same type for the new year and used it in a similar manner. National Geographic desk calendar had an additional bonus of space designed to write down phone numbers, contact informations, important anniversaries and birthdays. Writing those informations down not only made them easy to recall afterwards, it also served as a backup in case my phone is lost or suffers a catastrophic failure that renders me unable to access informations stored therein. At the beginning of each year I was copying those important informations to a new calendar, which also served as a review: informations no longer needed in the next year were left behind, and new addresses, phone numbers and important dates were added whenever I deemed it necessary. In some way those calendars acted as yearly chronicles, reflecting my friends moving out, some people changing their phone numbers, some contacts being lost and new ones acquired.</p>

<p>On multiple occasions I was happy to keep the old calendars at hand, when I needed to check up some details from the past, like the exact date of a certain meeting or an old address of a friend who moved away. The identical layout of all National Geographic Calendars facilitated retrieving informations quickly and efficiently, while allowing me for some retrospections and reflections on the past. I journal on a semi-regular basis, but often I found some important informations in calendars from past years rather than in my journal. I got into a habit of writing down titles of books, novels and fan fictions I was reading at the time, as well as movies seen in the cinema or concerts attended. Reviewing my activities from two or three years ago was refreshing.</p>

<p>Sadly, 2023 was the last year when National Geographic Calendar was available. There is no version for 2024, so after four years I had to switch to a different brand. Now I use a mountain-themed calendar I got as a Christmas gift. While not as beautiful as National Geographic, it is still a useful tool in my everyday life and I am wondering how much I will like it overall once the full year will have passed. I know for sure that I will not return to digital calendars in the form of an app anytime soon. They are fast and convenient, but they are not as good for helping one retain informations, plus they lack <em>soul</em>. That is why I still predominantly use fountain pens, refilled with bottled ink like in the old days, instead of regular pens. In the modern world, full of quick feedback and ever-present stimuli, using analogue tools and techniques helps one to slow down and can be considered a form of practising mindfulness.</p>

<p>I will continue to use paper calendars as long as I can find one. Perhaps one day i will find the perfect replacement for National Geographic calendars, but even if not — any calendar that allows me to write down important informations will be more useful than a piece of software. There is beauty in simplicity and elegance of the old ways of writing.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 3 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="calendar" /><category term="analogue" /><category term="paper" /><category term="mindfulness" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Despite my love for technology, there are certain aspects of life in which I prefer more analogue or traditional approach. One of them is managing my schedules, for which I use a traditional paper calendar.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hogwarts Legacy: a truly magical experience</title><link href="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-truly-magical-experience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hogwarts Legacy: a truly magical experience" /><published>2024-01-08T13:33:50+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-08T13:33:50+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-first-impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-truly-magical-experience/"><![CDATA[<p>After almost two years of waiting, I have finally been able to play Hogwarts Legacy on Nintendo Switch. The game was a Christmas gift and it couldn’t have arrived at better time. It was a lovely experience to explore the magic of Hogwarts and feel like I was wandering through the castle’s corridors. <!--more--></p>

<p>I am still at the beginning of my adventure in Hogwarts, having only visited Hogsmeade for the first time, after my first day at school. I have played the game for maybe five, six hours, but it was a fabulous time. Hogwarts Legacy reinvigorated my curiosity and excitement about the magical world of Harry Potter I first encountered as a child many years ago. Developers created an immersive, vibrant world where magic is accessible and attractive. That world made me want to return to the original books by J. K. Rowling and places, events and characters she described.</p>

<p>Although Hogwarts Legacy does not share any characters with Harry Potter series, happening a hundred years prior to the events mentioned in the books, it absolutely shares the same vibe and amazing atmosphere of a magical world hidden from the eyes of muggles. Even the first steps, taken <em>before</em> I started playing the game (that is, creating a Wizarding World account and connecting it to the game, sorting to the right house and choosing my wand) made me want to dive head-first into this universe. As it quickly turned out, the world of wizards and witches, although magical, can be really dangerous, and not every person or creature is friendly. I have learned that lesson before even arriving at Hogwarts.</p>

<p>Many things are still unknown to me regarding the gameplay. After all, I have only begun my adventure in Harry Potter’s world. Nevertheless, I have already fallen in love with this game, and the way it makes me feel like I’m a young boy again, excited about the magic I’m about to discover.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 2 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="hogwartslegacy" /><category term="harrypotter" /><category term="nintendoswitch" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After almost two years of waiting, I have finally been able to play Hogwarts Legacy on Nintendo Switch. The game was a Christmas gift and it couldn’t have arrived at better time. It was a lovely experience to explore the magic of Hogwarts and feel like I was wandering through the castle’s corridors.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 Days To Offload: a writing challenge</title><link href="https://leziak.com/100-days-offload/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 Days To Offload: a writing challenge" /><published>2024-01-02T13:31:13+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-02T13:31:13+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/100-days-to-offload</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/100-days-offload/"><![CDATA[<p>I have decided to participate in a writing challenge called <a href="https://100daystooffload.com">100 Days To Offload</a>. The challenge is fairy straightforward: to write a hundred articles on a personal blog within a timespan of 365 days. <!--more--> I first read about this challenge on Mastodon and I immediately realised it would be a perfect opportunity to make my personal website more dynamic and to utilise some of ideas for articles I have been putting away for too long.</p>

<p>In the era of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Closed_platform">walled gardens</a> the vast majority of information is shared via closed social media platforms like Facebook, Instagram or <del>Twitter</del> X, where only people having an account are able to access published content. They are virtually always subject to ad targeting and profiling, not to mention giving platform provider some rights to their content, as mentioned in terms of service. It deepens the issue with internet being more and more commercial and dwindling open access to interesting articles, blog entires, photographs produced by private individuals. In the early days of internet people were sharing their knowledge, experience, thoughts and opinions via personal websites, blogs, discussion boards and forums. Readers were usually not required to have an account in order to access entries shared by others. Over the last two decades the landscape of internet has shifted dramatically, which endangers the <a href="../persistence-of-information/">persistence and accessibility of information</a>. This is why initiatives like 100 Days to Offload are needed. They help to enrich the personal, unrestricted and non-commercial part of the internet, the part which is not focused on maximising the engagement to generate profit, but instead relies on authenticity and sharing information with others.</p>

<p>I am curious about how will this challenge go for me. Writing a hundred articles in a year means posting one article every 3.6 days on average. I do not aim at publishing at constant time intervals, though. Depending on what I have to say, I may post daily for some period of time followed by a break. I have an entire year to figure out the optimal solution.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 1 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="resolution" /><category term="newyear" /><category term="challenge" /><category term="website" /><category term="internet" /><category term="information" /><category term="ownyourwords" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have decided to participate in a writing challenge called 100 Days To Offload. The challenge is fairy straightforward: to write a hundred articles on a personal blog within a timespan of 365 days.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fallout 76 after two years</title><link href="https://leziak.com/fallout-76-after-two-years/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fallout 76 after two years" /><published>2023-12-20T09:43:10+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-20T09:43:10+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/fallout-76-after-two-years</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/fallout-76-after-two-years/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been two years since I first ventured into the Appalachian wilderness after leaving Vault 76 in Bethesda’s newest installment in the <em>Fallout</em> series. Those two years were full of adventure, fights, grinding and exploration. Was it worth it? Is Fallout 76 better than Fallout 4? Let’s find out. <!--more--></p>

<p>Those of you who follow this blog reguarly may remember my <a href="../fallout-76-impressions-after-three-months/">first article about Fallout 76</a>, in which I shared my opinions after three months of playing. I was pretty unexperienced in terms of what Fallout 76 had to offer back then, but I already knew that the overall vibe of the game was positive. Has it changed over those two years? Well, both yes and no.</p>

<p>What changed, is my opinion on the end game. Back in March 2022 when I wrote the first article about Fallout 76, I did not experience the actual end game, since I was far from finishing the main quest line. I remember, though, that many players complained in various places (Reddit, Twitter, etc.) about the lack of actual end game and the inability to replay the main quest line once it is concluded. I finished the main quest, culminating in lauching my first nuke, sometime last Summer. I had originally planned to not touch the nukes until I reach level 1000. However, I found myself getting more and more intrigued about the whole process, and since I have accumulated few hundreds nuclear keycards (consummable items required to lauch a nuke), I gave it a shot once I reached level 700.</p>

<p>I had read quite a few guides and articles about launching a nuke in Fallout 76 even before I tried it myself, so I knew what to expect. To be completely honest, I expected it to be <em>more</em> difficult than it actually was. Do not get me wrong, it still is a rather long ordeal, taking approximately 40-ish minutes (if done a proper way; there are numerous glitches that people use to finish the launch in under 10 minutes, but I prefer to play without using glitches). But because I have been using endgame equipment for months now, the challenges of a nuclear silo were not that difficult. The main issue during the first walkthrough the silo was finding the correct locations where to perform some tasks (especially, repairing the mainframe proved to be diffuclt, as I erroneously assumed I needed to repair the mainframe I had previously destroyed to deactivate the defense systems). Luckily, after an hour or so I finally managed to launch my first nuke and trigger the Scorched Earth event.</p>

<p>Ever since, I have launched nukes several times, from different silos in Appalachia (there are three silos: Alpha, Bravo and Charlie, although their internal layout is identical). It turned out to be a refreshing activity, in comparison to all “regular” quests and public events that I know thoroughly. I managed to stay under 40 minutes when fighting my way through the silo. At one point, however, I tried to change tactics and used Chinese Stealth Armour instead, to avoid confrontation whenever possible. It further reduced the time needed to complete the silo by additional 10 minutes or so.</p>

<p>The quests leading to the launch of the first nuke were interesting and diverse. They allowed me to travel through the entire Appalachia and visit locations I haven’t seen in a while. One thing that I skipped, though, was decyphering the launch code. I read a tutorial online and decided that it does not sound like fun. I used codes found at <a href="https://nukacrypt.com">NukaCrypt</a> instead.</p>

<p>Once I finished the main quest line I have entered the actual end game, since there are only few remaining quests, mostly related to previously published expansions, that I need to finish. Despite this fact, I do not feel like there is no end game. The end game itself is whatever one chooses it to be: finishing all side quests, rolling legendary weapons to find a perfect 3-star legendary, roleplaying as a Responder, Fire Breather, member of the Enclave, etc. Fallout 76 is so diverse anyone can find a way of enjoying the game once there are no more quests to do.</p>

<p>Regarding the things that stayed the same for me, those are mainly the standard issues with time gating. Although developers have increased daily limit for scrips (a type of virtual currency obtained for traiding in legenday items one does not want) and every now and then there are events when certain limits are doubled, Fallout 76 remains the game of patience. The upper limit of caps (money) in game remains at 40 000, and one can earn only 1400 each day by selling unwanted goods to an NPC vendor. If that is not enough one can always try to sell items to other players, although it is not guaranteed that anyone will purchase those items. Besides that, one can get small amounts of money by looting bodies or completing quests. But if you want to get rich fast, try some other games.</p>

<p>I must admit that I am no longer bothered by daily limits to the extend I used to during my first months of playing Fallout 76. That is mostly due to already using the best armour, weapons and equipment in the game. I have no incentives to earn more money or roll another legendary weapon, because the weapons that I have are already the best for my build. That’s why in the end game the limits are not as important as during the main playthrough, when one wants to level up fast.</p>

<p>While Fallout 76 is in mature state, it does not mean that the game is left on its own. Every couple of months there is a new season, and with each season there are new cosmetic items, skins and decorations introduced. However, what is more important, developers are regularly adding some small quality of life improvements. It is heartening to see that players’ opinions are heard and taken into account, and that the developers want Fallout 76 to be more user friendly. The newest update, from the beginning of December, brings two new expeditions to the game, together with new enemies and monsters. Unfortunately, it is visible that some of them are only reskinned mobs that were already in the game (they even share some sounds, which should not be the case). Nevertheless, it brings a bit of fresh air into the game.</p>

<p>Overall Fallout 76 is a good game, and while it is not for everyone, I found it pleasant and enjoyable. I like to roam Appalachia mountains and look for adventures in the wilderness and ruins dotting the landscape. After two years I can safely admit that it was a good decision to give this title a shot. I am sure there are many hours of great time awaiting me in Fallout 76.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="fallout" /><category term="fallout76" /><category term="onlinegames" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been two years since I first ventured into the Appalachian wilderness after leaving Vault 76 in Bethesda’s newest installment in the Fallout series. Those two years were full of adventure, fights, grinding and exploration. Was it worth it? Is Fallout 76 better than Fallout 4? Let’s find out.]]></summary></entry></feed>