<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leziak.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://leziak.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-15T14:33:31+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leziak.com</title><subtitle>Articles about technology, photography, art, writing and games</subtitle><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><entry><title type="html">Changes to the website</title><link href="https://leziak.com/changes-website-2022/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Changes to the website" /><published>2022-02-15T10:21:29+01:00</published><updated>2022-02-15T10:21:29+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/changes-to-the-website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/changes-website-2022/"><![CDATA[<p>A new update and some changes are coming to this website.
<!--more--></p>

<p>This is a long-overdue update. As you might have noticed, I hadn’t posted a new article on the website in quite a long time. There were many reasons for my prolonged absence here but the most important one was the pandemic. The events of 2020 &amp; 2021, multiple lockdowns and national quarantines have affected both my work and private life, forcing me to prioritise certain things over others.</p>

<p>Luckily, while the last two years were pretty rough, 2022 started with new possibilities and an opportunity to get back to one of activities I like the most, writing. I have many ideas for articles that I wanted to share with you for a long time, and hopefully, I will be able to do so in the coming months. I have already made some changes to this personal website, refining some elements and changing my hosting service. The layout and aesthetics of my homepage will remain mostly the same. When <a href="../change-to-jekyll/">switching from Wordpress to Jekyll in 2018</a> I chose minimalism over bloated graphics and visual effects, to increase site’s performance and to reduce its size. I still swear by those principles, against a common trend to place as many ads, banners and promotional links on a page as possible. My website will continue to be ad-free and I will not hide any content behind a paywall.</p>

<p>I created some new posts with my artworks and fan fiction, backdated to the original time of creation, so you might want to browse through my website again if you are interested in checking those out. From now on all new content will be posted with its actual date.</p>

<p>If you encounter any errors please <a href="../about/">let me know</a> so I can fix them.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="website" /><category term="technical" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A new update and some changes are coming to this website.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Heart of Etheria - Catra and Adora kiss</title><link href="https://leziak.com/heart-of-etheria-catra-adora-kiss/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Heart of Etheria - Catra and Adora kiss" /><published>2020-06-09T13:57:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-06-09T13:57:00+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/heart-of-etheria</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/heart-of-etheria-catra-adora-kiss/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/heart-of-etheria-catra-adora-kiss.jpg" alt="heart-of-etheria" />
<!--more--></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Don’t you get it? I love you. I always have. So please, just this once… stay.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>She-Ra and the Princesses of Power is absolutely amazing. I love this series!</p>

<p>A high resolution version of this drawing is available on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/vertiser/art/The-Hearth-of-Etheria-Catra-and-Adora-kiss-844948105">deviantART</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="art" /><category term="drawing" /><category term="catra" /><category term="adora" /><category term="she-ra" /><category term="catradora" /><category term="digitalart" /><category term="procreate" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Portal Catra</title><link href="https://leziak.com/portal-catra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portal Catra" /><published>2020-05-31T12:22:14+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-31T12:22:14+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/portal-catra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/portal-catra/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/portal-catra.jpg" alt="portal-catra" />
<!--more--></p>

<p>Ḩ̸̡̲͇̙͛̐̃̌̅͜͜e̸̪̹̬̞̠̻̼̺͛̏̄̂͑̂͗̕͝ͅy̸̡̛͉͍̜̠̼̰̟̖̜͆̈́̀̒͠͠͝,̸̛̺͖̖̈͛̌͆͠ ̶̛͇̾̈̃͠Ă̵͍̼͕̤͍͋͌͒͌d̴̏ͅò̴̧̹̜̱̺̗͎̅̋͘ŗ̶̯̰͒̑̒͐͛͒a̸̧͔̪̼̻̾̑̇̇̆͛͛̽̕</p>

<p>Portal Catra is one of my favourite characters in She-Ra and the Princesses of Power, so I had to draw her eventually. She has also inspired me to write <a href="../remember-me-she-ra-fanfiction/">a She-Ra fan fiction called Remember Me</a>.</p>

<p>A high resolution version of this drawing is available on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/vertiser/art/Portal-Catra-843810561">deviantART</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="art" /><category term="drawing" /><category term="catra" /><category term="she-ra" /><category term="digitalart" /><category term="procreate" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Remember Me - a She-Ra fanfiction</title><link href="https://leziak.com/remember-me-she-ra-fanfiction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Remember Me - a She-Ra fanfiction" /><published>2020-05-31T08:53:34+02:00</published><updated>2020-05-31T08:53:34+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/remember-me-she-ra-fanfiction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/remember-me-she-ra-fanfiction/"><![CDATA[<p>This story is an alternative take on the events in Hordak’s sanctum, leading to the opening of the portal in season 3 of She-Ra and the Princesses of Power. What if Catra and Adora talked about their past? Would Catra still pull the switch? Or would she switch sides?
<!--more--></p>

<h2 id="notes">Notes</h2>
<p>This fanfiction is also available on <a href="https://archiveofourown.org/works/24477115">Archive of our Own</a> and <a href="https://www.fanfiction.net/s/13602136/1/Remember-Me">fanfiction.net</a>. If you enjoy this story, please consider leaving feedback on either of those sites or on <a href="https://twitter.com/KamilLeziak">my Twitter profile</a>. I would love to hear your opinion.</p>

<p>I have also created <a href="../portal-catra/">an artwork</a> that can serve as a cover for this fanfiction. If you are interested, feel free to visit <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/vertiser/gallery/71908749/she-ra">my She-Ra gallery at deviantART</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Remember Me contains spoilers for episode 3x4 Moment of Truth of She-Ra and the Princesses of Power.</strong></p>

<p>I want to sincerely thank my two awesome beta-readers, Megaruru and Blackadder, for their insightful suggestions that helped me improve this story &lt;3</p>

<p>I wrote <em>Remember Me</em> after watching the beginning of season 4, therefore it does not include certain characters and events from seasons 4-5.</p>

<h2 id="dedication">Dedication</h2>

<p><em>For MW. Thank you for introducing me to She-Ra.</em></p>

<h2 id="chapter-1">Chapter 1</h2>
<p>“Open the portal and let’s end this!” Catra cried, seeing Hordak’s hesitation. The princesses were close, she could hear sounds of fighting in the corridor leading to Hordak’s Sanctum. They didn’t have much time. “Open the portal, now!”</p>

<p>Hordak looked at her, then at Adora. He approached the device assembled by Entrapta, frowning at the memory of the princess who betrayed him. A large metal lever occupied the central position in the complex machinery, surrounded by a mess of tangled cables. She-Ra’s sword was levitating above, emanating a soft blue glow, signalling that it was ready to release its power at any minute. Catra’s sensitive ears picked up a soft buzzing, constant electrostatic discharge around the sword, as if it knew what was about to happen and was accumulating energy on its own, preparing for the ultimate discharge. Hordak reached out, but before his fingers could grasp the lever, a powerful explosion shook the room. The shockwave knocked Catra over, throwing Hordak at the opposite wall with a loud thud. Only Adora, who was still firmly tied down to the huge pipe, remained in place, although with her hair and clothes completely dishevelled. Large fragments of the ceiling fell off, enveloping everyone and everything in the room in a thick cloud of dust.</p>

<p>Catra rose slowly, brushing away small pieces of debris that landed on her. As the dust settled, she saw that a large part of the room collapsed, cutting her and Adora off from the entrance. Hordak laid against the wall, unconscious. Damaged control panels were sending showers of sparks. Some of the broken screens were smoking lightly while the ones untouched by the explosion were showing a multitude of error messages and blinking alerts. The Portal machine, however, seemed intact.</p>

<p>“Adora! Hang on! We’ll get to you!” Glimmer’s muffled voice came from the other side of the rubble. Both Catra and Adora looked into that direction. Catra let out a quiet hiss and moved towards the lever to activate the portal.</p>

<p>“Catra, please, don’t.”</p>

<p>Adora’s voice made Catra freeze mid-step, and her tail rose, alerted. Hesitantly, she turned around and looked at Adora. Ever since Adora left the Horde, she has always seen anger and contempt in the eyes of her former friend. As if Adora couldn’t or didn’t want to forgive Catra for not running away with her when she had a chance. This time was different. Adora’s look was full of sadness and… regret?</p>

<p>But then other images appeared before Catra’s eyes. Adora leaving her after Thaymor. Adora choosing her new friends from the Rebellion over Catra. Adora doing everything to defeat Catra. Adora… hating her. Tears started to gather in Catra’s eyes, but she shook them off. She closed her eyes with a grimace, wanting to get rid of these memories, yet she couldn’t. When she opened her eyes she saw that Adora was still looking at her with that mysterious look.</p>

<p>Catra glanced over the lever activating the portal and unconscious Hordak, then returned her gaze to Adora.</p>

<p>“Give me one reason why I shouldn’t do it.”</p>

<p>“Because you would die.”</p>

<p>Catra burst with hysterical laughter, making Adora jerk back in reflex. It echoed around the room, muffling sounds coming from behind the rubble, where Glimmer and her companions were unsuccessfully trying to break into the sanctuary. Catra spread her hands, gesturing at the destroyed structure.</p>

<p>“Look around, Adora. I’m done. There is nothing left for me. Not here, nor in the entire Etheria. I don’t care if I die.”</p>

<p>“I do” Adora whispered softly.</p>

<p>Catra glared at her with fury in her eyes. In three quick steps she found herself in front of Adora and swung her claws, leaving four deep scratches on the pipe, inches above Adora’s head.</p>

<p>“Don’t lie, Adora! You left me!” she cried. “You promised that as long as we have each other nothing bad could happen, and then you left me!” Catra’s voice began to break, and despite the fact she really tried, she couldn’t stop tears flowing down her cheeks.</p>

<p>“Catra … I had to … the Horde …”</p>

<p>“Oh, give me a break!” Catra snorted. “Anybody who has at least two brain cells knows what they are like! Isn’t it obvious?”</p>

<p>“It wasn’t! Not until Thaymor” Adora replied calmly. “I thought we were the good ones, we were changing the world for the better …”</p>

<p>Catra stared at her in bewilderment.</p>

<p>“Were you really that stupid?”</p>

<p>“How would I know the difference? I’ve been in the Horde for as long as I can remember. I knew no other life.”</p>

<p>Catra looked at her with a mixture of skepticism and disbelief.</p>

<p>“It doesn’t matter. Even after Thaymor you could have returned. You had a chance. Chances” she corrected herself. “You could’ve just come back to Horde. To… me.”</p>

<p>Adora sighed heavily. “I couldn’t, Catra. I’m sorry.”</p>

<p>Catra’s eyes narrowed.</p>

<p>“You are sorry? That’s all you have to say?” she spat with anger, her fists clenched. “You have no idea how shitty things were for me. In what position you left me in. You don’t know how Shadow Weaver, Hordak, everyone treated me like a piece of garbage, like a fucking abomination. As if I was the reason you left the Horde and teamed up with your sparkly new friends” she gestured towards the big pile of rubble separating them from Glimmer and the others. “You were my best friend, my only friend in this shit-hole, and you left! You abandoned me! Do you know how many sleepless nights I spent crying my eyes out in your empty bed? Do you know how many times I was beaten bloody by other cadets, because there was no one who would take my side? Do you know how many times I’ve heard how useless I was and how you would be so much better?!”</p>

<p>Both girls now had tears in their eyes.</p>

<p>“I had no idea.” Adora replied quietly, uncertainly. She couldn’t look up, she could not look Catra in the eye.</p>

<p>“Well, you didn’t do much to find out, now did you? You found new friends, better friends. You know who I had? No one. I thought that Entrapta would…” she hesitated for a moment, but then shook her head, tail moving furiously, giving away her anger. “She ended up taking my place at Hordak’s side. She only cared about her research, she never cared about me! No one ever cares about me…” Catra’s voice trailed off.</p>

<p>“I…” Adora began, but Catra silenced her, waving her hand dismissively.</p>

<p>“Please don’t. I can’t take another lie from you.”</p>

<p>“But it’s true!” Adora claimed. “I cared about you! You were my only friend, too! I wasn’t friends with Kyle, or Lonnie, or Rogelio. I was friends with you. We were inseparable. And we still can. If Shadow Weaver could change her mind, why can’t you?”</p>

<p>“Shadow Weaver betrayed me!” Catra hissed with a furious look. “She pretended that she cared about me, but she only used me to escape from the Fright Zone. She was the reason I ended up in her own cell! Because of her, Hordak had almost sent me to Beast Island!”</p>

<p>Angry Catra paced in front of Adora. She looked at the tied-up girl with a mix of resentment and jealousy.</p>

<p>“Shadow Weaver used me to get to you. You were the only one who ever mattered to her! Even after you became She-Ra, joined the Rebellion, fought against the Horde, she still chose you” she pointed at Adora accusingly. “Nothing like that would have happened if you hadn’t left me and your whole life behind.”</p>

<p>“It wasn’t easy for me, too!” Adora burst out, crying. “My whole world came down in one moment! Everything I believed in! Everything I stood for! The Horde turned the lives of ordinary people into hell. And we helped in that! Thanks to Bow and Glimmer I saw a different world. A world of kindness and friendship, in which everyone helps you, unlike the Fright Zone, where everyone is just waiting for your failure, to take your place. The Horde taught us that absolute obedience and duty are everything. That we have to win at all costs. I didn’t know you could live in a different way until I came to Bright Moon. When I realised what the Horde was doing… I couldn’t get back, Catra! Not even… for you.”</p>

<p>When Adora’s final sentence reached Catra, she froze. A mix of shock and surprise appeared on her face for a split second, almost instantly replaced by an angry grimace. In one smooth movement she jumped towards Adora and, with a scream full of rage and despair, she swung her clawed hand aiming at Adora’s face.</p>

<p>Adora, seeing approaching claws, closed her eyes and clenched her teeth in anticipation of impact and pain, which, however … did not occur. After a few seconds she hesitantly opened her eyes.</p>

<p>Catra’s hand, with razor-sharp claws, stopped an inch from her face. Catra was breathing hard, not taking her eyes off Adora. A painful grimace appeared on her face, as if she was fighting herself. She withdrew her hand and swung once more but again, her hand hung harmlessly in the air in front of Adora’s face.</p>

<p>Resigned, Catra dropped to her knees. She started beating the concrete floor with her bare fists, crying.</p>

<p>“You took everything from me, Adora!” she said, hitting the floor again and again. “You even took away my revenge! I have nothing… nothing…”</p>

<p>Every now and then Catra’s crying was drowned out with a rumble, when elements of the structure couldn’t withstand the load and collapsed, destroying parts of the sanctum. However, two girls in the middle of the room did not seem to pay any attention to the world around them. Nothing else mattered at that moment.</p>

<p>“Catra …” Adora began quietly, giving her former friend a sad look. “I never wanted to fight against you. I’ve fought against injustice, violence, terror. I have never fought against you, as a person.” Tears were rolling down Adora’s face now. She could hardly suppress a sob when the feelings she had buried a long time ago came out, surging forward in full force. “I … I never considered you a bad person. We were brought up by the Horde, how could we know that what we’ve been doing was evil? In the Fright Zone everything was different. White was black and black was white. I didn’t realise it until the Thaymor. I don’t regret leaving the Horde. But I do regret leaving you.”</p>

<p>Catra raised her head and looked at Adora hopelessly. “It doesn’t matter anymore, Adora” she said in a resigned tone. “It’s too little, too late. I’m a goner.”</p>

<p>She got up slowly and looked at the portal machine, then back at Adora. She smiled sadly.</p>

<p>“You know that the Horde always gets what they want.”</p>

<p>“Catra, no!”</p>

<p>Catra ignored Adora’s plea. She walked to the lever and grabbed it hesitantly. Her heart was racing. She was scared, but she had to do it. She was never good enough for Shadow Weaver, she was never good enough for Hordak. She wasn’t even good enough for Adora, who still left her behind. But maybe this will change their minds. One last victory.</p>

<p>Catra turned her head towards the tied girl. “I’m sorry, Adora.”</p>

<p>She pulled the lever.</p>

<p>##Chapter 2
The portal machine instantly came to life. She-Ra’s sword started glowing with a blinding white light, and the portal began to form, revealing a passage in the middle. For a moment, everything seemed fine. The corners of Catra’s lips raised in a smile. She opened her mouth to announce her success to Adora, but then the sound made by the portal changed. It became lower, more ominous. The machine started to vibrate violently, sending sparks in all directions. The glow around the sword became so bright that both girls had to cover their eyes.</p>

<p>“What is happening?” Catra asked in surprise, stepping back.</p>

<p>Adora looked at the expanding white glow.</p>

<p>“The portal is broken,” she explained. “Mara, the previous She-Ra, created a flaw to make sure that Etheria would never be reachable through another portal. It will slowly grow and consume everything and everyone.”</p>

<p>Catra looked at her with wide eyes.</p>

<p>“Are you sure?”</p>

<p>Adora nodded.</p>

<p>Catra stood next to the pipe Adora was tied to, watching the expanding white void. Its borders were slowly expanding, already reaching the edges of the portal machine, although the outline of the sword could still be seen inside. She glanced uncertainly at Adora, who, strangely, seemed to accept their fate.</p>

<p>“Adora, I …” she began, but her voice stuck in her throat.</p>

<p>Adora looked her in the eyes and smiled sadly.</p>

<p>“It’s alright, Catra. I don’t blame you. It all happened because of the Horde. The two of us fighting, Shadow Weaver plotting against you, Entrapta joining the Horde… It’s all because we were all too proud and stubborn to admit that we were wrong, even to ourselves. The Rebellion, the Horde. No one wins this fight. Soon we will all just … cease to be.”</p>

<p>Terrified, Catra glanced at Adora, whose face showed no signs of fear, only acceptance.</p>

<p>“Aren’t you afraid?” she asked, surprised.</p>

<p>“No,” Adora replied, her eyes fixed at the expanding nothingness. “I … I’m glad you’re here with me.”</p>

<p>Catra raised her eyebrows.</p>

<p>“Why? I have just basically doomed you and the entire planet. Why are you not angry with me?”</p>

<p>Adora turned her gaze away from the portal and looked deeply into Catra’s eyes.</p>

<p>“Because I love you.”</p>

<p>Catra’s mind went haywire. Thousands of thoughts flashed through her head. She did not realise she was standing in front of Adora with her mouth open.</p>

<p>“You… love me?” she asked hesitantly after a moment, without taking her eyes off Adora. The white glow of the expanding portal reflected in her heterochromatic eyes.</p>

<p>“Yes, Catra. I love you.”</p>

<p>“But you mean it like … like a friend?” She asked sadly. She knew that Adora could not possibly love her the way she loved Adora. Adora would never love someone like her…</p>

<p>“No” Catra’s thoughts were interrupted by Adora’s denial. “You are more than that to me, Catra. I love you. I always have” she started crying again, tears staining her red jacket. “I was trying to ignore it, push it away when I became She-Ra, when I moved to Bright Moon. I wanted to stop loving you. It would have been so much easier to fight you knowing that we genuinely hated each other. It didn’t work. No matter what was happening, I could never really hate you. I thought I did. But I was just lying to myself.”</p>

<p>“No… no…” Catra felt panic building up inside her, she couldn’t believe it. She didn’t want to believe it. “Please, Adora, please don’t give me false hope. Not now, not in our final moments. Please, I beg you.”</p>

<p>Adora wanted to reach out to Catra, but she forgot she was tied down.</p>

<p>“Listen, Catra, please, look at me. Look into my eyes.”</p>

<p>Catra hesitantly obliged.</p>

<p>“I swear to you, by the honour of Grayskull, that I am telling the truth. You are the love of my life, Catra. I love you.”</p>

<p>Catra moved closer to Adora, their eyes met inches away.</p>

<p>“Are you telling me this as She-Ra?”</p>

<p>Adora shook her head.</p>

<p>Deep in Catra’s heart, something moved. A feeling she buried a long time ago when Adora made her choice, standing among the ruins of Thaymor. On that day Catra promised herself that she would never let it grow in strength again, because she knew that she would not be able to survive Adora abandoning her for the second time. This little, forgotten spark found a way to Catra’s heart.</p>

<p>For the first time in years, Catra was happy.</p>

<p>“I love you too, Adora” she whispered, embracing Adora in a soft hug. Adora, with her hands tied to a pipe, could not reciprocate the gesture, but she buried her face in the crook of Catra’s neck, feeling the warmth of her body, her smell, the soft touch of fur on her head.</p>

<p>Catra broke their hug eventually. Portal light permeated the room, enveloping their silhouettes in a soft glow. Adora turned her head to the portal. The white sphere was merely a couple feet away, although she could still see a faint contour of She-Ra’s sword in the center of the void.</p>

<p>“Catra, could you please untie me? I… I don’t want to go this way. Tied up to a pipe. I want to hold you in my arms when… when it reaches us.”</p>

<p>Catra gave Adora a strange look. Adora could not quite understand what it was expressing. Nostalgia? Desire? Sorrow? She heard a loud thud where the entrance to the sanctum was. Pieces of debris were being thrown aside with magic, and the gap appeared in the middle of the rubble, through which Adora could see some silhouettes. Catra glanced over them, then returned her attention to Adora.</p>

<p>“Glimmer and the rest will be here soon. They’ll untie you.”</p>

<p>“What? Why? I don’t…” Adora started, but Catra leaned slowly and kissed her tenderly, interrupting her. The kiss was short, it lasted maybe a couple of seconds, but for Adora it could have easily been hours. She felt the surge of pleasure and desire, but she was soon left longing, with only a glimpse of a bliss she will never experience again. Catra took a step back, her silhouette a contrast to the blinding light of the void behind her back. She looked at Adora intently.</p>

<p>“I’m sorry for everything. I wish I hadn’t hurt you and the others. I did many bad things, but maybe there is still something I can do right.”</p>

<p>Adora stared at her, confused.</p>

<p>“Catra, I don’t understand, I…”</p>

<p>“I love you, Adora” Catra smiled sadly. “Please… remember me.”</p>

<p>Before Adora could understand her words, Catra turned around and entered the white glow. As soon as she crossed its border, she bent in half, screaming in pain.</p>

<p>“Catra, no!” Adora cried, pulling her bonds in vain.</p>

<p>Catra’s silhouette stood out against the blinding glow around her, like a black spot in a sea of white. Still bent down, taking each step with great effort, she approached the sword levitating in the heart of the portal. Adora saw shining lines forming on Catra’s dark silhouette, like cracks on a marble statue. With every second there were more and more of them, they were growing wider, covering almost her entire body. Catra fell down and her cry became visceral, almost inhuman. Adora couldn’t stand it, she wanted to cover her ears, but was not able to, with her hands tied to a pipe. Her heart broke seeing Catra’s suffering.</p>

<p>“Catra, please, don’t! Get back, I beg you! Get back!”</p>

<p>Adora didn’t know if her voice could penetrate the white void at all, but a moment later she saw Catra rise and slowly walk on all fours towards the sword. She was nearly there, just a couple of feet from the center of the portal. Her entire body shone with a web of glowing cracks, as if Catra was broken into million pieces, held together only by her sheer will.</p>

<p>Six feet to the sword. Her legs gave out. She started to crawl on her hands.</p>

<p>Two feet to the sword. Adora noticed that Catra’s silhouette was becoming translucent. She could no longer hear Catra’s scream. In fact, she could no longer hear anything from inside the white void. She could only watch the silent scene unfolding in front of her.</p>

<p>In her last desperate attempt, Catra gathered all her strength and stood up unsteadily. She raised both hands, cracked with glowing lines, and clutched the sword’s hilt, pulling it back from the center of the portal. A dazzling explosion of yellow light followed, so bright that Adora was forced to close her eyes, yet she could still see the glow through her closed eyelids. The light flooded the entire room, casting away all the shadows, then suddenly disappeared, revealing She-Ra’s sword and the completely destroyed portal machine.</p>

<p>And a lifeless body lying on the floor.</p>

<p>“Adora! Are you okay?” Glimmer’s voice right next to her pulled Adora out of the shock. Bow appeared at her other side, cutting her ties with a knife-shaped arrowhead. They caught Adora in one big hug.</p>

<p>“I’m so happy to see you! We were so scared they’d hurt you!” Bow said, not loosening his embrace for a second.</p>

<p>“If it wasn’t for Shadow Weaver’s help, we would have never made it on time… Hey, why are you crying?”</p>

<p>Adora pushed them both aside and ran to the place where Catra lay. She gasped involuntarily, seeing the aftermath of Catra’s interaction with the portal. Most of Catra’s torso, right arm and half of her face were black as night. Glowing white line ran through her chest, like a rift, splitting her in two. Her eyes were closed and limbs, unmoving.</p>

<p>She heard a scream of terror above her head and looked up to see Glimmer, pale, with widely open eyes fixed at Catra.</p>

<p>“What happened to her? Did you… did She-Ra do this?”</p>

<p>“The portal did this” Adora answered quietly, returning her gaze to Catra’s body.</p>

<p>“Well… Good riddance. She got what she deserved after kidnapping you and stealing your sword.”</p>

<p>Adora didn’t register her body moving, but in the next moment she stood face to face with Glimmer, fists clenched on the fabric of her friend’s dress.</p>

<p>“SHE SAVED US! IF NOT FOR HER WE ALL WOULD BE DEAD BY NOW, ALONG WITH THE WHOLE ETHERIA!”</p>

<p>Glimmer’s mouth opened. “I didn’t know. I’m sorry, I didn’t think she would…”</p>

<p>“She sacrificed herself to save us all!” Adora interrupted, although in a calmer manner. “She did it for…”</p>

<p>“Hey, Adora.”</p>

<p>A faint, hoarse whisper was barely audible, but it made Adora stop instantly. She turned back to Catra. A single yellow eye, devoid of its usual glow, looked at her from behind a half-open eyelid. The other was all dark, except for the unmoving pupil, shining with a bright light, same as the crack on her chest.</p>

<p>“Catra!” Adora kneeled at her side, caressing Catra’s cheek.</p>

<p>“Did… it… work?” she mouthed, barely moving her lips. Adora realised that Catra’s breathing was irregular and raspy, it terrified her.</p>

<p>“Yes, it did! You saved us, Catra! You saved Etheria!”</p>

<p>Half of Catra’s mouth smiled faintly in response. Adora noticed that fingers in Catra’s unaffected hand were moving slightly, although the arm lay still. She gently enveloped Catra’s hand in both of her own.</p>

<p>“You are a true hero, Catra. You saved everyone!”</p>

<p>Catra didn’t seem to notice her words. Her remaining eye no longer followed Adora’s face.</p>

<p>Adora’s heart skipped a beat. She looked at Catra in terror.</p>

<p>“Catra, please, hold on… Wake up! Can you hear me? Catra! Catra!”</p>

<p>“What is happening?” Bow asked, but Adora ignored him.</p>

<p>“Glimmer! Can you teleport her to Bright Moon? She needs healing!”</p>

<p>“I’m sorry, Adora! I can’t use my powers anymore! Shadow Weaver drained too much. I need to recharge.”</p>

<p>Adora’s face fell. She looked at unmoving Catra, noticed that her eyes were now closed. She felt something warm on her cheeks. Tears.</p>

<p>“Catra, please don’t leave me now…” she sobbed, hugging the limp body of her loved one. “Please, don’t abandon me. I will never leave you again, I promise! Just open your eyes, please!”</p>

<p>Catra stayed still.</p>

<p>##Chapter 3</p>

<p><em>Three months later…</em></p>

<p>Bright Moon was full of people. Everyone gathered to pay homage to the new queen. After the battle of the Fright Zone, during which the Horde’s machines were destroyed, and She-Ra recovered her sword, the Horde was forced to sign a truce. Seeing Glimmer’s role in restoring the peace, Queen Angella decided it was time for her daughter to take over the duties of the ruler of Bright moon. The first official ceremony announced by the new queen was to be held with panache, all the princesses and guests from distant lands were invited. There was some consternation among the gathered, caused by the presence of a delegation from the Horde, with Princess Scorpia as its leader, but Queen Glimmer didn’t want to hear about it.</p>

<p>“We are all here today thanks to Catra. Both the Horde and the Rebellion. I will not let the celebration that pays tribute to her sacrifice be held without her friends. Even if they belong to the Horde.”</p>

<p>Therefore, the first decision of the new queen has been carried out. The crowd gathered in the square in front of the royal gardens. The podium for the queen was erected in the central place. Behind it, a huge sheet of red silk hid a mysterious shape. The delegation from the Horde was invited to take seats in the first row. It was not difficult to recognise the strangers, among whom Princess Scorpia not only towered in height, but also attracted attention with her giant tail and pincers. Observant people would notice that the princess was sad, and her gaze every now and then wandered towards an empty chair placed at her side.</p>

<p>“Are you sure you want this chair to be here?” Scorpia heard someone’s voice and turned around, seeing Adora, or rather She-Ra, in her elegant costume, with a sword in hand. “Doesn’t it remind you of what you lost?”</p>

<p>Scorpia smiled with nostalgia, but then shook her head. “No, Adora. It’s fine. This is the best place. I’m sure that Catra would have wanted to witness it… Our wildcat is getting her own statue… Who would know… “</p>

<p>Adora put a hand on her shoulder, then took a seat on the other side of the empty chair. A moment later Bow joined her. Scorpia also spotted Queen Angella (or should she say Former Queen? She’s never really been good at titles and royal etiquette…), sitting on the other side of the wide passage, with the princesses. To her surprise, in the second row Scorpia saw a winged unicorn who had been constantly trying to steal the attention of the audience. It was, however, Bright Moon, and Scorpia knew that one should not be too surprised by anything.</p>

<p>The crowd was loud and excited. Everyone was discussing what the new queen’s reign would be like, what would happen now, after the peace with the Horde had been made, and what the statue of Catra, the mysterious heroine of the Fright Zone, who had reportedly put an end to the war, looks like.</p>

<p>When the clock on the castle tower struck twelve, a pink glow appeared in the central part of the podium. A few seconds later Queen Glimmer materialised in that spot, standing in an elegant silver robe that glistened in the rays of the sun. The noise of the crowd died down immediately, everyone turned their eyes to the young queen.</p>

<p>Glimmer looked around the square, as if searching for someone, then smiled slightly when she saw She-Ra and Bow, who waved at her. After a moment, she took a deep breath and put on a dignified expression.</p>

<p>“Dear residents of Bright Moon, honourable guests, princesses, friends” she began, looking at the crowd. “I want to greet you all today, on this special occasion that marks the beginning of my rule at Bright Moon. I am proud to be able to celebrate with you the dawn of a new era, peace and harmony, and I promise that I will do my best to be a worthy successor to my mother, Queen Angella.” Glimmer nodded to her mother, who returned the gesture and smiled broadly.</p>

<p>“I promise that I will look after all my subjects and will stand up for justice so that no one will be hurt or harmed.”</p>

<p>The crowd cheered enthusiastically, so Glimmer paused, waiting for the noise to stop. After a while she continued.</p>

<p>“But I wouldn’t be here, we wouldn’t be here if it wasn’t for heroic actions of a member of the Horde.”</p>

<p>All eyes turned to the Horde’s delegation. Scorpia blushed, seeing that everyone was looking at them. Fortunately, Glimmer continued her speech, so the crowd’s attention slowly drifted back to the queen.</p>

<p>“Catra, for she is the person I’m talking about, grew up in the Horde with Adora, who most of you know as She-Ra. When Adora left the Horde and joined the Rebellion, they fought each other for some time. Catra had her reasons to fight for the Horde, just as Adora had her reasons to fight for us. However, it was Catra’s noble action, her sacrifice when, regardless of the danger, she entered the unstable portal in the heart of the Fright Zone, that not only stopped the destruction of Etheria, but made it possible to stop the war tormenting our lands for decades. In her last words before stepping into the portal she asked for forgiveness. And forgiveness she did receive.”</p>

<p>The memory of those moments made Adora’s heart sink. In her mind, she could still see Catra’s broken body, lying still on the floor of Hordak’s sanctum. Next to her Scorpia wiped her nose, crying openly.</p>

<p>The atmosphere on the square has changed. During these three months that passed since the portal was destroyed, virtually everyone learned what they owed to Catra, to her final choice. Everyone knew what she had sacrificed to save Adora and all of Etheria. Her deeds as a Horde soldier have not been forgotten. But they have been forgiven tenfold.</p>

<p>Glimmer’s voice was loud and clear when she proclaimed her first official decision as the Queen of Bright Moon.</p>

<p>“By my royal decree, henceforth, Catra of the Horde shall always be known as the Heroine of Etheria. Her sacrifice will not be forgotten. It will remind us that everyone, even in the darkest hour, can rise to the challenge and become a hero that saves the world.”</p>

<p>Glimmer raised her hand. On this signal the velvet curtain dropped, revealing a marble statue. It depicted Catra, standing tall and brave, with She-Ra’s sword raised in her hand. The fanfare echoed in the square, quickly followed by the crowd’s cheer and applause. In that chaos hardly anyone noticed that Adora shed a single tear, which she wiped with the back of her hand. Scorpia’s stare changed between the empty chair next to her and Catra’s statue. She smiled at her memories.</p>

<p>The applause lasted a long time. When it stopped, Glimmer glanced at the statue, then fixed her gaze back at the crowd in front of her.</p>

<p>“I hope that this monument will remind us every day how precious are sacrifices made by our loved ones and that we should always show them our love and support. But I believe that even better than a piece of rock will be a testimony of someone who witnessed these events themselves. Please, welcome our guest warmly.”</p>

<p>Glimmer turned around and gestured at the row of guardswomen behind her. The soldiers parted, making passage for a lonely person hidden behind, who slowly, hesitantly limped over to the queen. The crowd froze for a moment when they saw a figure leaning on a cane, with a patch on one eye. The second, yellow one, looked at them inquisitively.</p>

<p>Catra smiled shyly.</p>

<p>The crowd exploded with joy, cheering and applauding. One by one, the guests spontaneously rose from their seats, until finally the entire square was giving Catra a standing ovation.</p>

<p>Scorpia smiled broadly. “I told you we would need that chair!” She said, elbowing Adora playfully. “I knew that Catra wouldn’t miss out on her celebration!”</p>

<p>Adora didn’t respond. Instead, she launched herself towards the podium and hugged Catra, making her groan.</p>

<p>“You really didn’t have to do this” Catra muttered, steadying herself on the healthy leg. “You know I hate parties.”</p>

<p>“Nonsense” Adora replied. “This whole celebration is for you! You deserve it!”</p>

<p>Catra glanced at her statue. “Well, I do look pretty cool with your sword. I wish I had a cape, though.”</p>

<p>Adora laughed joyfully. She took off her cape and put it over Catra’s shoulders in a chivalrous gesture.</p>

<p>“Now you do. And everybody knows you are mine” she said, smiling wildly, her eyes full of love.</p>

<p>The girls stared into each other’s eyes for a moment, then slowly joined their lips in a kiss, making the crowd go wild.</p>

<p>The party and celebrations lasted a whole night. Cheers and congratulations echoed throughout the streets of Bright Moon and beyond, announcing to everyone that the two heroines have finally found their happiness.</p>

<p><strong>THE END</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="catra" /><category term="adora" /><category term="she-ra" /><category term="catradora" /><category term="writing" /><category term="fanfiction" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This story is an alternative take on the events in Hordak’s sanctum, leading to the opening of the portal in season 3 of She-Ra and the Princesses of Power. What if Catra and Adora talked about their past? Would Catra still pull the switch? Or would she switch sides?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life is Strange photo wall (Max Caulfield memorial wall)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-photo-wall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is Strange photo wall (Max Caulfield memorial wall)" /><published>2020-01-29T16:57:25+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-29T16:57:25+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-photo-wall</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-photo-wall/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things that enchanted me in <em>Life is Strange</em> was Max Caulfield photo memorial wall at Blackwell Academy. It was one of those small details that made me fall in love with this game, contributing to its unique atmosphere. The Polaroid wall in Max’s dorm room allows player to not only appreciate her photography skills, but also learn more about her personality. In some way it also reflects Max’s decisions, especially the ones made at the beginning of the game.</p>

<p>Ever since my first playthrough of the game, I’ve been thinking about recreating Max’s photo wall at home. The opportunity for that appeared in August 2019, when I was doing a renovation of my home office. I decided to dedicate a whole wall to <em>Life is Strange</em>. I want to share the final result with you, along with a small DIY tutorial on how to make Max photo wall that will look as similar to the in-game version as possible. <!--more--></p>

<p><a href="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-dark-office.jpg"><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-dark-office-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-dark-office" /></a>
<em>The recreation of Max Caulfield photo memorial wall in my home office at night…</em></p>

<p><a href="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day-office.jpg"><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day-office-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day-office" /></a>
<em>… and during the day.</em></p>

<p>There are many variants of Life is Strange Polaroid wall that one can recreate at home, depending on available space, materials, desired aesthetics, budget, etc. Please keep in mind that below you’ll find only one of many possibilities. I encourage you to be creative and simply have fun with it – there is no bad way of making a photo wall and perhaps you’ll come up with your own ideas on how to make something work in a better way than described below. If you have any questions, do not hesitate to contact me.</p>

<h2 id="my-photo-wall-inspired-by-life-is-strange">My photo wall inspired by Life is Strange</h2>

<p>My Max Caulfield photo wall consists of 76 prints of various moments from both <em>Life is Strange</em> and <em>Before the Storm</em>. Some of them are the exact optional photographs that Max can take in the game, while others are cropped from screen shots or cut scenes.  All pictures match the size of a classic Polaroid film Max has been using throughout the game and are printed on a thick, high quality paper. While Max’s Polaroid wall at Blackwell is organic in its nature (i.e. photographs are not perfectly aligned with each other, nor are they group thematically), I aimed for a more organised look that would be pleasant even for a person not familiar with the original composition. That’s why I decided to make a few “thematic zones” referring to different characters, locations or events.</p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-pricefield-1-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-pricefield-1" /></p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-pricefield-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-pricefield" />
<em>My Life is Strange photo wall is loosely divided into several thematic zones. Here you can see the central part of the composition, devoted to Max and Chloe</em></p>

<p>The most difficult thing was, by far, to obtain proper lights for the photo wall. Recreating the exact composition of Polaroids from the game was not a priority for me, but I wanted to have lighting matching the original one as close as possible. The vast majority of lanterns available online is way too small in diameter (and there are not that many types resembling Max’s lights to begin with). It took me a few hours of googling, plus help of my friends from Twitter, to find a <em>single</em> model of lights similar to the ones that Max used at Blackwell. Still, they are not an exact match (they are made from polyester, not paper like the ones in the game). But on the other hand they use warm LED lights, so they have low energy consumption and don’t warm up too much.</p>

<p>You can see that my Life is Strange photo wall has two additions. The first one is a fine art print of Chloe and the mysterious raven from <em>Before the Storm</em>. It was one of the first artworks I bought after playing <em>Life is Strange</em> for the first time. In fact, I ordered it even before I finished <em>Before the Storm</em>, so at that moment I wasn’t quite sure about the role that raven was supposed to play in the events of the game. The second one, presenting one of my favourite scenes from the original game, is in fact a postcard. I decided to add it to the wall not only for the graphic on the front, but, most importantly, because of the message at the back from my dear friend (who is also a fan of <em>Life is Strange</em>).</p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-day" />
<em>I decided to add some extra things to my Life is Strange photo wall: a fine art print of Chloe and the raven and a postcard depicting one of my favourite moments from the original game. Together they create a centrepiece that viewer’s eyes naturally gravitate to.</em></p>

<p>The whole Max Caulfield photo memorial wall is situated at the wall opposite to my desk, so all I have to do when I’m working is to lean to the side a bit, to see it behind my computer screen, at the far end of the room. During the daytime the lights are unplugged, but in the evening they turn my home office into a location taken out from Arcadia Bay. They also work perfectly as a mean to reduce contrast between bright computer screen and the background, when the ceiling lights are turned off.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-make-your-own-life-is-strange-photo-wall">How to make your own Life is Strange photo wall</h2>

<p>If you want to create your own Polaroid wall, I have some good news for you: the whole process is actually much simpler than one could think and doesn’t require any tools, although spirit level is recommended for the best effect. If you have all materials at hand and have already planned the layout, you can make your own photo memorial wall in one afternoon (of course, depending on the size of the wall and complexity of your project).</p>

<p><strong>Shopping list – what you are going to need:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Polaroids or print-outs made on a thick, stiff paper</li>
  <li>chain of paper lanterns or other similar lights</li>
  <li>adhesive putty (recommended) or double-sided adhesive tape (not recommended)</li>
  <li>spirit level</li>
  <li>long ruler (optional)</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, let’s talk about each of these items.</p>

<h3 id="life-is-strange-polaroids-or-prints">Life is Strange Polaroids or prints</h3>

<p>They will be the core element of your decoration, so you have to make sure they are of a good quality and all have correct size (any variations in terms of height or width will result in misalignment of neighbouring pictures). The thicker, sturdier the paper they have been printed on, the better, because it is less likely to get bent or damaged when placing the decoration, rearranging pictures or taking them down. You can either print them yourself (naturally, you need to prepare all graphics first) or purchase them online. I bought all my Life is Strange Polaroids from <a href="https://www.etsy.com/uk/shop/TheRewindClub">The Rewind Club</a> on Etsy and I wholeheartedly recommend you that store. They have a wide selection of Polaroids and other merchandise from <em>Life is Strange</em>, <em>Before The Storm</em> and <em>Life is Strange 2</em>.</p>

<h3 id="lights">Lights</h3>

<p>This is the most difficult item to get right. On the contrary to what one could think, it is very hard to find the exact chain of paper lanterns that Max had in her room at Blackwell, both in terms of size and appearance<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Most of the lanterns I checked were either too small or didn’t have paper covers. I really wanted to have lighting as close to the original as possible, and in the end I was ready to assemble them myself, buying empty paper lanterns and generic lights separately. Luckily, my friends recommended me an excellent set that looks almost identical to lights used for Max’s photo wall. I’m talking about <strong>Lunar Lantern Lights</strong> produced by Lights4fun. These are LED lights certified for  both indoor and outdoor use. They come in warm white flavour, which is perfect for my purposes and are easy to set up. There are ten lanterns in one set, but you can connect multiple sets together, creating longer chains. The main difference between these and Max’s lanterns is, their covers are made of polyester, not paper. It makes them refract light in a slightly different way (the glow coming from Lunar Lantern Lights is more pearly, while the one from normal paper lanterns is rather matt). For me, personally, it does not matter in the slightest. Additionally, polyester covers are far more durable and they don’t get dirty easily. The whole set is waterproof, so you can even clean it with water or wet cloth if needed, just remember to keep the plug dry. I found these lamps <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/product/B01ANZR3RO">on Amazon</a>, however you might be able to get these (or something similar) at your local store.</p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lunar-lantern-lights-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lunar-lantern-lights" /></p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-vertical" /></p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-vertical-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-vertical" />
<em>Lunar Lantern Lights used in my installation have polyester covers instead of paper ones, which results in a more pearly, satin glow.</em></p>

<h3 id="adhesive-material">Adhesive material</h3>

<p>Depending on the way you’ll want to mount your Polaroids, you are going to need some sort of adhesive to stick them to the wall. I strongly recommend using <strong>adhesive putty</strong> for the best effect, since it will not damage the paint on the wall or the prints themselves when taking the decoration down. You can shape it into any way you want, it is perfect for holding such light objects like prints or Polaroids against a wall. It also allows for corrections after placing the picture, either by moving it slightly when adhered to the wall, or replacing it entirely in new location. For my Life is Strange photo wall I used <strong>Faber-Castell Tack-It</strong> adhesive putty bought <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Faber-Castell-Reusable-Removable-Adhesive-Multipurpose/dp/B075QDRJWZ">on Amazon</a>, but you can pick whatever brand you want, since they all have virtually the same properties and usability.</p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-adhesive-putty-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-adhesive-putty" />
<em>I used Faber-Castell Tack-It adhesive putty to mount Polaroids on the wall, although you can choose from a multitude of other options.</em></p>

<p>Another option is a <strong>double-sided adhesive tape</strong>. It is cheaper and easier to find in stores, and it offers much stronger connection between the Polaroid and the wall. The problem is, double-sided tape is so strong, it will almost certainly peel off some wall paint when you will try to take the decoration down eventually, not to mention ruining the prints as well (i.e. tearing or delaminating their backs). It also glues both surfaces instantly, so you have only one try to align each print in the correct way.</p>

<p>Alternatively, you can mount a set of cords stretching from wall to wall and attach prints to these cords using clothes pegs. In that way the wall behind will remain intact, but on the other hand you’ll have to find a way of hooking the cords to opposite walls, which might require some drilling.</p>

<h3 id="spirit-level">Spirit level</h3>
<p>I believe this part is self-explanatory. The use of a spirit level will depend on the aesthetics you aim for when creating your own Polaroid wall. If you are a fan of neat, organised compositions, spirit level will make it much, much easier to create a levelled, straight layout, with equal intervals between prints. Generally speaking, the longer the spirit level, the better, because you can control your level for more than a single Polaroid at the time (you can also mark vertical and horizontal intervals directly on your level with a pencil). I’ve been using a regular, 50-centimetre long spirit level I bought years ago, but you can also use a laser line level (although it will not be as comfortable to use in this particular case as an old school spirit level). Of course if you desire to get a more organic appearance of your photo wall and you don’t want (or need) to keep all photographs perfectly aligned, you can just eyeball the level of each row of prints. That, while not neat and perfect, would create a look more resembling the original Polaroid wall seen in <em>Life is Strange</em>.</p>

<h3 id="long-ruler">Long ruler</h3>
<p>If you decide not to use a spirit level (or you are using a laser line level instead) but still want to keep equal spacing between Polaroids, you are going to need something to mark the correct interval, both horizontally and vertically. For that you can use a plain ruler (again, the longer ones would be more convenient), or a long strip of a cardboard, etc. Basically anything that would allow you to measure and mark a distance and that could be placed conveniently at the wall.</p>

<h2 id="making-life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-step-by-step">Making Life is Strange Polaroid wall step by step</h2>

<h3 id="1-plan-your-photo-wall">1. Plan your photo wall</h3>

<p>Before you grab your tools and start putting Polaroids on the wall, you should plan the whole thing and visualise your desired composition. First of all, you need to know how much space do you have available for the decorations and how many photos you want to fit on that space. If you want to incorporate other elements (like the fine art print or the postcard in my case) you need to include them in your plan as well. You can either draw the whole thing or take a picture of a wall and annotate it digitally (see my example below).</p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-layout-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-layout" />
<em>You should plan the entire layout of your photo wall beforehand. The main limiting factor for positioning the lanterns may be the length of the cable available.</em></p>

<p>I recommend you start outlining your composition with placement of the lights. Please keep in mind that one of the factors limiting your layout might be the length of a cable connecting neighbouring lanterns. You need to plan where to place each lantern in a sequence as not to exceed the cable length available to you. Of course the type of lighting will also determine your composition. For example, you might opt for a bare lightbulbs instead of LED lights in paper lanterns. In that case your lights would have a different diameter, which would have to be accounted for in the planning stage.</p>

<hr />
<p><strong>A tip:</strong> you can achieve best results in terms of aesthetics when designing an asymmetrical lighting layout. Try to avoid placing lanterns in a predictable way, at regular intervals, etc. If you are still unsure about it, remember that Max Caulfield photo memorial wall was not symmetrical either.</p>

<hr />

<p>When planning the layout of your photo wall you have many various options, depending on your personal preferences. You can sort or group them in rows or columns thematically by characters, location, the game they are from, etc. You can also arrange them in zones (i.e. group together Blackwell students, adult characters) or place them chronologically, to reflect the progress of the story. A good idea is to group Polaroids with the same/similar dominating colours, so they can create a mosaic of some sort on your wall. You can also embrace the chaos and place them randomly or semi-randomly. Whatever works for you best.</p>

<p>One more thing: when planning your photo wall you should know whether it will be a finished composition or you are going to add some elements later. This will dictate how you are going to place lanterns and other elements (i.e. it may be necessary to put a lantern outside of your current composition, so it would provide enough light to the extension in the future). Always plan for the final version, even if it means that for the time being a part of your Polaroid wall might look unfinished. It will save you much time in the future, keeping you from rearranging the entire thing from scratch.</p>

<h3 id="2-choose-and-collect-all-required-elements-and-tools">2. Choose and collect all required elements and tools</h3>

<p>Having the whole thing outlined, you can start gathering all the decorations, lighting and other items necessary to finish the composition. If buying Polaroids online make sure that they are of a correct size and printed on a good-enough paper. Check the technical requirements for the lights (my lanterns were only available with a UK plug, so I had to buy an adequate adapter for EU sockets beforehand). Get an adhesive putty and try it out at some hidden part of your wall to make sure it does not damage it and can be easily removed. Collect your tools, if you need any. Check the batteries in a laser line level, if you use one.</p>

<h3 id="3-prepare-your-working-place">3. Prepare your working place</h3>
<p>Get yourself some flat surface (a desk, coffee table, couch, etc.) that is big enough to lay out all the Polaroids that will be placed on your wall. Then, using your notes and plan from the first step, recreate the entire composition. Don’t worry about spacing, photos can overlay each other. You only have to make sure that they are sorted correctly (i.e. which photos will be put next to which ones in neighbouring rows/columns). <strong>Double check everything.</strong> It’s easier to make some corrections now rather than to rearrange Polaroids when they are already on the wall. At this stage you may also see that some photos do not work well next to each other, so it is a good moment to make some final rearrangements.</p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-layout-2-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-layout-2" />
<em>To make everything go smoothly recreate your desired composition on a flat surface, like a desk or coffee table, remembering to leave empty space for lanterns or other objects. It will give you an easy reference when transferring your idea onto a wall.</em></p>

<h3 id="4-start-placing-your-first-row-of-photos-at-the-wall">4. Start placing your first row of photos at the wall</h3>
<p>Although you can place Polaroids either by rows or by columns, I strongly recommend the former, because it is much easier to check if everything is levelled and spaced correctly. The first row of pictures is the most important one and it has to be placed precisely, because you are going to use it as a reference for the next ones. In order to minimise errors and inaccuracies, it is best to start with a middle row of a composition rather than the top or bottom one. You can use a spirit level or a ruler to mark the exact interval required in your composition, therefore placing next Polaroids will be easier. <strong>Always believe what the spirit level shows you, not your own eyes.</strong> I cannot stress that enough. If you are 100% sure that the Polaroid is not placed straight, but the spirit level shows you that it is, it is in fact straight. If you are working on a big repetitive pattern (like a grid of Polaroids on a wall) it is ridiculously easy to lost a sense of true level, because our brain will naturally switch to using existing Polaroids placed in a row as a reference for the true level. I was using a spirit level and still, I skew the right third of the layout upward, because I listened to the sense of level perceived with my eyes and not to what the spirit level showed me.</p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-making-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-making" />
<em>You should do your best to place the first row as precisely as possible (you can use a spirit level to check of the Polaroids are straight). It will allow you to work quicker when expanding your composition to the next rows.</em></p>

<p><strong>Remember to leave empty space where you want to place your lights!</strong><sup id="fnref:fn2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>If you are using an adhesive putty, you can place two small pieces of it about 1 centimetre (half of an inch) from the top and bottom edges of the picture, along its centreline. They shouldn’t be too thin, otherwise it would be difficult to scrap them from the wall if they stick. They do, however, need to be relatively flat, as not to cause visible bulge in the print when you press it against the wall.</p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-adhesive-putty-2-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-adhesive-putty-2" />
<em>One piece of adhesive putty is enough to mount a single print on the wall. Just tear it in half and place both pieces near the top and the bottom of a Polaroid, along the centreline. Make sure to flatten the adhesive putty a bit, although don’t make it too thin.</em></p>

<h3 id="5-extend-your-polaroid-wall-from-the-first-row-upwards-and-downwards">5. Extend your Polaroid wall from the first row upwards and downwards</h3>
<p>After successfully placing the first row (and checking several times that it is, in fact, level) you can start expanding your Polaroid wall by adding next rows, starting right above and below the first one and then proceeding outwards. At this stage, if you were precise with the first row, you don’t need to keep the spacing between Polaroids (you can follow the spacing of the original row using a level or a ruler), but you need to carefully check if every new Polaroid is straight. A good idea is to, every couple of Polaroids placed, take a few steps back and look at the wall as a whole from the distance. It will help you to detect potential problems, like some photos being rotated, rows (or parts of them) being skewed, or some photos not mixing very well aesthetically. Don’t be afraid to make necessary adjustments, but also remember that you still have your original layout you are trying to recreate, so you need to be aware of all the deviations you’ve made since the beginning of the work. When you are done check all Polaroids to make sure they are attached securely to the wall.</p>

<h3 id="6-prepare-the-lighting">6. Prepare the lighting</h3>
<p>Assemble the lanterns according to the user’s manual provided with the product. Plug them in to check if they work correctly and there are no dangerous anomalies (smoke, overheating, etc.). If everything is fine, unplug them and start placing lanterns at the reserved spots on the wall. Lunar Lantern Lights are very light, so I had no problem mounting them with the same adhesive putty I used for the Polaroids. You just need to remember to place adhesive on cables above the lanterns themselves, in a way that would allow them to hang in the correct position. You may need to use two of three pieces of adhesive for every mounting point to achieve best results.</p>

<p><img src="../images/life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-3-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-polaroid-wall-lights-3" />
<em>When mounting the lights, remember to place adhesive putty on the cables above the lanterns, so the lanterns hang in the correct position on the wall. You may want to combine two or three pieces of adhesive putty to ensure the mounting is stable.</em></p>

<h3 id="7-enjoy-your-own-max-caulfield-photo-memorial-wall">7. Enjoy your own Max Caulfield photo memorial wall!</h3>
<p>Well done! You did a great job and now you can enjoy your own piece of Arcadia Bay at home 🦋 If you found this tutorial useful, please don’t forget to reach out to me <a href="https://www.twitter.com/kamilleziak">on Twitter</a>, I would love to see a picture of your creation!</p>

<p>Have fun!</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>At least in Europe. Maybe it’s easier in North America. <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Technically, you don’t need to leave empty space for lights, but by doing so you will avoid a situation in which some pictures are permanently obscured by lanterns. <a href="#fnref:fn2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="polaroid" /><category term="photography" /><category term="blackwellacademy" /><category term="decorations" /><category term="tutorial" /><category term="diy" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the things that enchanted me in Life is Strange was Max Caulfield photo memorial wall at Blackwell Academy. It was one of those small details that made me fall in love with this game, contributing to its unique atmosphere. The Polaroid wall in Max’s dorm room allows player to not only appreciate her photography skills, but also learn more about her personality. In some way it also reflects Max’s decisions, especially the ones made at the beginning of the game. Ever since my first playthrough of the game, I’ve been thinking about recreating Max’s photo wall at home. The opportunity for that appeared in August 2019, when I was doing a renovation of my home office. I decided to dedicate a whole wall to Life is Strange. I want to share the final result with you, along with a small DIY tutorial on how to make Max photo wall that will look as similar to the in-game version as possible.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Catra and Adora (Catradora artwork from She-Ra)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/catra-and-adora-artwork-from-she-ra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Catra and Adora (Catradora artwork from She-Ra)" /><published>2020-01-13T18:46:25+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-13T18:46:25+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/catra-and-adora</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/catra-and-adora-artwork-from-she-ra/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/Catra_and_Adora_wm_740px.png" alt="catra-and-adora-artwork-from-she-ra" />
<!--more--></p>

<p>Thanks to the awesome recommendation of my friend, I’ve started watching She-Ra and the Princesses of Power on Netflix recently. I immediately fell in love with the main characters, Adora and Catra. Which means that my first artwork of 2020 is this Catradora piece.</p>

<p>It was drawn in Procreate (which is an excellent program by the way).</p>

<p>For a bigger version click <a href="../images/Catra-and-Adora-wm_resized.png">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="art" /><category term="catra" /><category term="adora" /><category term="she-ra" /><category term="catradora" /><category term="drawing" /><category term="digitalart" /><category term="procreate" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happy New Year 2020</title><link href="https://leziak.com/happy-new-year-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happy New Year 2020" /><published>2020-01-01T11:13:34+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-01T11:13:34+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/happy-new-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/happy-new-year-2020/"><![CDATA[<!--more-->
<p>On this special day, I want to wish you every success for the coming year.</p>

<p><em>Click on the picture to see a full-sized version</em></p>

<p><a href="../images/life-is-strange-neil-gaiman-new-year-wishes.jpg"><img src="../images/life-is-strange-neil-gaiman-new-year-wishes-740px.jpg" alt="life-is-strange-neil-gaiman-new-year-wishes" /></a></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="neilgaiman" /><category term="personal" /><category term="website" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Max Caulfield - simple drawing</title><link href="https://leziak.com/max-caulfield-simple-drawing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Max Caulfield - simple drawing" /><published>2019-09-30T15:21:21+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-30T15:21:21+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/max-caulfield-simple-drawing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/max-caulfield-simple-drawing/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/max-caulfield-simple-drawing.jpg" alt="max-caulfield-simple-drawing" />
<!--more--></p>

<p>One of my first artworks drawn on Wacom Cintiq 16 using Photoshop.</p>

<p>A high resolution version of this drawing is available on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/vertiser/art/Max-Caulfield-simple-drawing-851986076">deviantART</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="art" /><category term="drawing" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="digitalart" /><category term="photoshop" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chloe Price - simple drawing</title><link href="https://leziak.com/chloe-price-simple-drawing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chloe Price - simple drawing" /><published>2019-09-26T10:12:39+02:00</published><updated>2019-09-26T10:12:39+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/chloe-price-simple-drawing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/chloe-price-simple-drawing/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/chloe-price-simple-drawing.jpg" alt="chloe-price-simple-drawing" />
<!--more--></p>

<p>This was my very first drawing made with a Wacom Cintiq 16 in Photoshop. It took me a bit of time to adjust to a new workflow using a display tablet instead of an ordinary graphics tablet.</p>

<p>A high resolution version of this drawing is available on <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/vertiser/art/Chloe-Price-simple-drawing-851986069">deviantART</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="art" /><category term="drawing" /><category term="chloeprice" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="digitalart" /><category term="photoshop" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life is Strange comic book vol. 7 (Waves #3)</title><link href="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-7/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life is Strange comic book vol. 7 (Waves #3)" /><published>2019-07-30T15:21:31+02:00</published><updated>2019-07-30T15:21:31+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/life-is-strange-comic-book-vol-7/"><![CDATA[<p>The previous issue of Life is Strange comic book has been, in my opinion, the best one yet. It was the first issue that I thoroughly enjoyed. Will the seventh one live up to its predecessor? Let’s find out! <!--more--></p>

<p>At this point I’m pretty sure that you have already read (or at least looked at) my articles about all the previous issues of Life is Strange comic book, but if you didn’t (or if you simply want to refresh your memory), you can find all of them under the <a href="https://leziak.com/tags/liscomicbook/">#liscomicbook</a> hashtag.</p>

<p>The cover of issue #7 (the third one in Waves story arc) is pretty simple yet interesting. We can see Max standing in front of a shop window. Next to her reflection there is a reflection of the mysterious guy wearing black, the one that we know from the two last issues. But he is only visible through a reflection, he doesn’t occupy the same physical space as Max. It instantly reminded me of the cover made for the first issue of the comic comic book, the one in which Chloe was next to Max, but her reflection was missing. Is this a sign that the sad guy and Max do not belong to the same timeline or reality? Or maybe <em>neither</em> of them belongs to the reality in which they have met?</p>

<p>I am very skeptical about introducing new original characters into the stories with a well-established set of characters. In this situation I still cannot make myself like this guy, even despite the fact that apparently he will play some crucial role in Waves, otherwise he wouldn’t be featured on the cover. Because this is second-to-last issue, I’m hoping to get some new information about him and why Max can see him even if others can’t (or can only for a brief time).</p>

<p><img src="../images/lis-comic-book-cover-7.jpg" alt="lis-comic-book-6" />
<em>The cover if issue #7 of Life is Strange comic book reminds us that there is more than one reality and not everything is visible for everyone</em></p>

<p>The first scene in this issue shows some shady dealings in the dark alley made at night. Turns out it’s a retrospection showing a little backstory to the sad emo guy’s character. He and his friend were trying to make a deal with some drug dealers but things went wrong. The sad guy – Tristan as it turns out –  disappeared and his best friend got killed. The scene moved us to the girls’ apartment, where Tristan was telling his story to Max in her room. It looks like his powers allow him to become invisible. He uses them to survive on the street, although when Max points out it’s technically stealing, he says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I survive. I take what I need. Only what I need.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While it does not lessen his crimes, it is a bit similar to what Max does in her current timeline. She just survives. While she wants to give Chloe happiness (even if it means seeing her with Rachel as her girlfriend), she, for herself, only wants a bare minimum to remain functional. She does not have ambitions, dreams, hopes (beside seeing Chloe happy). She is only a shadow of her former self. She only wants to survive and that’s what she and Tristan have in common.</p>

<p>Also, Tristan mentioned that his parents are the reason why he lives on the street, they have always considered him a black sheep. It is weirdly familiar to another person who, as we know, was not accepted by his parents, or at least by his father (yep, I’m talking about Nathan Prescott). Although being unaccepted by parents is where the similarities end. As far as I know, Tristan didn’t try to kill anyone or didn’t drug anyone (but we still don’t know his full story).</p>

<p>A few hours later Chloe and Rachel arrive. They banter playfully while Rachel tries to convince Max to go to the party her friends throw. Both girls talk about Rachel’s nearing performance on the East Coast which brings some new informations. Apparently Rachel is trying to take Chloe with her, so they won’t be separated for the six-month-long tour. I didn’t know about it and if it happens, Max will be completely abandoned and even more unhappy than she is now.</p>

<p>But anyway, when Rachel knocks on the door to Max’s room, brunette emerges after a while, introducing Tristan to Chloe and Rachel. That scene was awesome (and hilarious). The look on Chloe’s face when she realised Max was not alone in there was gold! And I love how Chloe’s temper got better of her and she started saying something, before Rachel stopped her in a rather unsophisticated way. It was perfect, showing both Rachel’s and Chloe’s personalities in a realistic way, consistent with Life is Strange and Before the Storm.</p>

<p><img src="../images/lis-comic-book-max-tristan-meeting.jpg" alt="lis-comic-book-max-tristan-meeting" />
<em>The surprised look visible on Chloe’s face when she realised her shy, socially awkward best friend has been socialising with a stranger, was priceless (no pun intended)</em></p>

<p>It looked like Max and Tristan reached some sort of understanding. Max discovered why sometimes she was the only person to see him and he learned about her and her time-travel powers. That was interesting and, actually, not a bad start. Once I learned more about him he didn’t bother me that much in the story. Besides, his appearance in the girls’ apartment resulted in an interesting situation for Max, who was demanded by Chloe and Rachel to explain what he was doing there.</p>

<p>Max told them that both her and Tristan needed some help, needed to talk, so they had helped each other. Of course this didn’t settle too well with Chloe who only the previous day was trying to convince Max to trust her, to share her burden. And she failed. Max tried to explain it, but I’m not sure it made the situation any better when she talked to Chloe:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I know this will make no sense to you, and I wish I could explain it, but… sometimes there are things that are easier to share with a stranger than with people you love.”<br />
“You are right, Max… it makes no sense to me…”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That scene was written and drawn awesomely! Especially the anger, the betrayed trust that was clearly visible in Chloe’s eyes made it so emotional. It was the second time Life is Strange comic book has surprised me in a very positive way. Introducing this new dynamics between Max and Chloe in the previous issue, and now complicating it further with the fact that Max was more willing to tell her secrets to a total stranger than her best friend, it made me hope that the rest of Waves will focus on Max and Chloe and their relationship (unfortunately, only as friends in this timeline).</p>

<p>At last, Max, Chloe and Rachel arrived to the party that Rachel’s friends (if we can use that word referring to acquaintances and social media influencers she knows) organised. I must say, it was amazeballs to see the girls in their evening attires (I don’t think Max has ever appeared in a party dress before, both in the game and comic books), although the party was a festival of cliche and superficiality (but it only made our girls to stand out even better). There was a beautiful and nostalgic scene in which Max and Chloe reflected on how they both have changed since childhood.</p>

<p><img src="../images/lis-comic-book-party-max-chloe-memories.jpg" alt="lis-comic-book-party-max-chloe-memories" />
<em>We played hide and seek in waterfalls… we were younger…</em></p>

<p>In the meantime Tristan (who has been invited to the party by Max) decided he didn’t want to be anywhere near that place, invisible or not. He luckily found an abandoned backpack on the street, in which there was some food… and drugs… and a gun.</p>

<p>And then, at the party, all hell broke lose. It turned out that Callie, the girl who organised all of this, OD’d. Max took her phone and ran out of the building and into the street to get better signal… and then she witnessed how the drug dealers from Tristan’s story were aiming at him with a gun, blaming him and his deceased friend for the arrest of one of their own. The issue finished with a gunshot, although we can’t see what happened.</p>

<p>The seventh issue of Life is Strange comic book was… interesting. Intriguing. And it left me wanting to see more. It wasn’t as good as the previous one (which, again, was so great because it focused on Max entirely) but it was still good. The biggest positive surprise (that I still can’t quite explain) is that Tristan’s story did not bother me as much as I expected. It wasn’t cheesy, it wasn’t over-empathised, it was okay. And knowing his story and his relation to Max made me look at him with a little more sympathy (which does <strong>not</strong> mean that I think he should be featured on the cover as one of the main characters).</p>

<p>I will still hold myself with complementing Waves until I see the conclusion to this story arc presented in issue #8. It all depends on how the story will finish (or, it will rather not finish <em>per se</em>, it will certainly end with some cliffhanger and life-changing event that will set the tone for the third story arc). Both this and the previous issue were enjoyable for me, due to the fact we had much more Max and Chloe screen time than in Waves #1. Although it still hurts me to see that we do not have any realistic chance for Pricefield in this story arc (and probably not in the next one either, if it depicts the events during Rachel’s performances on East Coast). Having said that, there are noticeable improvements to the writing in comparison to Dust and graphics are always on the best level. I recommend reading this issue regardless of your favourite ship or <a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=One%20True%20Pairing">OTP</a>.</p>

<h3 id="yay">Yay!</h3>
<ul>
  <li>focused on Max and Chloe</li>
  <li>we’ve learned about the mysterious guy and his story</li>
  <li>scene when Chloe and Rachel discover Max and Tristan</li>
  <li>Max and Chloe’s talk at the party</li>
  <li>Chloe’s facial expressions</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="nay">Nay!</h3>
<ul>
  <li>drugs, drugs, drugs!</li>
  <li>Rachel and Chloe’s playful banter in their apartment</li>
  <li>the possibility of Chloe going to the East Coast with Rachel</li>
  <li>Tristan’s encounter with the drug dealers</li>
  <li>the party</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="overall-summary-in-three-words">Overall summary in three words</h3>
<p><strong>interesting, multidimensional, enjoyable</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="comicbooks" /><category term="lifeisstrange" /><category term="maxcaulfield" /><category term="chloeprice" /><category term="rachelamber" /><category term="arcadiabay" /><category term="series" /><category term="review" /><category term="recap" /><category term="liscomicbook" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The previous issue of Life is Strange comic book has been, in my opinion, the best one yet. It was the first issue that I thoroughly enjoyed. Will the seventh one live up to its predecessor? Let’s find out!]]></summary></entry></feed>