<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leziak.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://leziak.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-09-03T10:07:43+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leziak.com</title><subtitle>Articles about technology, photography, art, writing and games</subtitle><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><entry><title type="html">Freewrite Traveler after fourteen months</title><link href="https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-after-14-months/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Freewrite Traveler after fourteen months" /><published>2025-02-11T14:25:20+01:00</published><updated>2025-02-11T14:25:20+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-after-14-months</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-after-14-months/"><![CDATA[<p>It has been fourteen months since I bought Freewrite Traveler, an e-Ink device with a sole purpose of writing text and with limited editing capacity. Did it really change how often and how much I write? <!--more--></p>

<p>Well, it <em>did</em>, but not in a way I expected. After an initial honeymoon phase, which lasted for a couple of months, I ended up writing <em>less</em> while owning Freewrite Traveler than I did before. From the end of August 2024 to February 2025 Traveler collected dust on my shelf. Was it Traveler’s fault? No. Maybe. I don’t know.</p>

<p>The first thing I need to state, is that <strong>Freewrite Traveler works as well as it did at the very beginning</strong>. I really cannot complain about the device. It worked as advertised and I was happy with the way it worked. So, in some way, me writing less is not Traveler’s fault. However, I noticed that ever since I got it, even if I had brief moments when I wanted to write something down, and I did not have Traveler with me, I postponed writing session till the time I get my hands on the device. When I finally got home, I was tired or occupied with other things, and ended up not writing at all. Previously, in situations like this I would probably use my iPad to type down a few paragraphs, so in a way it was indeed Traveler’s fault, me writing less.</p>

<p>One of the most important realisations I had after owning Freewrite Traveler for a couple of months was, <strong>it does NOT make you write more</strong>. I cannot stress that enough: if you want to buy a Freewrite device hoping that somehow it would allow you to write more, you will fail. No Freewrite, be it Smart Typewriter, Traveler of their newest product, Alpha, magically creates more writing opportunities or gives you more time to write. All those devices serve their intended purpose <strong>only</strong> when you are actively seeking more opportunities to write. And if you do, it does not matter what are you writing on: an e-Ink device, an iPad, a laptop, or in a paper notebook. If you have a solid writing routine or are self-disciplined enough to always find some time to write, then you will write thousands of words on a Freewrite. Otherwise, you will fail to exact the same excuses as you did when writing on any other device. That is what happened to me: I did not have time to write, and I was not motivated enough to <em>create</em> more time to write, so my Traveler ended up collecting dust for five months. Am I happy because of that? Of course not. But I need to be honest with myself, and with you. If you are not rigorous enough, Freewrite might not make big difference in your writing habits after all.</p>

<p>One thing to consider: although Freewrite Traveler is smaller than most of laptops, it still has a considerable weight. That is why I was not bringing it with me when leaving home, unless I was absolutely sure I would be writing something down on it. I always need to bring with me several things, including a notebook, calendar, phone, powerbank and pen case. None of those items has zero weight or volume, so the space in my bag is more limited (and more valuable) than I had initially thought when considering the purchase of Traveler. Unless something changes, I do not picture myself bringing Traveler with me every time I leave the house, or even <em>half the time</em>. It is a good device, it serves its intended purpose. But it still needs to compete for my attention and for space in my bag, and it usually loses on both fronts.</p>

<p>This article is no. 14 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="freewrite" /><category term="eink" /><category term="keyboard" /><category term="typewriting" /><category term="hardware" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It has been fourteen months since I bought Freewrite Traveler, an e-Ink device with a sole purpose of writing text and with limited editing capacity. Did it really change how often and how much I write?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Traveler’s Notebook Passport Size</title><link href="https://leziak.com/travelers-notebook-passport/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Traveler’s Notebook Passport Size" /><published>2024-10-01T09:49:50+02:00</published><updated>2024-10-01T09:49:50+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/travelers-notebook-passport-size</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/travelers-notebook-passport/"><![CDATA[<p>I may have just found a perfect notebook. <!--more--> As an avid writer who loves analogue experience, I have been using paper notebooks extensively for many years. I keep several notebooks in use, one for every major topic: work, writing, photography, drawing, gaming, etc. This compartmentalisation allows me to work independently on any topic, without the distraction of others, which improves my focus and makes it much easier to find any required information. There is one big caveat, though: when I’m on the move, I need to decide in advance what I will be working on and put appropriate notebook or notebooks in my bag. This quickly gets out of hand for two reasons. First, I often overestimate the amount of free time or the number of things I would be working on, leading to taking too many notebooks, of which some are never used during my trip. Secondly, since I use hardcover notebooks with fountain pen friendly paper, their weight quickly adds up and reaches a level that is not comfortable. Therefore, on most occasions I am forced to leave some notebooks behind and only take what I consider necessity for the given journey.</p>

<p>This system works relatively well, although more than once I found myself regretting not taking a particular notebook with me, because I not only had a time to work on a topic (which on its own is quite rare), I had internal motivation to do so (which is even rarer). Luckily for me, one Summer evening I stumbled across an article explaining the concept of <strong>traveler’s notebooks</strong>. They work in a different way to regular notebooks I have been using for years. <strong>Instead of having many hardcover notebooks that are physically separated, a traveler’s notebook takes a form of a single leather cover, in which one can bound several softcover inserts</strong> (usually by securing them with a rubber band). Each of the inserts acts as a separate notebook, but since they are bound in a single leather cover, they occupy less space and are lighter than separate hardcover notebooks. That’s due to their size (usually somewhat smaller and thinner than a standard A5 notebook) and the lack of a hardcover (inserts have cover made of craft paper or flat cardboard, which makes them thinner).</p>

<p><img src="../images/travelers-notebook-passport-size-olive.jpg" alt="travelers-notebook-passport-size-olive" />
<em>My first Traveler’s Notebook, in Passport Size. The leather ages beautifully, showing all tiny scuffs and marks from everyday use.</em></p>

<p>When I learned about the specifics of a traveler’s notebook system, I immediately knew it had potential to vastly improve my experience. Now, instead of taking a couple of heavy hardcover notebooks with me, I could take a single traveler’s notebook with a couple of inserts and be done with it. What is even better, one can easily swap inserts in a couple of seconds, so I could adjust the content of the traveler’s notebook depending on what I am doing or where I am travelling.</p>

<p>However, switching to a traveler’s notebook system can be quite expensive. There are many brands of traveler’s notebooks, with different notebook format, inserts and, most of all, prices. After a careful deliberation, supported by watching a dozen of hours of reviews, I decided to go with the original Traveler’s Notebook<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, created originally by Midori, presently by The Traveler’s Company. It is a Japan company that has a fairly big experience in stationery and high quality paper. Their notebook was the most pleasing aesthetically, plus the closing rubber band was mounted at the centre of the back cover, what I actually <em>prefer</em> to the mounting point at the spine, prevalent in most of other brands.</p>

<p>I did not want to instantly abandon my old approach to note taking before making sure the traveler’s notebook system is right for me. Therefore I started with a Traveler’s Company Traveler’s Notebook in a so-called “Passport Size”. As the name suggest, the notebook is just big enough for you to safely store your passport inside. I bought a couple of different inserts in this size, acting as separate notebooks for various topics, while I still maintained my regular A5 notebook for the important things, like work, maintenance, etc. It allowed me to test the Traveler’s Notebook without any pressure, as I could always fall back to the original notebooks.</p>

<p>I had been using Traveler’s Notebook Passport Size for three months before I determined that indeed, this is the right solution to my problems. Since then I have also bought a so-called Regular Size Traveler’s Notebook, with dimensions of approximately 1/3 of an A4 sheet of paper. In the weeks to come I plan to gradually move all my note taking to specific notebooks (refills) in my Traveler’s Notebooks, both Regular and Passport Size.</p>

<p>Stay tuned, I will write more about Traveler’s Notebook in the future.</p>

<p><em>This article is no. 13 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I use small letters, as in <em>traveler’s notebook</em>, when I write about this notebook and refill-binding system in general, and capital letters, as in <em>Traveler’s Notebook</em>, when writing about a specific product from The Traveler’s Company. <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="travelersnotebook" /><category term="writing" /><category term="notebook" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I may have just found a perfect notebook.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://leziak.com/images/travelers-notebook-passport-size-olive.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://leziak.com/images/travelers-notebook-passport-size-olive.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hogwarts Legacy: the final battle</title><link href="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-final-battle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hogwarts Legacy: the final battle" /><published>2024-06-25T11:48:14+02:00</published><updated>2024-06-25T11:48:14+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-final-battle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-final-battle/"><![CDATA[<p>As all good things must end eventually, so did my Hogwarts adventure. I have completed the game together with all the quests, achievements and collectibles. Has my opinion on it changed in the meantime? <!--more--> The short answer is no, I still consider Hogwarts Legacy to be an excellent title, not only for Harry Potter fans, but for everyone who wants to feel a bit of magic in their lives.</p>

<p>I must say I haven’t approached the end game in an ordinary way. In the middle of my play I have focused mostly on aquiring the achievements related to collectibles. I was exploring the entire map looking for new Merlin Trials, baloons to pop while airborne, astronomical tables to use, etc. It was fun and exciting experience, because I never knew what I would encounter: a new enemy? Undiscovered place? A riddle to solve? I put many hours into finding all the collectibles, getting the achievements and so on. As a result, when I had nothing left to do but the final quest of the game, I was already at level 39, out of 40 maximum levels available in the game, with most of the revelant perks maxed out, fully upgraded armour and four sets of spells on quick draw. I was more than ready to face Ranrok.</p>

<p>The final quest and the final battle with Ranrok was pleasingly unsurprising: it tested my magic skills, ability to cast different spells in rapid succession, dodge and reposition myself, use elixirs and magic plants—yet none of that was particularly difficult, complicated or frustrating. This is <em>exactly</em> how end game battles should feel most times. Maybe I’m simply too old, or maybe I value my time a little too much, but I no longer feel the pressure to try and punish myself with the highest difficulty level and sweat for hours, trying to defeat the final boss, only to get killed numerous times. In Hogwarts Legacy the balance of the difficulty and weight of the final battle with Ranrok, contrasted with player’s abilities to match the game requirements for speed and dexterity, is perfect, at least on normal difficulty mode. It was not trivial to defeat Ranrok, but it was also not annoyingly difficult. When the battle was over I still had a solid part of my magical supplies left.</p>

<p>One thing I wish Hogwarts Legacy’s developers could change, is the ability to reach the maximum level <em>before</em> the main fight. I was trying hard to do this, but it turned out to be impossible. To reach level 40 one needs to complete all achievements, and one of them can only be completed upon finishing a side quest <em>after</em> the main battle. Unfortunately, this happens quite often in many games: the final level, or the best armour, or the best weapon can often be obtained only so late in the gameplay, those upgrades are no longer useful, because most battles are over by then. The Witcher 1 is a good example of such strategy.</p>

<p>What Hogwarts Legacy did right, though, was the ability to continue the exploration of the game world even after the main plotline is finished. Although I’ve spent dozens of hours immersing myself in the Hogwarts universe, I have not reached a point when I could said “I’m done, I don’t want to see Hogwarts anymore”. I love to, every now and then, load the game and fly around the Hogwarts on my broom, or to play with magical creatures I saved and gave shelter to, or simply to walk through castle’s corridors at night, observing moving portraits, ghosts and other wonders.</p>

<p>I can honestly say that Hogwarts Legacy is the best game I have played in the last year.  I do not know if there is a sequel planned (although I would be really surprised if it weren’t—the game was a global hit), but once Hogwarts Legacy 2 is released, I will gladly return to this magical world.</p>

<p><em>This article is no. 12 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="hogwartslegacy" /><category term="harrypotter" /><category term="nintendoswitch" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As all good things must end eventually, so did my Hogwarts adventure. I have completed the game together with all the quests, achievements and collectibles. Has my opinion on it changed in the meantime?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kaweco BRASS Sport — the smallest and possibly the coolest fountain pen I own</title><link href="https://leziak.com/kaweco-brass-sport-fountain-pen-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kaweco BRASS Sport — the smallest and possibly the coolest fountain pen I own" /><published>2024-03-19T08:48:26+01:00</published><updated>2024-03-19T08:48:26+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/kaweco-brass-sport-fountain-pen-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/kaweco-brass-sport-fountain-pen-review/"><![CDATA[<p>At the beginning of 2024 I acquired a new fountain pen, Kaweco BRASS Sport. I have been looking at it for quite some time, pondering whether it was worth purchasing. In the first week of January I finally decided to check that pen out. Here is my review after two and a half months of usage. <!--more--></p>

<p>When I opened the box my first thought was “this is a <em>really small</em> pen!”. I knew it was small, but seeing it firsthand, I was still surprised by its minuscule size. The size, however, goes in pair with quite a substantial weight, thanks, of course, to the solid brass casing. Closed, the fountain pen has a length of 107 millimetres, but once uncapped and posted, it converts to 135 millimetres, which is more conservative in size. Kaweco BRASS Sport weights 48 grams. In comparison, full-sized Aurora Talentum GT, my everyday carry, weights 34 grams. The bigger weight of Kaweco is a good think, though, because it makes a small pen easier to handle. It is also reassuring when I carry it in my pocket, because I know right away that it is with me and I have not lost it.</p>

<p>Together with the Kaweco BRASS Sport one gets a metal box, which has a black plastic mould inside, which allows to carry up to two Kaweco Sports in a parallel configuration, or a single pen in either a diagonal or straight configuration. It is a nice touch because the box can act as a sturdy case. Not that the fountain pen made of brass requires delicate treatment - on the contrary, it is impressively robust and almost indestructible. I only have one Kaweco Sport now, but in the future I want to get one of each metal collection, that is STEEL, AL and BRONZE versions.</p>

<p><img src="../images/kaweco_brass_sport_case.jpg" alt="kaweco_brass_sport_case" />
<em>The metal box can hold up to two Kaweco Sport pens of any type.</em></p>

<p>In the box we receive a rectangular black sticker with Kaweco logo, as well as a tiny brochure featuring the most important dates in Kaweco’s history, labelled in both German and English (although English translation is not error-free). The metal box is further enclosed in a cardboard sleeve, with sleeve’s outer surface lacquered in black, with white and grey lettering. I appreciate the multi-layered packaging of the fountain pen, offering both enhanced protection as well as serving as a proof of manufacturer’s care. I definitely will be using the metal case in the future, especially once I get another Kaweco Sport. One final addition is a single blue ink cartridge, in an international short size.</p>

<p>Initially, I was surprised to discover that Kaweco does not include a clip with Kaweco Sport fountain pen, but the reason soon became obvious. Due to pen’s size and portability, some people may prefer to not use a clip at all, as not to add additional bulk to the otherwise slim and sleek design. And for those who cannot imagine using a clip-less fountain pen, Kaweco offers a choice of four (!) colours, to combine with any Kaweco Sport as they please. I went for a chrome finish clip, which matches the colour of a steel nib.</p>

<p><img src="../images/kaweco_brass_sport_opened.jpg" alt="kaweco_brass_sport_opened" />
<em>Kaweco Sport does not come with a clip, but one can choose to buy one separately. They are available in four colours: chrome, gold, black and bronze. The chrome one nicely matches the standard steel nib</em></p>

<p>I have also bought a mini converter, to allow for use of bottled ink. However, I have been using ink cartridges so far, mostly because the capacity of the ink converter turned out to be diminutive. I was surprised to see the converter being so small. It holds even less ink than a regular short cartridge, yet it looks like it is of a good quality and sturdy. It should work well for a long time. It is a classic piston converter with a plastic plunge and a rubber seal. The end looks like a standard international receptacle.</p>

<p>When I was reading opinions about Kaweco BRASS Sport, many people had complained about a characteristic smell of metal lingering on their hands after using the brass pen. In my particular case the smell of brass is faint and unobtrusive. It is closest to the smell of a coin. It lingers on a hand slightly, but is only noticeable to me when I stick my palm just under my nose. Washing my hands with a regular soap gets rid of it easily. It should be noted, however, that since the above-mentioned smell is a product of metal staying in contact with skin oils, it is possible that both the intensity and duration of the smell would vary from person to person.</p>

<p>Regarding the nib, I use a regular Kaweco Steel F nib, although one can swap it really easily with a gold-coated version or a different size. The nib is robust and works well regardless of time spent unused. The ink does not dry out in a capped pen, but the nib experiences occasional dry starts. There is no skipping or scratching, though. The width of a line produced by an F nib is approximately 0.3-0.4 millimetre, and there is virtually no variation in line width, which is consistent with a steel, non-flexible nib.</p>

<p><img src="../images/kaweco_brass_sport_nib.jpg" alt="kaweco_brass_sport_nib" />
<em>The regular steel nib is nothing fancy, but it is reliable and robust enough, despite some dry starts every now and then</em></p>

<p>I have some pens with nibs that write nicer, although I would be afraid to use them in a situation when I need to scribe something down hastily, for the fear of applying too much pressure and deforming the nib. In that regard a steel nib of Kaweco Sport resembles a regular pen in terms of its resistance and usability. This reaffirms that Kaweco BRASS Sport is a perfect fountain pen for everyday carry.</p>

<p>After purchasing Kaweco BRASS Sport I found myself carrying a fountain pen much more often than before, due to its pocket size and toughness. This brass pen is incredibly robust. I have always worried about accidentally damaging my fountain pens when carrying them casually in a pocket, and this pen has absolutely removed my fear. I have a feeling that I could let a tank drive over it and the pen would still be functional.</p>

<p>I was surprised to observe how quickly the patina developed on brass and how dark it is. It was a matter of a couple of days, at most, and I were not even using the pen all that much. I store my fountain pens in a natural leather roll case, so maybe that was a factor in catalysing the patina development. Interestingly, there are few places where patina has not developed yet, mostly near the clip and its mount. It allows me to compare the original look of the fountain pen out of the box with its current tone. I preferred the raw, initial look of brass without the patina, mostly because the patina made brass look duller and noticeably darker.</p>

<p><img src="../images/kaweco_brass_sport_patina.jpg" alt="kaweco_brass_sport_patina" />
<em>I was bewildered by how quickly the patina developed on brass casing, and how dull it made it look in comparison to the original shine</em></p>

<p>When writing for longer periods of time (an hour or so) the weight of the fountain pen may tire one’s hand quicker than a lighter, ebonite or aluminium pen. The solution is to simply un-post the pen and put the cap away. It makes Kaweco BRASS Sport half as heavy but also half as long, which may be another important factor in ergonomics. Nevertheless, I found this fountain pen to be a good choice regardless of its weight.</p>

<p><img src="../images/kaweco_brass_sport_closed.jpg" alt="kaweco_brass_sport_closed" />
<em>The robustness and small size of Kaweco BRASS Sport make it a perfect pocket pen for everyday carry</em></p>

<p>In general, Kaweco BRASS Sport is a perfect everyday pen for me, and I am already looking forward to expanding my collection with the bronze version. Of course, should I purchase Kaweco BRONZE Sport, I will publish my opinion as well.</p>

<h3 id="yay">Yay!</h3>
<ul>
  <li>durability</li>
  <li>brass finish</li>
  <li>portability</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="nay">Nay!</h3>
<ul>
  <li>patina makes the pen look dull</li>
  <li>slight smell of coins</li>
  <li>may be tiring to use in very long session when posted</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="overall-summary-in-three-words">Overall summary in three words:</h3>
<p><strong>interesting, unique, pocketable</strong></p>

<p><em>This is article no. 11 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="fountainpen" /><category term="handwriting" /><category term="writing" /><category term="kaweco" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[At the beginning of 2024 I acquired a new fountain pen, Kaweco BRASS Sport. I have been looking at it for quite some time, pondering whether it was worth purchasing. In the first week of January I finally decided to check that pen out. Here is my review after two and a half months of usage.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://leziak.com/images/kaweco_brass_sport_case.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://leziak.com/images/kaweco_brass_sport_case.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">13 years on deviantART</title><link href="https://leziak.com/13-years-deviantart/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="13 years on deviantART" /><published>2024-02-06T08:22:53+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-06T08:22:53+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/13th-deviantart-anniversary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/13-years-deviantart/"><![CDATA[<p>This morning I was surprised by a message from deviantART, stating “Happy Anniversary, vertiser!”<!--more--></p>

<p><img src="../images/deviantart_13th_anniversary.png" alt="deviantart" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>vertiser, you’ve been a deviant for 13 years!
Here’s to another year of creativity and inspiration.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Apparently I created an account on deviantart.com on the 6th of February 2011. I must admit I only remember the year, not the exact date, and if not for that e-mail, I would not have guessed that today is my deviantART anniversary. At this moment deviantART is one of the places on the Internet where my presence is the longest. The earliest still active profile is my YouTube account, set up in January 2005.</p>

<p>I had originally joined deviantART in an endeavour to explore the art of photography. 2011 was the year when I upgraded from my compact camera (well, it was Konica Minolta Dimage Z3, so it was not <em>that</em> compact) to a Digital Single-Lens Reflex Camera, namely Nikon D90. It was a huge upgrade for me, basically in every aspect of photography. Better sensor, bigger resolution, a true pentaprism viewfinder instead of a poor electronic one in Minolta. Interchangeable lenses and plethora of accessories, like filters and flashes, made it a wonderful piece of equipment for me.</p>

<p>But I had joined deviantART before I even bought that Nikon. I wanted to see how others work with light, composition, objects and people in order to create an interesting piece of art. DeviantART was like an infinite source of inspiration, curiosity and motivation to expand my knowledge, try out some new ideas, improve the technical aspect of my photographs. With time I made some connections with other members of deviantART community, joined some groups, engaged in discussions and conversations on various topics related to art and photography. DeviantART was a happy place back then.</p>

<p>Unfortunately there were some rather controversial changes in deviantart.com look, features and core aspects. One things that caused the mass exodus of users was the forced change into a new layout, which, in my opinion, has completely destroyed deviantART’s originality, making it just one of hundreds of photo- and art-sharing websites. There were some other changes that followed, which alienated big part of the community even further. Still, there is some magic left in deviantART and its longevity, and perhaps the website will rise again in the future.</p>

<p>I am not an active user of deviantART nowadays, mostly because I do not publish any new photographs or artworks. I hope to return to that website at some point in the future. Perhaps I will be there on my 14th anniversary or maybe sooner? Time will tell.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 10 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="photography" /><category term="art" /><category term="deviantart" /><category term="internet" /><category term="photography" /><category term="art" /><category term="dslr" /><category term="nikon" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This morning I was surprised by a message from deviantART, stating “Happy Anniversary, vertiser!”]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://leziak.com/images/deviantart_13th_anniversary.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://leziak.com/images/deviantart_13th_anniversary.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hogwarts Legacy in the middle of the adventure</title><link href="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-middle-adventure/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hogwarts Legacy in the middle of the adventure" /><published>2024-02-05T10:19:22+01:00</published><updated>2024-02-05T10:19:22+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-middle-of-the-adventure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-middle-adventure/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been playing Hogwarts Legacy for some time now and have advanced in the story and the discovery of game’s world. After putting about 20-25 hours in the game I can say that the magical world is more and more fascinating with every hour spent within. <!--more--></p>

<p>I have enjoyed the world created for the game from the very beginning. It was not entirely unknown to me, as I have been a fan of Harry Potter books since my late childhood. I know how Hogwarts was presented in movies, how it is depicted in books, but being able to explore the castle myself is an entirely new experience. It is obvious that developers spent many hours crafting the world that is both homogenous with cinematic source material and captivating for players. Hogwarts Legacy makes me want to lose myself in the world of magic and wonder, providing an immersive experience that is entertaining for both adults and children alike. There were many occasions on which I have been casually exploring my surroundings, looking for floating keys, magical creatures or simply enjoying the magnificent view, instead of progressing the main mission or a side quest.</p>

<p>This is a huge plus of Hogwarts Legacy: it allows one to choose their own adventure and play the game their way. There are days when I am focusing on a certain mission, or learning a new spell. On other days I can wander around, looking for magical plants to replenish my supplies needed for crafting potions. There are some days when I am focused on acquiring certain collectibles or discovering new locations to use the <a href="https://harrypotter.fandom.com/wiki/Floo_powder">floo powder</a> to teleport to. My playstyle varies from day to day but regardless, Hogwarts Legacy is always an enjoyable and entertaining title.</p>

<p>I am playing Hogwarts Legacy on Nintendo Switch and while I am aware that the graphics are inferior to those on PCs or other consoles, I am absolutely satisfied with the visuals delivered. To be honest, Hogwarts Legacy on Nintendo Switch looks <em>better</em> than I expected. Special effects related to magic are attractive and the entire experience is cohesive and well-thought, unlike many Switch ports which make playing on a console frustrating (I am looking at you, Skyrim). There are some occasional glitches or stutters, especially when lighting changes due to weather or time of the day, but they do not impact the experience and do not break the immersion. User interface and controls are quite intuitive, although changing spells casted during fights requires some practise. I should also mention the music and sound effects, which greatly enhance the experience. I am playing in docked mode only but I suppose they would be even more important in hand held mode, when one uses headphones. Speaking of the audio side of the game, I cannot ignore the excellent voice acting for the characters living in the magical world. Everything about Hogwarts Legacy shows developers’ care and attention to details.</p>

<p>Although I am not yet in the middle of the <em>story itself</em> (I would even dare to say I barely scratched the surface of Hogwarts’ world) I can confidently say that this is one of the best games available for Nintendo Switch, and one of the best games I have ever played. I am looking forward to discovering more magical secrets and becoming a true master of wizardy. And I will document my progress along the way.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 9 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="hogwartslegacy" /><category term="harrypotter" /><category term="nintendoswitch" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been playing Hogwarts Legacy for some time now and have advanced in the story and the discovery of game’s world. After putting about 20-25 hours in the game I can say that the magical world is more and more fascinating with every hour spent within.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sometimes older things work better than new ones</title><link href="https://leziak.com/older-things-better-than-new/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sometimes older things work better than new ones" /><published>2024-01-31T07:58:19+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-31T07:58:19+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/older-things</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/older-things-better-than-new/"><![CDATA[<p>It may not be an universal truth, but it happens often enough. Nowadays planned obsolescence prevails, but in the past, when both labour and materials were more expensive, things were built to last a lifetime. <!--more--></p>

<p>Yesterday a colleague at work asked me to borrow a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barometer">barometer</a> to conduct some research. She asked if we had a digital barometer available that can be moved from one place to another. I told her that our digital barometer is stationary, permanently mounted in a fixed location, but we can lend her an older, analogue device, called an aneroid, which is portable.</p>

<p>That particular device in question, an aneroid used to measure barometric pressure of the Earth atmosphere, was produced in 1939, that is 85 years ago, in the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR), a country that no longer exists. Yet, the aneroid works perfectly well despite its age, and is far more accurate than the majority of consumer-grade digital barometers currently in sale. If one were to match its accuracy, a digital barometer in the range of a thousand US dollars or more would be required. Still, the robustness and the high build quality of that analogue aneroid means it will probably be working well fifty years from now, while I have little hope for its digital counterpart to reach a similar lifespan.</p>

<p>Various materials, electronics and labour are cheaper now that at any previous point in history. This is both the blessing and the curse of our times. We can get any device, machine or tool imaginable, but most of those items will be obsolete, broken or otherwise useless in a couple of years, a decade or two at most. Every year smartphone producers convince us that we need the newest, the fastest, the thinnest model, with the best camera possible. And all the older, unwanted, less-than-the-best-but-still-very-capable devices will fill up drawers or, at worst case, landfills.</p>

<p>Somewhere in the ever-present race to get the best, shiniest things we have lost appreciation for things that are older and yet just as capable, if not better than their newer replacements. Of course this is not an universal and always-true paradigm, but in many cases older or even “vintage” (although this term is interpreted in a wildly varying manner) things are forgotten, even if they get the job done no worse than modern variants.</p>

<p>I am not immune to the allure of new and bright things, and I often buy products when I still have an older, working version. But I try to use some older things whenever it is possible or whenever I perceive them as superior to newer models. One example are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_single-lens_reflex_camera">Digital Single-Lens Reflex Cameras</a>, which, in my opinion, were the peak of photographic technology. Modern <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirrorless_camera">mirrorless cameras</a> have digital viewfinder instead of a prism or a set of mirrors, which is the biggest downside for me. No matter how great a digital screen is, it will never compare to an actual optical track leading from the lens to the eyepiece, with virtually infinite resolution, no delay and no power drawn. That is why I still use my old Nikon D90 and have no plans to move into the mirrorless dominium.</p>

<p>Sometimes older things are simply better.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 8 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="misc" /><category term="technology" /><category term="meteo" /><category term="barometer" /><category term="aneroid" /><category term="hardware" /><category term="dslr" /><category term="mirrorless" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It may not be an universal truth, but it happens often enough. Nowadays planned obsolescence prevails, but in the past, when both labour and materials were more expensive, things were built to last a lifetime.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Freewrite Traveler a month and a half later</title><link href="https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-month-and-half-later/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Freewrite Traveler a month and a half later" /><published>2024-01-30T11:21:39+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-30T11:21:39+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-after-month-half</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-month-and-half-later/"><![CDATA[<p>Last December I bought Freewrite Traveler, a smart typewriter with an e-Ink screen, in a laptop form factor. I have spent six weeks with the device so far. How did it change my writing habits? <!--more--></p>

<p>During those six weeks I was using Freewrite Traveler on a semi-daily basis. It became my go-to device when preparing new articles for this website, mostly because it was easy (and fun) to write using a device with an e-Ink screen. I sticked to the distraction-free rule, meaning that when working on Traveler I avoided using my phone or computer, unless it was absolutely necessary for some research related to the article I was writing. It worked really well for me, making it noticeable easier and faster to finish an article. Something about Traveler and its single purpose makes words flow much easier than when I am sitting in front of a computer, with many other programmes open in the background, besides the word processor itself. Having said that, I have to note that it was still a challenge to find time to write with my current work schedule. So, while Traveler makes it <em>easier</em> to write, it does not magically makes it easier to <em>find time to write</em>. There were a few occasions on which I simply decided not to bother with opening Traveler, however chances of me using a computer to write something were even slimmer on those days.</p>

<p>The simplicity of turning Traveler on and its readiness to accept any words I might type within a few seconds makes it almost a perfect device for writing things down in a moment of inspiration. My experience has not been frictionless, though. On two separate occasions I found Traveler completely unresponsive, despite it working normally the previous evening and having its battery sufficiently charged. Both times Traveler froze and did not accept any keyboard input, nor did it acknowledge plugging the charger in (the battery indicator light simply did not turn on, like if the charging circuit within the Traveler was inactive). Initially I was worried, and couldn’t quite understand why this had happened. But once I referred to the manual prepared by Astrohaus, I noticed a short tutorial on what to do in such situation. By simply keeping power button pressed for 15 seconds one can force Traveler to restart regardless of the status of its software and indeed, it prompted my device to “wake up” and start working normally, including a detection of the charging cable being plugged in. During such restart Freewrite Traveler performs a cold start, so it can take about two minutes before the booting process is complete and one can start writing. In contrast, putting Traveler to sleep by simply closing the lid makes it boot up almost instantaneously after the lid is opened again, allowing for a faster beginning of the work. On the other hand, even in sleep mode Traveler’s battery slowly drains, so if one wants to put Freewrite away for prolonged period of time it is best to turn the device off completely.</p>

<p>Fortunately, once Traveler was working again after the freeze I noticed that none of my texts were missing, and the device was synchronised with Postbox. I would not have lost any progress anyway, because I always send my texts to e-mail as a backup, but it is reassuring to see that even in the event of device’s software freezing no work is lost (or no work has been lost in this particular case; your mileage may vary).</p>

<p>The second freeze happened two days later, in similar circumstances. I finished my work for the day and closed the lid, and once I opened Traveler on the next day it was unresponsive. Again, I was forced to use the trick mentioned in the manual to restart the device, and after booting up it was back in working order. No files were lost.</p>

<p>Both incidents happened sometime at the end of December, and I have not experienced any troubles with Traveler ever since. I do not know what caused those issues in the first place, but the fairy close interval suggests some problems with either the firmware or Astrohaus servers. A couple of days before, Traveler’s firmware caught up to date after a series of updates, so maybe that caused both freezes? Or maybe it was due to some issues with the server to which Freewrite devices connect? I can only speculate, but what is important in such case, is that the fix described in the manual works and no files are lost<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>To be honest, it did make me feel uncomfortable to experience such software freezes so quickly after purchasing Traveler. However, the problem had little consequences and did not impede my workflow that much. Naturally, I would prefer my writing device to work all the time, but considering the experimental nature of Freewrite, I can forgive Astrohaus a mishap or two.</p>

<p>Going back to my experiences with writing on Traveler, I can say that it works well. The e-Ink screen is a delight to look at, and the lack of built-in light is compensated by commonly available external light sources (I use Traveler either at work or in my home office, so I can comfortably use additional light in either of those locations). The delay of an e-Ink screen is no factor for me, because I look at the keyboard when writing. And the keyboard itself, while not mechanical, is <em>the best</em> scissor-switch device I have ever typed on. Key travel is deep for a scissor-switch keyboard, keycaps are comfortable and sturdy, key size and spacing is very close to a normal-sized laptop. I only wish there was a variant with ISO layout available, but as I have mentioned before, Astrohaus decision to get rid of different physical keyboard variants is understandable.</p>

<p>For me Freewrite Traveler is everything it was promised to be. Nothing more, but at the same time, nothing less. It is not a fully functional word processor, but it was never advertised as such. It is not a replacement for Word, or Pages, or <a href="https://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener">Scrivener</a>, but again, it was not expected to be. It is a piece of hardware with fairy narrow functionality, but within its limits it performs really, really well. After almost two months I am still satisfied with my purchase and I can say with all certainty that without Traveler I would not have written nearly half as many words as I did. Distraction-free writing just works.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 7 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>with a big asterisk, since two cases of an issue on a single device are hardly representative for the whole population of Freewrite devices <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="freewrite" /><category term="eink" /><category term="keyboard" /><category term="typewriting" /><category term="hardware" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last December I bought Freewrite Traveler, a smart typewriter with an e-Ink screen, in a laptop form factor. I have spent six weeks with the device so far. How did it change my writing habits?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Animal Crossing: New Horizons - a lovely, peaceful game for everyone</title><link href="https://leziak.com/animal-crossing-new-horizons/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Animal Crossing: New Horizons - a lovely, peaceful game for everyone" /><published>2024-01-29T10:18:01+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-29T10:18:01+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/animal-crossing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/animal-crossing-new-horizons/"><![CDATA[<p>I have joined the Animal Crossing party quite late, in the second half of 2023, although I had been considering beginning my adventure on a tropical island for quite some time. I can honestly say that Animal Crossing: New Horizons is a unique game and one that I will probably play for many years to come. What made is so special for me? <!--more--></p>

<p>First of all, Animal Crossing is beautifully uncompetitive. In a world dominated by ever-present rankings, competition and rivalry Animal Crossing takes a firm stand in the domain of peaceful, casual gaming. It shows that a game can be successful without a leaderboard and without putting the constant pressure on players. It is a very interesting approach, not very popular among modern titles, which often use rankings as a way of increasing players’ engagement. I believe that Animal Crossing approach is more fulfilling and adequate, though. In a world dominated by the constant desire to be the best at all cost there is something inspiring in an approach focused on cooperation and sharing common values.</p>

<p>One way in which Animal Crossing shines is, in my opinion, its way of instilling kindness and positive emotions in people. All interactions with other inhabitants of our tropical island are based on kind, peaceful gestures, help and support. I cannot find a single thing that would emanate negative energy in Animal Crossing, which is simply beautiful. We need more games showing us that goodness and kindness not only have place in this world, but they can be the foundation of modern world.</p>

<p>Throughout our adventure on an island we help our neighbours build their houses, we reunite them with lost items, can exercise together, have pleasant conversations and share many milestones in island’s development. The gameplay is fairy simple at its core: we do not have any strict objectives and limitations. There are certain tasks that we are expected to perform, but it is entirely up to us whether we will do that straight away or take our time. Repaying the home loan, for example, can be done in a fairly fast manner, or whenever we feel like it. There are no interests and no penalties for not paying the mortgage. heck, we don’t even need to pay the loan at all, unless we want to expand our house.</p>

<p>As for other objectives, we can hunt for bugs, fishes and other sea creatures, we can collect fossils and donate them to the museum, we can try our luck in gardening, planting trees, flowers and bushes of various kind. We can even decorate the entire island if we feel like it, not to mention decorating our own home in any way we see fit. The possibilities are almost endless. I believe that at least some of Animal Crossing success comes from a simple fact that every player can play this game in their own way. You want to focus on the expansion of the village and bringing new animals to live in your paradise? You certainly can. Or maybe you would like to decorate your home according to the newest trends in interior design? Have a go at it. Do you want to be a nature lover and collect all the land and sea creatures that can be donated to the museum? You are most welcome to do so. You decide what you will do and how you will shape the future of your island.</p>

<p>Animal Crossing: New Horizons is one of the least stressful games one can play (if not the least stressful). Unironically, it makes it especially useful for adults, since we tend to have too much stress in our daily lives, and every chance at getting away from the troubles of everyday life in such a friendly environment is precious. Some games can be emotionally taxing, especially if they are associated with online activity with huge doses of competitiveness (Escape from Tarkov is a perfect example). Animal Crossing, on the other hand, makes one calmer, happier and overall more relaxed. There were many days when I returned from work tired and not really in the mood for playing any games, and while I often resigned from turning on my PC, I frequently grabbed my Nintendo Switch and played Animal Crossing even for a couple of minutes. It definitely helped me unwind after a long day.</p>

<p>The structure of Animal Crossing gameplay will not be perfect for everybody, though. The game is pretty open, but every day there is limited amount of resources one can collect. Many processes happen over several days, as the time in game flows at the same rate as in the real world. There are certain vendors or NPCs visiting the island only on certain days and one needs to learn to be patient in order to not get frustrated by the waiting. But that waiting is also what makes Animal Crossing so perfect: things happen in an organic way. One does not feel any artificial time gating, which is pretty popular in <a href="../tags/fallout76">Fallout 76</a>, for example, and one’s patience is always rewarded. I read that some players change system time on their consoles to make things happen faster in Animal Crossing, but in my opinion such action completely misses the point of playing that game in the first place. 95% of other games are fast paced and competitive, and so is the real world. We do not need to transfer that attitude into a game which main purpose is to calm and relax us. Not to mention that observing how things change in game can be a rewarding experience. For example, seasons on our tropical island are linked to actual seasons in the hemisphere we are located in. I started playing Animal Crossing: New Horizons in Summer, and it was so lovely to enjoy the vibrant atmosphere of my island. But observing how its features, weather and colours change as the seasons change around me in real life was definitely satisfying. Of course purists would say that there are no four seasons on tropical islands, and there is virtually no snow there at any point throughout the year, but it is a game, and games do not need to be a perfect reflections of reality. In fact, the games I enjoy the most are, in one way or another, quite different from real world. I use games as a form of escapism, and for that I do not need them to remind the real world.</p>

<p>Right now I am still at a fairy early stage of my adventure in Animal Crossing. I have paid all my home loans, but I haven’t progressed various tasks and quests much. I still have mostly empty rooms in my house and I need to gather some resources to craft furnitures and appliances that would fill the otherwise empty interior. I still need to connect all parts of my island with bridges and ramps, instead of carelessly vaulting through the river to explore the distant areas. I have donated dozens of various creatures to the museum, making many exhibitions possible, yet there are many more bugs, fishes and other creatures that still elude me. It will definitely take months, if not years, to catch them all but I don’t mind. I love Animal Crossing for the adventure, and the road is what matters here, not the end point.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 6 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="nintendoswitch" /><category term="animalcrossing" /><category term="games" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have joined the Animal Crossing party quite late, in the second half of 2023, although I had been considering beginning my adventure on a tropical island for quite some time. I can honestly say that Animal Crossing: New Horizons is a unique game and one that I will probably play for many years to come. What made is so special for me?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why a catch-all e-mail configuration may not be the best idea</title><link href="https://leziak.com/catch-all/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why a catch-all e-mail configuration may not be the best idea" /><published>2024-01-23T14:04:42+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-23T14:04:42+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/catch-all</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/catch-all/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been aware of the importance of a proper e-mail configuration and strict privacy for a long time, which is the main reason why I had left Gmail many years ago and migrated to another provider. One of advices I saw in many places on the Internet was to set up a <em>catch-all</em> e-mail domain, to ensure the convenience and privacy when using many accounts in various places online. <!--more--></p>

<p>In normal circumstances a person has one e-mail address in a single domain, i.e. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email@domain.com</code>. There is no explicit need to set up separate addresses for each and every service one uses their e-mail for. For example, I can use the same address with my social media accounts, utility companies, and so on. The issue that arises is, when many organisations, companies and individuals have one’s e-mail address in their databases, it is only a matter of time before one’s address leaks into the web and is used by third parties to send tons of spam. To avoid that, one can set up separate e-mail addresses, distinctive for each website and service they use. For example, one can set up an e-mail account (or simply just an alias forwarding messages to the main address) called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email2@domain.com</code> and use it only to log into a single website or service. That way, if they start to receive spam to that address they can first, identify that the company for which an account has been set up with that address has leaked that address, either intentionally or unintentionally. And secondly, they can simply delete that e-mail account or remove/disable the alias in order to stop receiving spam coming to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email2@domain.com</code>.</p>

<p>That approach would work easily for a dozen or so services or websites, but the more different accounts one would have on different websites, the more tiresome managing separate e-mail accounts or aliases can become. At one point I had over <em>two hundred</em> accounts on different websites, for various services, social media, discussion boards, etc. It would be simply impractical for me to manage that many separate accounts or aliases, so I turned towards a more systemic approach. Depending on one’s e-mail provider, it can be possible to set up a configuration called a <em>catch-all</em>. It allows the user to create e-mail aliases <em>ad hoc</em>, without any configuration, by simply allowing for messages sent to <em>any</em> e-mail address in their domain to be forwarded to their main e-mail account (or to any account they own). Of course, this option is only possible when one owns the domain in which they have their e-mail address. It is not possible to set up a <em>catch-all</em> configuration for a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@gmail.com</code> address, for example. But if one owns the domain in which their e-mail address ends, it is possible to configure their e-mail so messages sent to any address whatsoever ending in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@domain.com</code> will be forwarded to their inbox.</p>

<p>Such setting allows for a convenient creation of aliases on the go. Since e-mails sent to any address in one’s domain will appear in their main mailbox, there is no need to set up any aliases in e-mail configuration options — one could even type a random set of letters before the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@domain.com</code> and message sent to such random address would still be delivered to them. With <em>catch-all</em> enabled one can type any e-mail addresses on any websites. If one is setting up a Mastodon account on one of many servers, they can use address <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mastodon@domain.com</code>. If they are configuring their account at the electricity provider, they can use an address like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">energy@domain.com</code> or just <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">company@domain.com</code>. That way if they start receiving spam to the e-mail address they shared with that specific company only, they can be certain their address got leaked by the company.</p>

<p>When I finally enabled <em>catch-all</em> for my e-mail domain I decided to wait for few weeks before I would start changing e-mail addresses associated with each of my two hundred accounts to a unique one, clearly identifying the company or its service. Since I had no previous experience with <em>catch-all</em>, I was wary to observe any potential adverse effects of enabling that option. And indeed, once <em>catch-all</em> became active, I started receiving even <em>more</em> spam than before!</p>

<p>Initially, I was bewildered by that change. After all, I enabled that option to increase my privacy and reduce the usage of my primary e-mail address in places where it is not necessary. But quick analysis of new spam messages that started appearing after <em>catch-all</em> was turned on revealed that those were advertisements sent to some most common pre-defined e-mail addresses, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">contact@domain.com</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">info@domain.com</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">office@domain.com</code> and so on. I did not see that spam previously because I simply did not have such addresses created in the first place, therefore the e-mail server kept rejecting those messages, since they could not be delivered to a non-existent e-mail address. But enabling <em>catch-all</em> changed server’s response in a way that any e-mail sent to a non-existent address would be forwarded to my main e-mail account (after all, that is what <em>catch-all</em> is all about). That resulted in an increased volume of spam that reached my inbox.</p>

<p>Perhaps spam filters of my e-mail provider would have eventually caught up with the new spam making its way into my inbox, but since those messages had not been reaching me before, my personal filter was not trained to block them effectively. After few weeks I have decided that <em>catch-all</em> was more trouble than it was worth and have disabled that option. My inbox instantaneously became cleaner, and few spam messages that still managed to reach my inbox were put in spam folder automatically by the filter.</p>

<p>Perhaps there is a way to set up <em>catch-all</em> in a way that takes into account a list of certain addresses it rejects messages sent to automatically, although it would became <em>catch-some</em> in that circumstances. I have not explored the topic any further but if you have any experience in that regard feel free to <a href="../about">let me know</a>.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 5 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="technology" /><category term="email" /><category term="internet" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been aware of the importance of a proper e-mail configuration and strict privacy for a long time, which is the main reason why I had left Gmail many years ago and migrated to another provider. One of advices I saw in many places on the Internet was to set up a catch-all e-mail domain, to ensure the convenience and privacy when using many accounts in various places online.]]></summary></entry></feed>