<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://leziak.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://leziak.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-23T14:13:39+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Leziak.com</title><subtitle>Articles about technology, photography, art, writing and games</subtitle><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><entry><title type="html">Why a *catch-all* e-mail configuration may not be the best idea</title><link href="https://leziak.com/catch-all/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why a *catch-all* e-mail configuration may not be the best idea" /><published>2024-01-23T14:04:42+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-23T14:04:42+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/catch-all</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/catch-all/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been aware of the importance of a proper e-mail configuration and strict privacy for a long time, which is the main reason why I had left Gmail many years ago and migrated to another provider. One of advices I saw in many places on the Internet was to set up a <em>catch-all</em> e-mail domain, to ensure the convenience and privacy when using many accounts in various places online. <!--more--></p>

<p>In normal circumstances a person has one e-mail address in a single domain, i.e. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email@domain.com</code>. There is no explicit need to set up separate addresses for each and every service one uses their e-mail for. For example, I can use the same address with my social media accounts, utility companies, and so on. The issue that arises is, when many organisations, companies and individuals have one’s e-mail address in their databases, it is only a matter of time before one’s address leaks into the web and is used by third parties to send tons of spam. To avoid that, one can set up separate e-mail addresses, distinctive for each website and service they use. For example, one can set up an e-mail account (or simply just an alias forwarding messages to the main address) called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email2@domain.com</code> and use it only to log into a single website or service. That way, if they start to receive spam to that address they can first, identify that the company for which an account has been set up with that address has leaked that address, either intentionally or unintentionally. And secondly, they can simply delete that e-mail account or remove/disable the alias in order to stop receiving spam coming to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email2@domain.com</code>.</p>

<p>That approach would work easily for a dozen or so services or websites, but the more different accounts one would have on different websites, the more tiresome managing separate e-mail accounts or aliases can become. At one point I had over <em>two hundred</em> accounts on different websites, for various services, social media, discussion boards, etc. It would be simply impractical for me to manage that many separate accounts or aliases, so I turned towards a more systemic approach. Depending on one’s e-mail provider, it can be possible to set up a configuration called a <em>catch-all</em>. It allows the user to create e-mail aliases <em>ad hoc</em>, without any configuration, by simply allowing for messages sent to <em>any</em> e-mail address in their domain to be forwarded to their main e-mail account (or to any account they own). Of course, this option is only possible when one owns the domain in which they have their e-mail address. It is not possible to set up a <em>catch-all</em> configuration for a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@gmail.com</code> address, for example. But if one owns the domain in which their e-mail address ends, it is possible to configure their e-mail so messages sent to any address whatsoever ending in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@domain.com</code> will be forwarded to their inbox.</p>

<p>Such setting allows for a convenient creation of aliases on the go. Since e-mails sent to any address in one’s domain will appear in their main mailbox, there is no need to set up any aliases in e-mail configuration options — one could even type a random set of letters before the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@domain.com</code> and message sent to such random address would still be delivered to them. With <em>catch-all</em> enabled one can type any e-mail addresses on any websites. If one is setting up a Mastodon account on one of many servers, they can use address <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">mastodon@domain.com</code>. If they are configuring their account at the electricity provider, they can use an address like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">energy@domain.com</code> or just <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">company@domain.com</code>. That way if they start receiving spam to the e-mail address they shared with that specific company only, they can be certain their address got leaked by the company.</p>

<p>When I finally enabled <em>catch-all</em> for my e-mail domain I decided to wait for few weeks before I would start changing e-mail addresses associated with each of my two hundred accounts to a unique one, clearly identifying the company or its service. Since I had no previous experience with <em>catch-all</em>, I was wary to observe any potential adverse effects of enabling that option. And indeed, once <em>catch-all</em> became active, I started receiving even <em>more</em> spam than before!</p>

<p>Initially, I was bewildered by that change. After all, I enabled that option to increase my privacy and reduce the usage of my primary e-mail address in places where it is not necessary. But quick analysis of new spam messages that started appearing after <em>catch-all</em> was turned on revealed that those were advertisements sent to some most common pre-defined e-mail addresses, like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">contact@domain.com</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">info@domain.com</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">office@domain.com</code> and so on. I did not see that spam previously because I simply did not have such addresses created in the first place, therefore the e-mail server kept rejecting those messages, since they could not be delivered to a non-existent e-mail address. But enabling <em>catch-all</em> changed server’s response in a way that any e-mail sent to a non-existent address would be forwarded to my main e-mail account (after all, that is what <em>catch-all</em> is all about). That resulted in an increased volume of spam that reached my inbox.</p>

<p>Perhaps spam filters of my e-mail provider would have eventually caught up with the new spam making its way into my inbox, but since those messages had not been reaching me before, my personal filter was not trained to block them effectively. After few weeks I have decided that <em>catch-all</em> was more trouble than it was worth and have disabled that option. My inbox instantaneously became cleaner, and few spam messages that still managed to reach my inbox were put in spam folder automatically by the filter.</p>

<p>Perhaps there is a way to set up <em>catch-all</em> in a way that takes into account a list of certain addresses it rejects messages sent to automatically, although it would became <em>catch-some</em> in that circumstances. I have not explored the topic any further but if you have any experience in that regard feel free to <a href="../about">let me know</a>.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 5 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="technology" /><category term="email" /><category term="internet" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been aware of the importance of a proper e-mail configuration and strict privacy for a long time, which is the main reason why I had left Gmail many years ago and migrated to another provider. One of advices I saw in many places on the Internet was to set up a catch-all e-mail domain, to ensure the convenience and privacy when using many accounts in various places online.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The best story is the one you haven’t written yet</title><link href="https://leziak.com/story-you-havent-written/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The best story is the one you haven’t written yet" /><published>2024-01-15T08:44:31+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-15T08:44:31+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/story-you-havent-written</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/story-you-havent-written/"><![CDATA[<p>This simple truth speaks about our innate desire to create, to make something out of nothing, or rather to make something out of countless ideas and concepts floating in our minds. It is trivially easy to conjure some stories, characters or tropes in our heads, but the moment we try to transfer them into a physical world, either as words on paper or bytes in digital memory, they always lose some of their allure. It is a normal if frustrating process.<!--more--></p>

<p>It is important to be aware of the fact that any story will <em>always</em> loose part of its magic when it takes a specific form. After all, stories in our minds are shapeless, <em>limitless</em>. They are always interesting. It is our job, as writers, to try and bring out as much of their original potential  as we can, when we forge them into words, sentences, paragraphs and chapters. It is not an easy task, but a task we are responsible for. Sometimes it is a matter of deciding whether we feel ready to tell a certain story, or maybe we need to save it for another time. When stories live in our minds they are boundless, they can be anything anywhere. But once we write them down, they will never transform into something new. That finality can be intimidating — it certainly is for me.</p>

<p>Still, I am ready to share my stories knowing that I will not be able to convey everything I had hoped for. But I will be able to convey enough, and knowing that with each story written, my skills will improve and allow me to write better. <a href="../writing-resolutions/">Practice and perseverance goes a long way.</a></p>

<p><em>This is article no. 4 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="writing" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This simple truth speaks about our innate desire to create, to make something out of nothing, or rather to make something out of countless ideas and concepts floating in our minds. It is trivially easy to conjure some stories, characters or tropes in our heads, but the moment we try to transfer them into a physical world, either as words on paper or bytes in digital memory, they always lose some of their allure. It is a normal if frustrating process.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I like paper calendars</title><link href="https://leziak.com/why-i-like-paper-calendars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I like paper calendars" /><published>2024-01-09T07:14:23+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-09T07:14:23+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/paper-calendars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/why-i-like-paper-calendars/"><![CDATA[<p>Despite my love for technology, there are certain aspects of life in which I prefer more analogue or traditional approach. One of them is managing my schedules, for which I use a traditional paper calendar.<!--more--></p>

<p>For the past four years I have been using National Geographic desk calendars. They came in a form of a hardcover stitch-bound book with golden page edges and a textile bookmark. I appreciated their elegance and beauty, and I loved how each week was accompanied by a photograph with a brief description, often showing some interesting places at the opposite side of the globe. I had been writing down all my appointments, meetings and any time-related tasks in that calendar, creating a comprehensive schedule for both professional and private aspects of my life. I realised some time ago that such an approach really works for me. In 2020 I decided to conduct an experiment in the form of Year of Analogue — that is, making sure I prioritise the use of traditional and analogue techniques over their modern counterparts. As a result, for a year I was using a paper calendar instead of the Calendar app on my phone. What I discovered was, it actually made me more productive to use a traditional form of writing down important time-related informations instead of relying on Apple Calendar. It might be counterintuitive at first, but it turned out that writing down details of meetings, appointments, projects, etc. improved my memory and ability to analyse, coordinate and compare informations. The sole act of writing down a piece of information activates different regions of brain than the touch typing or dictating the note to a voice assistant. It makes details more memorable and easier to process afterwards.</p>

<p>I have benefited from using a paper calendar for the entire year 2020, and once it was close to an end, I decided to permanently move on to paper calendars as a replacement for the Calendar app. Because I enjoyed using National Geographic calendar so much, I bought the same type for the new year and used it in a similar manner. National Geographic desk calendar had an additional bonus of space designed to write down phone numbers, contact informations, important anniversaries and birthdays. Writing those informations down not only made them easy to recall afterwards, it also served as a backup in case my phone is lost or suffers a catastrophic failure that renders me unable to access informations stored therein. At the beginning of each year I was copying those important informations to a new calendar, which also served as a review: informations no longer needed in the next year were left behind, and new addresses, phone numbers and important dates were added whenever I deemed it necessary. In some way those calendars acted as yearly chronicles, reflecting my friends moving out, some people changing their phone numbers, some contacts being lost and new ones acquired.</p>

<p>On multiple occasions I was happy to keep the old calendars at hand, when I needed to check up some details from the past, like the exact date of a certain meeting or an old address of a friend who moved away. The identical layout of all National Geographic Calendars facilitated retrieving informations quickly and efficiently, while allowing me for some retrospections and reflections on the past. I journal on a semi-regular basis, but often I found some important informations in calendars from past years rather than in my journal. I got into a habit of writing down titles of books, novels and fan fictions I was reading at the time, as well as movies seen in the cinema or concerts attended. Reviewing my activities from two or three years ago was refreshing.</p>

<p>Sadly, 2023 was the last year when National Geographic Calendar was available. There is no version for 2024, so after four years I had to switch to a different brand. Now I use a mountain-themed calendar I got as a Christmas gift. While not as beautiful as National Geographic, it is still a useful tool in my everyday life and I am wondering how much I will like it overall once the full year will have passed. I know for sure that I will not return to digital calendars in the form of an app anytime soon. They are fast and convenient, but they are not as good for helping one retain informations, plus they lack <em>soul</em>. That is why I still predominantly use fountain pens, refilled with bottled ink like in the old days, instead of regular pens. In the modern world, full of quick feedback and ever-present stimuli, using analogue tools and techniques helps one to slow down and can be considered a form of practising mindfulness.</p>

<p>I will continue to use paper calendars as long as I can find one. Perhaps one day i will find the perfect replacement for National Geographic calendars, but even if not — any calendar that allows me to write down important informations will be more useful than a piece of software. There is beauty in simplicity and elegance of the old ways of writing.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 3 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="calendar" /><category term="analogue" /><category term="paper" /><category term="mindfulness" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Despite my love for technology, there are certain aspects of life in which I prefer more analogue or traditional approach. One of them is managing my schedules, for which I use a traditional paper calendar.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hogwarts Legacy: a truly magical experience</title><link href="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-truly-magical-experience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hogwarts Legacy: a truly magical experience" /><published>2024-01-08T13:33:50+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-08T13:33:50+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-first-impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/hogwarts-legacy-truly-magical-experience/"><![CDATA[<p>After almost two years of waiting, I have finally been able to play Hogwarts Legacy on Nintendo Switch. The game was a Christmas gift and it couldn’t have arrived at better time. It was a lovely experience to explore the magic of Hogwarts and feel like I was wandering through the castle’s corridors. <!--more--></p>

<p>I am still at the beginning of my adventure in Hogwarts, having only visited Hogsmeade for the first time, after my first day at school. I have played the game for maybe five, six hours, but it was a fabulous time. Hogwarts Legacy reinvigorated my curiosity and excitement about the magical world of Harry Potter I first encountered as a child many years ago. Developers created an immersive, vibrant world where magic is accessible and attractive. That world made me want to return to the original books by J. K. Rowling and places, events and characters she described.</p>

<p>Although Hogwarts Legacy does not share any characters with Harry Potter series, happening a hundred years prior to the events mentioned in the books, it absolutely shares the same vibe and amazing atmosphere of a magical world hidden from the eyes of muggles. Even the first steps, taken <em>before</em> I started playing the game (that is, creating a Wizarding World account and connecting it to the game, sorting to the right house and choosing my wand) made me want to dive head-first into this universe. As it quickly turned out, the world of wizards and witches, although magical, can be really dangerous, and not every person or creature is friendly. I have learned that lesson before even arriving at Hogwarts.</p>

<p>Many things are still unknown to me regarding the gameplay. After all, I have only begun my adventure in Harry Potter’s world. Nevertheless, I have already fallen in love with this game, and the way it makes me feel like I’m a young boy again, excited about the magic I’m about to discover.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 2 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="hogwartslegacy" /><category term="harrypotter" /><category term="nintendoswitch" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After almost two years of waiting, I have finally been able to play Hogwarts Legacy on Nintendo Switch. The game was a Christmas gift and it couldn’t have arrived at better time. It was a lovely experience to explore the magic of Hogwarts and feel like I was wandering through the castle’s corridors.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">100 Days To Offload: a writing challenge</title><link href="https://leziak.com/100-days-offload/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="100 Days To Offload: a writing challenge" /><published>2024-01-02T13:31:13+01:00</published><updated>2024-01-02T13:31:13+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/100-days-to-offload</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/100-days-offload/"><![CDATA[<p>I have decided to participate in a writing challenge called <a href="https://100daystooffload.com">100 Days To Offload</a>. The challenge is fairy straightforward: to write a hundred articles on a personal blog within a timespan of 365 days. <!--more--> I first read about this challenge on Mastodon and I immediately realised it would be a perfect opportunity to make my personal website more dynamic and to utilise some of ideas for articles I have been putting away for too long.</p>

<p>In the era of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Closed_platform">walled gardens</a> the vast majority of information is shared via closed social media platforms like Facebook, Instagram or <del>Twitter</del> X, where only people having an account are able to access published content. They are virtually always subject to ad targeting and profiling, not to mention giving platform provider some rights to their content, as mentioned in terms of service. It deepens the issue with internet being more and more commercial and dwindling open access to interesting articles, blog entires, photographs produced by private individuals. In the early days of internet people were sharing their knowledge, experience, thoughts and opinions via personal websites, blogs, discussion boards and forums. Readers were usually not required to have an account in order to access entries shared by others. Over the last two decades the landscape of internet has shifted dramatically, which endangers the <a href="../persistence-of-information/">persistence and accessibility of information</a>. This is why initiatives like 100 Days to Offload are needed. They help to enrich the personal, unrestricted and non-commercial part of the internet, the part which is not focused on maximising the engagement to generate profit, but instead relies on authenticity and sharing information with others.</p>

<p>I am curious about how will this challenge go for me. Writing a hundred articles in a year means posting one article every 3.6 days on average. I do not aim at publishing at constant time intervals, though. Depending on what I have to say, I may post daily for some period of time followed by a break. I have an entire year to figure out the optimal solution.</p>

<p><em>This is article no. 1 from the <a href="../tags/100daystooffload/">100 Days To Offload</a> series.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="resolution" /><category term="newyear" /><category term="challenge" /><category term="website" /><category term="internet" /><category term="information" /><category term="ownyourwords" /><category term="100daystooffload" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have decided to participate in a writing challenge called 100 Days To Offload. The challenge is fairy straightforward: to write a hundred articles on a personal blog within a timespan of 365 days.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fallout 76 after two years</title><link href="https://leziak.com/fallout-76-after-two-years/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fallout 76 after two years" /><published>2023-12-20T09:43:10+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-20T09:43:10+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/fallout-76-after-two-years</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/fallout-76-after-two-years/"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been two years since I first ventured into the Appalachian wilderness after leaving Vault 76 in Bethesda’s newest installment in the <em>Fallout</em> series. Those two years were full of adventure, fights, grinding and exploration. Was it worth it? Is Fallout 76 better than Fallout 4? Let’s find out. <!--more--></p>

<p>Those of you who follow this blog reguarly may remember my <a href="../fallout-76-impressions-after-three-months/">first article about Fallout 76</a>, in which I shared my opinions after three months of playing. I was pretty unexperienced in terms of what Fallout 76 had to offer back then, but I already knew that the overall vibe of the game was positive. Has it changed over those two years? Well, both yes and no.</p>

<p>What changed, is my opinion on the end game. Back in March 2022 when I wrote the first article about Fallout 76, I did not experience the actual end game, since I was far from finishing the main quest line. I remember, though, that many players complained in various places (Reddit, Twitter, etc.) about the lack of actual end game and the inability to replay the main quest line once it is concluded. I finished the main quest, culminating in lauching my first nuke, sometime last Summer. I had originally planned to not touch the nukes until I reach level 1000. However, I found myself getting more and more intrigued about the whole process, and since I have accumulated few hundreds nuclear keycards (consummable items required to lauch a nuke), I gave it a shot once I reached level 700.</p>

<p>I had read quite a few guides and articles about launching a nuke in Fallout 76 even before I tried it myself, so I knew what to expect. To be completely honest, I expected it to be <em>more</em> difficult than it actually was. Do not get me wrong, it still is a rather long ordeal, taking approximately 40-ish minutes (if done a proper way; there are numerous glitches that people use to finish the launch in under 10 minutes, but I prefer to play without using glitches). But because I have been using endgame equipment for months now, the challenges of a nuclear silo were not that difficult. The main issue during the first walkthrough the silo was finding the correct locations where to perform some tasks (especially, repairing the mainframe proved to be diffuclt, as I erroneously assumed I needed to repair the mainframe I had previously destroyed to deactivate the defense systems). Luckily, after an hour or so I finally managed to launch my first nuke and trigger the Scorched Earth event.</p>

<p>Ever since, I have launched nukes several times, from different silos in Appalachia (there are three silos: Alpha, Bravo and Charlie, although their internal layout is identical). It turned out to be a refreshing activity, in comparison to all “regular” quests and public events that I know thoroughly. I managed to stay under 40 minutes when fighting my way through the silo. At one point, however, I tried to change tactics and used Chinese Stealth Armour instead, to avoid confrontation whenever possible. It further reduced the time needed to complete the silo by additional 10 minutes or so.</p>

<p>The quests leading to the launch of the first nuke were interesting and diverse. They allowed me to travel through the entire Appalachia and visit locations I haven’t seen in a while. One thing that I skipped, though, was decyphering the launch code. I read a tutorial online and decided that it does not sound like fun. I used codes found at <a href="https://nukacrypt.com">NukaCrypt</a> instead.</p>

<p>Once I finished the main quest line I have entered the actual end game, since there are only few remaining quests, mostly related to previously published expansions, that I need to finish. Despite this fact, I do not feel like there is no end game. The end game itself is whatever one chooses it to be: finishing all side quests, rolling legendary weapons to find a perfect 3-star legendary, roleplaying as a Responder, Fire Breather, member of the Enclave, etc. Fallout 76 is so diverse anyone can find a way of enjoying the game once there are no more quests to do.</p>

<p>Regarding the things that stayed the same for me, those are mainly the standard issues with time gating. Although developers have increased daily limit for scrips (a type of virtual currency obtained for traiding in legenday items one does not want) and every now and then there are events when certain limits are doubled, Fallout 76 remains the game of patience. The upper limit of caps (money) in game remains at 40 000, and one can earn only 1400 each day by selling unwanted goods to an NPC vendor. If that is not enough one can always try to sell items to other players, although it is not guaranteed that anyone will purchase those items. Besides that, one can get small amounts of money by looting bodies or completing quests. But if you want to get rich fast, try some other games.</p>

<p>I must admit that I am no longer bothered by daily limits to the extend I used to during my first months of playing Fallout 76. That is mostly due to already using the best armour, weapons and equipment in the game. I have no incentives to earn more money or roll another legendary weapon, because the weapons that I have are already the best for my build. That’s why in the end game the limits are not as important as during the main playthrough, when one wants to level up fast.</p>

<p>While Fallout 76 is in mature state, it does not mean that the game is left on its own. Every couple of months there is a new season, and with each season there are new cosmetic items, skins and decorations introduced. However, what is more important, developers are regularly adding some small quality of life improvements. It is heartening to see that players’ opinions are heard and taken into account, and that the developers want Fallout 76 to be more user friendly. The newest update, from the beginning of December, brings two new expeditions to the game, together with new enemies and monsters. Unfortunately, it is visible that some of them are only reskinned mobs that were already in the game (they even share some sounds, which should not be the case). Nevertheless, it brings a bit of fresh air into the game.</p>

<p>Overall Fallout 76 is a good game, and while it is not for everyone, I found it pleasant and enjoyable. I like to roam Appalachia mountains and look for adventures in the wilderness and ruins dotting the landscape. After two years I can safely admit that it was a good decision to give this title a shot. I am sure there are many hours of great time awaiting me in Fallout 76.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="fallout" /><category term="fallout76" /><category term="onlinegames" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s been two years since I first ventured into the Appalachian wilderness after leaving Vault 76 in Bethesda’s newest installment in the Fallout series. Those two years were full of adventure, fights, grinding and exploration. Was it worth it? Is Fallout 76 better than Fallout 4? Let’s find out.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Freewrite Traveler — first impressions</title><link href="https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-first-impressions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Freewrite Traveler — first impressions" /><published>2023-12-12T08:34:43+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-12T08:34:43+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-first-impressions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/freewrite-traveler-first-impressions/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I have bought a Freewrite Traveler, a portable distraction-free writing device with an e-Ink screen. Here are my first impressions regarding that purchase. <!--more--></p>

<p>The initial configuration on the device itself was simple and straightforward. However, I have encountered problem when trying to set up a Postbox account, which is necessary to unlock the true potential of Traveler. There was simply… no option to create a new account on a Postbox main page! I had to switch to Springer, a website distraction-free interface, and only there, when I clicked on a status bar at the bottom of the screen, I was able to see an option to sign up to Postbox. It definitely was <strong>not</strong> an easy feat, and this is something that Astrohaus could definitely improve.</p>

<p>Nonetheless, the rest of the configuration process was fast and easy. It took me about a minute to connect to my home Wi-Fi and log into Postbox. Not to mention that one can start writing on the device immediately after the booting up is complete. Postbox, while enhancing the functionality of Traveler, is absolutely not necessary to use it.</p>

<p>One of my biggest concerns before I got Traveler was the quality of its keyboard. Unlike the Smart Typewriter, Traveler lacks mechanical keyboard and uses scissor-switch keyboard, which is standard for middle and upper tier laptops. The keyboard is honestly not that bad. While it is not as good as a mechanical one (I use Keychron Q3 Pro as my daily driver), it is more comfortable than my MacBook Air, mostly due to fairy deep key travel, significantly improved over standard scissor-switch keys. Naturally, I cannot say how the keyboard performs in the long run just yet, but my first impressions are surprisingly positive. The only thing that could further improve Traveler’s keyboard (save for using low-profile mechanical switches, of course), is the option for purchasing a device equipped with ISO layout, which is pretty standard in Europe, yet practically unheard of in the USA. I got accustomed to an inverted L return key and I miss it a bit in Traveler. Yet I do understand why Astrohaus abandoned the idea of selling two versions of device with different keyboard layout after the second generation of Smart Typewriter (which one could purchase with ISO keys). It is simply cheaper to develop one version of hardware.</p>

<p>When it comes to an e-Ink screen, watching countless YouTube videos about Traveler I was afraid it would be too small for my liking (at least that is how it looked in many reviews). I was surprised to find it a perfect size for Traveler’s form factor. It gives me enough space to not feel claustrophobic and at the same time it does not distract me with too much of the previous text visible. One of the first things I changed in Traveler’s settings was font size, of which I picked the smallest. It makes approximately two paragraphs visible on the screen, which is absolutely enough to not get lost in the general flow of my thoughts. The clarity of the e-Ink display is superb. For someone who spends most of the time staring into backlighted displays, an e-Ink screen brings much needed rest for the eyes. As for the lack of front light that Smart Typewriter has, it turned out to be not as much of a hinderance as I expected. Because I always write while sitting at a desk or table of some sort, I can use the overhead light or a desk lamp. I have also bought a small book lamp with adjustable brightness, which works perfectly with Traveler.</p>

<p>I know that many people find the delay of the e-Ink screen distracting. I understand why it can be an issue, especially for touch typists. The delay between pressing a key and letter appearing on the screen is in the range of 0.5-0.7 second. For me it is perfectly acceptable, since I do not look at the screen when typing, and once I finish writing a sentence and look at the screen, it just about finishes updating. One should keep in mind that many people noticed increased lag as their documents are getting longer, so I will have to update my review once I reach that state. Still, I do not expect screen delay to be an issue for people who do not touch type.</p>

<p>The overall build quality is pretty good, although not perfect. My device has few rough edges where the white plastic meets the black one in the upper lid, and I have seen in few reviews that people have similar issues in other places. It is only noticeable when I look for it, though, and I do not care all that much. As a portable writing machine I expect to take Traveler in many places where it could get scratched or worse. I will let you know after a couple of weeks or months how it is holding up. One comestic thing that bothers me <em>just a little bit</em> is the way the label <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">new</code> is printed on two red keys at the bottom of the keyboard. I have noticed that already in a couple of other users’ photographs that the print on the red keys is a bit fuzzy and not as crisp as on the white ones. From up close I can confirm that this is true. The labels on <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">new</code> keys seem to be printed in a different technique or with a different paint than the rest, which gives the text a bit more glossy, yet unsharp, look. Since I have only been using Traveler for an hour or so, I cannot comment on the durability of the labels, but again, I will get back to that topic after a longer period of using Traveler extensively.</p>

<p>One thing is certain, though: it <strong>does</strong> help one write faster. Without distractions of my computer or iPad I am 100% focused on <em>what</em> I am writing and <em>how</em> I am writing it. Because there is no web browser, no e-mail, no apps with notifications, nothing bothers me when I pour words onto digital paper. Interestingly, when I got some notification on my phone lying nearby I instinctively chose to ignore it, as if I knew at subconscious level that this is the time for writing and writing only. I did not extend such restraint when working in a text editor on a computer or tablet. It is still too early to say whether this positive effect will persist, and whether I will actually improve my productivity in the long run, but looking at how I enjoy this device, I am optimistic.</p>

<p>There are still many things I need to learn about Traveler, and the more I will use it the more refined my opinion will be. For now, I am happy about my purchase and I believe there are many joys of writing awaiting me.</p>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="freewrite" /><category term="eink" /><category term="keyboard" /><category term="typewriting" /><category term="hardware" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently I have bought a Freewrite Traveler, a portable distraction-free writing device with an e-Ink screen. Here are my first impressions regarding that purchase.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In the search of a perfect writing setup</title><link href="https://leziak.com/perfect-writing-setup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In the search of a perfect writing setup" /><published>2023-11-14T14:20:03+01:00</published><updated>2023-11-14T14:20:03+01:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/search-perfect-writing-setup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/perfect-writing-setup/"><![CDATA[<p>I have been looking for a way to optimise my writing workflow and find a perfect setup for many years. I have tried numerous solutions, both software (word processors, markdown editors, notepads) and hardware-related (keyboards in almost every shape and form). The more I looked for a perfect setup the more I doubted it had ever existed. Experimenting, however, brought me an immense joy, even if paired with a bit of frustration at times.<!--more--></p>

<p>I have always appreciated writing. It is a truly fascinating process, in which one can immortalise their thoughts, opinions and memories. I have learned more about myself by reading my old journals than through any other form of retrospection. But for me the act of writing is strongly affected by technical aspects and the smoothness of the overall experience. That is why I write a lot by hand, and use fountain pens on a daily basis. I care about the details of the process, as they can help me to immerse myself in the story I am telling without any external disruptions. That is why the quality of the writing workflow and specifics of the writing setup are so important to me.</p>

<p>For handwriting, I have already found the perfect solution<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>: a combination of a comfortable fountain pen with an excellent nib, good quality ink and acid-free paper. My daily driver is <strong>Aurora Talentum GT</strong>, currently paired with <strong>Aurora 100th Year Special Edition Gray</strong> ink and <strong>Leuchtturm 1917</strong> notebook.</p>

<p>For typewriting, I have tried many solutions. It is relatively easy to find a good stationary setup. If one has no intention to move the hardware very often (or at all), a good mechanical keyboard with a high resolution monitor can be paired with a multitude of devices, from a regular PC, through a Mac, to a tablet or similar device. Having a dedicated space for a stationary setup means that one can invest in hardware that is optimised in terms of ergonomy and usability. An excellent solution would be a second, e-ink computer screen, used solely for writing, although they are hard to come by and pretty expensive (one of the best examples is <a href="https://onyxboox.com/boox_mira">Onyx Boox Mira</a>). I would love to use it as a dedicated computer screen for writing, yet I cannot justify such expense.</p>

<p>E-ink screens are superior to regular LCD or LED ones, due to lack of a backlight and eye strain that comes with it. They have also excellent readability in the sunlight, which may not be a top priority for a stationary setup, but is a huge factor for a mobile writing station. There have been a few projects trying to use the advantage of an e-ink screen in a portable writing device, with mixed results.</p>

<p>One of the most notable examples is the Freewrite Smart Typewriter, produced by Astrohaus. I <a href="../freewrite/">wrote about Freewrite back in 2016</a>, when the first generation was available for purchase. The device combines a mechanical keyboard with an e-ink screen and some basic sync functions in order to deliver a distraction-free typing experience. Currently Astrohaus sells the third generation of the Freewrite, which, while virtually identical to its predecessor in terms of visuals, offers certain software enhancements. The synchronisation feature is also more developed, allowing for wireless sharing of the draft to Google Drive, e-mail or Postbox (Astrohaus’ proprietary cloud service). I must admit that I was seriously considering buying the newest generation of the Freewrite Smart Typewriter (they also sell a portable device called Freewrite Traveler, but it lacks mechanical keyboard and the screen, while still e-ink, misses the built-in illumination).</p>

<p>There is a viable alternative for people looking for a mobile e-ink device suitable for writing: Remarkable 2. It is an e-ink tablet which allows for the creation of handwritten notes, offers handwriting OCR for many languages, PDF annotations and more. Some time ago a Remarkable Type Folio premiered, an external keyboard in a form of a folio cover. It allows one to use Remarkable as an e-ink typewriter. Although Remarkable Type Folio does not have a mechanical keyboard, it still offers a portable writing solution with an e-ink screen free of backlight-induced eye strain. It lacks illumination, just like Smartwrite Traveller, so is not usable in a dark without access to an external light source. Unfortunately, the Remarkable Type Folio supports only a handful of keyboard layouts, with the vast majority of European languages missing. It means that one cannot enter language-specific diacritics, which sadly is a deal-breaker for me. Although I write most of my essays in English, I want to retain the option to write in Polish if necessary.</p>

<p>This is almost as far as the e-ink options go, both Freewrite and Remarkable do not have competition in their respective categories<sup id="fnref:fn2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. It is a shame, thought, because I believe users could benefit greatly from innovation and price drop forced by competition in the market. Nevertheless, both devices serve a niche purpose, and there is not much demand for an e-ink typewriter or word processor in general. Most people are okay with starring at backlit LCD or OLED screens and are probably not even aware of benefits of the electronic paper.</p>

<p>My current option for writing on the go is an 11-inch iPad Pro with Paperlike screen protector and Logitech Folio Touch. It does not offer full benefits of an e-ink screen, but it does reduce glare and resultant eye-strain. I have been a fan of writing on iPad from the beginning. I used the original Smart Keyboard Folio for 2018 iPad Pro, but sadly the quality of that thing was abysmal. I had Smart Keyboard Folio break down on me after a year and a half, and its replacement followed the same course. After that I decided to make an exception and <em>not</em> buy Apple’s Magic Keyboard for the new 2020 iPad Pro, mostly because I was still wary of all the issues with their folio keyboard. Plus, the price of that accessory, even for the 11-inch model, was eye-watering (in fact, it still is). Since my iPad Pro from 2020 does not support some new functions like Stage Manager on external display, I decided to keep it for as long as possible, and only buy Magic Keyboard for the new model, once I decide it is time to upgrade. And since the current model has been working like a charm for four years now, it might not happen anytime soon.</p>

<p>I am thinking about experimenting with an external mechanical keyboard connected to an e-ink tablet working on Android, or to a Raspberry Pi connected to an e-ink display. The first solution would be trivially easy to implement, but also quite expensive (e-ink tablets, especially ones with a colour screen, still cost a lot), while the second one would allow me to save some money but for the price of time taken to make everything work well together. For now, I continue to use my iPad Pro, hoping that one day I will find that elusive perfect writing setup.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>It should be noted, naturally, that what is the perfect solution for <em>me</em> may not necessarily be the perfect solution for anyone else. I am not trying to arbitrary push my setup as the best option here, but merely to show you one of many possibilities. <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>People often compare Remarkable 2 and Kindle Scribe in general, but for the purpose of typewriting Kindle is useless, as it does not support any external keyboards. <a href="#fnref:fn2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="technology" /><category term="freewrite" /><category term="remarkable" /><category term="eink" /><category term="keyboard" /><category term="typewriting" /><category term="hardware" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been looking for a way to optimise my writing workflow and find a perfect setup for many years. I have tried numerous solutions, both software (word processors, markdown editors, notepads) and hardware-related (keyboards in almost every shape and form). The more I looked for a perfect setup the more I doubted it had ever existed. Experimenting, however, brought me an immense joy, even if paired with a bit of frustration at times.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I made a Pixelfed account</title><link href="https://leziak.com/pixelfed-account/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I made a Pixelfed account" /><published>2023-08-08T12:56:24+02:00</published><updated>2023-08-08T12:56:24+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/pixelfed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/pixelfed-account/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I’ve created a <a href="https://pixelfed.social/vertiser">Pixelfed</a> account to share my everyday and casual photographs online. <!--more--> I had deleted my Instagram account a couple of years ago and I’ve been trying various replacements since. While Instagram inarguably has the largest user base, it also has serious privacy issues, as it (or actually Meta, the parent company of Instagram and Facebook) collects tremendous amount of data about its users, their devices, location, habits, interests and multitude of other things. All this for a single purpose: to serve users the most effective ads possible.</p>

<p>I abhor Meta’s dubious ethics, therefore I was looking for Instagram alternative. I’ve tried various services, of which <a href="https://www.vsco.co">VSCO</a> briefly captured my attention. Ultimately I was discouraged by the recurring subscription cost and the fact that it felt very hermetic and monotonous. With the increased popularity of federated social media I started to publish photographs on my <a href="https://mastodon.social/@vertiser">Mastodon</a> first<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, but it didn’t feel like an optimal solution. I considered creating a separated account in federated social media specialised in sharing photographs, namely Pixelfed. That thought stayed with me for a couple of months, but only at the end of July I finally took the step to create an account and upload my first photographs.</p>

<p>The whole experience has been positive so far and I intend to keep my Pixelfed profile. As for its content, it will be similar to VSCO and, previously, Instagram: casual, everyday photographs, occasionally mixed with some travel shots. If you are looking for some thematically consistent series of fine art photographs, feel free to check out the <a href="https://www.deviantart.com/vertiser/gallery/71989994/photographs">Photography gallery on my deviantART profile</a>. DeviantART is still the main place where I publish more sophisticated works.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I had an account since 2018, but I hardly posted anything until I started seriously considering leaving Twitter in 2022) <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="photography" /><category term="technology" /><category term="pixelfed" /><category term="socialmedia" /><category term="vsco" /><category term="federated" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently I’ve created a Pixelfed account to share my everyday and casual photographs online.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I will play every game I own</title><link href="https://leziak.com/play-all-games/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I will play every game I own" /><published>2023-07-17T11:15:09+02:00</published><updated>2023-07-17T11:15:09+02:00</updated><id>https://leziak.com/play-all-games</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://leziak.com/play-all-games/"><![CDATA[<p>If you are a gamer, you probably have a long list of titles in your library, and chances are, you have not played all of those games. Thanks to spontaneous purchases, Steam Summer Sales, Black Friday offers, etc. we tend to accumulate more and more games at attractive prices. ‘It was a bargain, and I wanted to play this game anyway’ one may justify their purchase to themselves (<em>I</em> do quite often, actually). In the end many of those games never see the proverbial light of day, and they stay on shelves of our digital libraries, collecting virtual dust. <!--more--></p>

<p>During my decades of gaming I realised that, most of the time, I prefer to replay known titles rather than to try out something new. I have certain favourites that have a permanent place in my heart, like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gothic_(video_game)">Gothic</a>, Skyrim, The Witcher series, and I like to get back to them whenever I can. But the problem arising from this attitude is, I rarely try something new. Buying Nintendo Switch in 2019 has partially alleviated the issue, allowing me to try many new games, especially when travelling. But it has not solved the problem with many titles staying in my library, never even installed, or only opened briefly for a couple of minutes. At some point I decided to change that, so I created the <a href="../all-games/">All Games</a> project.</p>

<p><strong><a href="../all-games/">The All Games</a> project is my attempt at playing every single game I have in my gaming library (or <em>all</em> my gaming libraries, to be precise).</strong> I have an intention to play every game on my many accounts: Steam, GOG, Origin, as well as standalone games I bought digitally or physically over the years. The goal is, to actually experience all the games I own. So I do not want to only open them, finish the first chapter, mission or quest and be done with it, but get involved with the core aspect of each game. This rule does not specify that I must have a 100% completion of all games<sup id="fnref:fn1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:fn1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, nor that I need to get all of the game’s achievements/trophies on a respective platform. I do not need to finish the main storyline or quest, but I must engage in each game. For certain games I may add my own goals or achievements that I want to get. Once I obtain them all, I will consider game fully completed from my point of view.</p>

<p>Should I inevitably buy some new games along the way, they will be added to the goal; they will affect the progression and count towards the total number of games to play. Both the list of the games and the progression will be updated regularly. Naturally, games that I had already played and completed will be included in the list. I have no incentive to do things that I do not like in my free time, so if there is a game that displeasures me, I will abandon it at certain point, but not before making several attempts to discover some likeable aspects.</p>

<p>There is no specific timeframe or a deadline for the whole endeavour. I treat it as an ongoing personal project, a way of making sure I fully utilise the entertainment potential of games I already own. <a href="../all-games/">The progress page</a> will be updated regularly, to reflect the current status of the project.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>as a matter of fact, it would be impossible, since many games do not have a measurable progress or completion <a href="#fnref:fn1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Kamil Leziak</name></author><category term="games" /><category term="project" /><category term="games" /><category term="onlinegames" /><category term="gothic" /><category term="allgames" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you are a gamer, you probably have a long list of titles in your library, and chances are, you have not played all of those games. Thanks to spontaneous purchases, Steam Summer Sales, Black Friday offers, etc. we tend to accumulate more and more games at attractive prices. ‘It was a bargain, and I wanted to play this game anyway’ one may justify their purchase to themselves (I do quite often, actually). In the end many of those games never see the proverbial light of day, and they stay on shelves of our digital libraries, collecting virtual dust.]]></summary></entry></feed>